<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>airbnb | Tom Slee</title>
    <link>/tag/airbnb/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/airbnb/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>airbnb</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2016 01:01:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>airbnb</title>
      <link>/tag/airbnb/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Why is Airbnb offering a bonus for new hosts in Vancouver?		</title>
      <link>/post/why-is-airbnb-offering-a-bonus-for-new-hosts-in-vancouver/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2016 01:01:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/why-is-airbnb-offering-a-bonus-for-new-hosts-in-vancouver/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;            Here&#39;s an odd thing. Airbnb has a [new program in Vancouver](http://blog.airbnb.com/yvrdeals/), offering $250 cash bonus for first-time hosts. It&#39;s odd for two reasons. First, the company has been under pressure for exacerbating the city&#39;s housing affordability crisis (Vancouver&#39;s housing market is [the most expensive in North America](http://globalnews.ca/news/2477598/vancouver-ranked-3rd-least-affordable-housing-market-in-the-world-survey/)), so this looks like asking for more trouble. Second, Airbnb in Vancouver is already going gangbusters, so why does Airbnb feel the need to pay out to attract new hosts?
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a chart that shows what I mean by &amp;ldquo;gangbusters&amp;rdquo;. The y axis is the total reviews per month for a set of North American cities, with Vancouver picked out in bold red. The total number of visits is probably about one-and-a-half times this number, so it&amp;rsquo;s a measure of overall Airbnb traffic in the city. You can see there is a seasonal trend, with traffic dropping off over winter and picking up again in summer, but it&amp;rsquo;s pretty clear that this summer&amp;rsquo;s peak is well above last summer for most of these cities. Vancouver is now running at well over twice the volume of last year. (Click to expand, and hit the back button to return to the post)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://whimsley.s3.amazonaws.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/vancouver_11.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://whimsley.s3.amazonaws.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/vancouver_11.png&#34; alt=&#34;vancouver_1&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;But there&amp;rsquo;s another way of looking at this growth. Vancouver is again highlighted in bold red in the chart below, which unpacks the overall traffic shown above. The x axis is the number of listings in the city, and the y axis is the average occupancy rate measured as the number of reviews per month per listing. Multiply them together and you get the total traffic for the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most cities the trend is to more listings, with the occupancy rate going through the same seasonal trend we saw up above. (Although Philadelphia and Chicago are not doing so great, and San Francisco (the curly green line) seems to have hit a limit of listings, probably because of the drastic action Airbnb is taking to legitimize itself in that city. But that&amp;rsquo;s another story.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://whimsley.s3.amazonaws.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/vancouver_2.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://whimsley.s3.amazonaws.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/vancouver_2.png&#34; alt=&#34;vancouver_2&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An increase in traffic can come about two ways: more listings, or higher occupancy, and there&amp;rsquo;s a bit of a trade-off between the two. So Toronto and Montreal (yellow and brown) have seen a rapid growth in the number of listings and the occupancy rate has grown significantly, but not massively. Meanwhile Vancouver has not seen such a rapid growth in the number of listings, but the occupancy rate is growing like topsy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if a hotel was counted as a single listing it would be way to the top left of this chart, while Airbnb wants to claim that its hosts are only occasionally renting out the place in which they live &amp;ndash; which translates into the bottom right. The fact that Vancouver listings are getting used more often could be bad news for Airbnb in its battle for legitimacy, so if it can attract more hosts they may take up some of the slack and move the line out to the right and down a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To step back a bit, you do have to wonder if &amp;ldquo;bottom right&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;top left&amp;rdquo; makes much of a difference from the actual affordability and neighbourhood impact perspective. If you live in an apartment building and every other person rents out their place once a month, that&amp;rsquo;s the same impact in terms of traffic, extra utilities and the other things people complain about than a small number of people renting out their places all the time. And thousands of tourists staying in a small neighbourhood will have a similar impact (good and bad) in some ways if they are scattered across many listings or huddled together in a few. And what about the impact on house prices in high-traffic hotspots? It&amp;rsquo;s not obvious to me that a large number of low-occupancy listings has less of an impact than a small number of high-occupancy listings, though I could be convinced either way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I feel pretty confident that Airbnb is making its offer to offset the bad image that goes with the high-occupancy rates that Vancouver is now experiencing. And if there&amp;rsquo;s an offer for Seattle hosts, well that will confirm my suspicions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; Thanks to Caroline O&amp;rsquo;Donovan for pointing me to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/TheMountaineers/photos/a.390506682724.166603.137083717724/10153981442407725/?type=3&amp;amp;theater&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;: an Airbnb host promotion in Seattle. Suspicions confirmed!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Airbnb in Barcelona: two readings		</title>
      <link>/post/airbnb-in-barcelona-two-readings/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2016 18:35:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/airbnb-in-barcelona-two-readings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;            A story on Ada Colau, who [may be the world&#39;s most radical mayor](http://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/may/26/ada-colau-barcelona-most-radical-mayor-in-the-world), hjighlighte how Airbnb can create problems for the cities where it operates:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Colau’s stated priority is to move Barcelona away from what she considers “massified tourism”, with no thought for sustainability, strategic planning or input from the public. “Until now, all we have had were private initiatives doing what they wanted,” Colau told me. “This has led to a model that is out of control.” She added: “We suffered the same short-sighted model here with the real estate bubble. We are trying to prevent the same mistakes happening again with tourism.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a detailed look behind the scenes, Albert Arias Sans and Alan Quaglieri have a new paper called &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.academia.edu/24653298/Unravelling_Airbnb_Urban_Perspectives_from_Barcelona&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Unravelling Airbnb: Urban Perspectives from Barcelona&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; (sadly, login required). They investigate the claims made in Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;reports&amp;rdquo; on the city and show each of them to be false:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb claim: The vast majority of Airbnb accommodation is located outside the areas with major concentrations of hotels.
Arias/Quaglieri: There is a strong correlation between Airbnb listings and the presence of hotels. Airbnb supply is located to a large extent in the same neighbourhoods as hotels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb claim: Airbnb focuses on a new type of traveller seeking the authentic to immerse themselves in other cultures.
Arias/Quaglieri: Analyzing languages spoken by hosts: the composition of the Airbnb host community is different from the profile of the area as a whole. Airbnb appears as a field for the ‘cosmopolitan consuming class’, where hosts and guests share a similar approach to the city around a ‘cosmopolitan sense of local’ from which a large proportion of the rest of the residents of Barcelona are excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb: proceeds from Airbnb allow hosts to cover their basic expenses and reach the end of the month
Arias/Quaglieri: Airbnb hosts are not representative of the local communities. They are far more educated, have fewer children, and live in less-crowded households. While Airbnb hosting may help solve the prolems of people living in middle- to upper-class neighbourhoods, it is not a resource open to those in the poorer neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A really interesting read, which is a significant step forward in the debate about Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s impact on the major tourist centres.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Airbnb&#39;s business in New York City		</title>
      <link>/post/airbnbs-business-in-new-york-city/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2015 02:10:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/airbnbs-business-in-new-york-city/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;            [According to the New York Times](http://www.nytimes.com/2015/12/02/technology/airbnb-releases-trove-of-new-york-city-home-sharing-data.html), Airbnb yesterday &amp;quot;released&amp;quot; data about their business in New York City. As I first reported on Airbnb in New York [two years ago](http://tomslee.net/2013/11/airbnb-business-in-new-york-revisited.html), when that business was a lot smaller, I was interested. Airbnb&#39;s Chris Lehane says &amp;quot;Our hope is that people will understand 99 percent of people on Airbnb in [New York City](http://topics.nytimes.com/top/classifieds/realestate/locations/newyork/newyorkcity/manhattan/?inline=nyt-geo) are using it as an economic lifeline,” and who could object to that? Would the real numbers show that we critics are wrong?
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My work has been based on scrapes of the Airbnb web site (now done better by Murray Cox at &lt;a href=&#34;http://insideairbnb.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Inside Airbnb&lt;/a&gt;), so it&amp;rsquo;s necessarily less accurate than Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s own data. On the other hand, I don&amp;rsquo;t have a $25 billion market valuation at stake in the answer, so it may be easier for me to be honest in my reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hoped that &amp;ldquo;released&amp;rdquo; meant that I could get the data, but I was quickly disillusioned. It turns out to mean &amp;ldquo;made available only by making an appointment to visit Airbnb’s New York City office&amp;rdquo;, which is a bit of a joke. Instead, all we get is the summary statements from Airbnb PR. Still, it is better than nothing. So I read on&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first response to the New York Times article was dismay at this statement: &amp;ldquo;From November 2014 until November 2015, some 93 percent of revenue earned by active hosts in New York City who share their entire home came from people who have only one or two rental listings on the platform&amp;rdquo;. That is a number far higher than I had seen, and suggests that a much bigger portion of the Airbnb business is their archetypal &amp;ldquo;regular New Yorkers occasionally renting out the home in which they live&amp;rdquo; than I had thought. I had reported about 40% of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business coming from people with more than one rental listing and the numbers suggested 20% of business coming from people with more than two listings. Have I and other critics been getting it wrong? In the absence of complete data we have to make some estimates about income after all. This would be unfortunate as I have just &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orbooks.com/catalog/whats-yours-is-mine-by-tom-slee/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PUBLISHED A BOOK ABOUT THE SHARING ECONOMY THAT MAKES A GREAT CHRISTMAS PRESENT&lt;/a&gt; and that is critical of Airbnb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But today the New York Times ran a correction: &amp;ldquo;From November 2014 until November 2015, some **75 percent **of revenue earned by active hosts in New York City who share their entire home came from people who have only one or two rental listings on the platform.&amp;rdquo;  (my emphasis). The change from 93% to 75% is significant: that&amp;rsquo;s almost four-fold increase in the proportion that comes from three-or-more listers. All of a sudden the Airbnb numbers look much more like those collected by myself and other external investigators, which Airbnb routinely say are inaccurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what&amp;rsquo;s the real picture? Yes, 25% of Airbnb revenue in NYC comes from people renting out &amp;ldquo;more than two&amp;rdquo; listings. My own estimate actually comes out &lt;em&gt;below&lt;/em&gt; that at 20% so my estimates are more friendly to Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;regular people&amp;rdquo; pitch than reality. My numbers also show that about 40% of total revenue comes from people with more than one listing, which is just what I reported two years ago. It&amp;rsquo;s likely that the real number is closer to half, given the way my estimates seem to underestimate revenue from &amp;ldquo;more than three&amp;rdquo; listers. In short, far from showing that the critics were wrong, Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s numbers show that our data, which they have been rubbishing, is pretty good and even generous to them: their numbers suggest that even more of the business comes from multiple listers than we have been claiming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&amp;rsquo;s the right way to say it. &amp;ldquo;From November 2014 to November 2015, about half of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s revenue in New York City comes from multiple-listing hosts. Hosts with three or more listings contribute 25% of the total.&amp;rdquo; That&amp;rsquo;s a much more commercially-focused operation than the original claim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 93% number that Airbnb gave is, by the way, their projection on next year&amp;rsquo;s figures, to  which I can only say - if you&amp;rsquo;re going to release data, maybe talk about the data and not about your dreams and aspirations? So far their supposed efforts to clamp down on hosts with many listings have been half hearted, and given that it may cut into their revenues we should not give it a lot of credibility. Airbnb has been talking the talk a long time about this challenge on their site, and yet so far they have done basically nothing about it (I&amp;rsquo;m travelling and don&amp;rsquo;t have access to the full data set at the moment, or I&amp;rsquo;d show you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe more on this later. But for now, the new Airbnb numbers do nothing to undermine the critics&#39; case.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				A few updates		</title>
      <link>/post/a-few-updates/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 08:16:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/a-few-updates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;            I&#39;ve completed my book manuscript, and it&#39;s time to return to blogging. I&#39;m going to change things a bit. Mostly until now I&#39;ve done fairly long-form essays every now and again, but I&#39;m going to try going more frequent and more links than original stuff (so if you get the emails you may want to click that Unsubscribe button). I don&#39;t think there is a place that aggregates Sharing Economy events and commentary, so I&#39;m going to try that for a while.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start off, here are three interesting pieces. All links open in a new tab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The indefatigable Ellen Huet &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.forbes.com/sites/ellenhuet/2015/09/11/uber-raises-uberx-commission-to-25-percent-in-five-more-markets/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;highlights&lt;/a&gt; Uber&amp;rsquo;s continual efforts to raise its take of each ride: it has now raised its commission to 25% in five more cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;In the last few months, Uber has quietly bumped up commissions from 20% to 25% for new drivers in five cities. New York City drivers who joined as of April will pay 25%, as well as drivers in Toronto, Indianapolis, Boston  and Worcester, Mass., who joined as of August, the company confirmed.
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;San Francisco drivers who joined in the last year still pay a 25% commission. An Uber spokeswoman declined to say whether the 30% commission pilot program has spread to more drivers or markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping the higher commission to recent drivers doesn’t actually limit its impact very much. Uber’s workforce is constantly churning and growing: In January, an Uber-conducted study showed &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.forbes.com/sites/ellenhuet/2015/01/22/uber-study-workforce/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a quarter of its active drivers had joined in the last month&lt;/a&gt;. It’s unclear if raising the commission deters new drivers from signing up, but if the policy has spread from its first test city, it suggests it makes economic sense.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The churn among Uber&amp;rsquo;s drivers matches that in Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s hosts: new people try it out, and a lot decide it&amp;rsquo;s not for them. You would think that the more Uber takes from each ride, the weaker its claims that it is not responsible (just a technology company) when things go wrong, but it looks like they are confident they can take more money without taking on more risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ilya Marritz in WNYC news &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wnyc.org/story/when-inspectors-look-illegal-hotels/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt; on city inspectors chasing down potential illegal rentals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;WNYC has obtained detailed records from a year and a half of inspections. Here’s what we learned by reading through all 2,684 reports.
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;from October 2013 through April 2015, the city received 1,616 complaints about illegal hotels. In the same period, inspectors made 2,684 visits looking for rentals that violate local laws&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Airbnb is responsible for most, it surprises me how many reports are from non-Airbnb listings. In particular, Priceline has more than HomeAway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Airbnb - 101
Booking.com (owned by Priceline)– 40
Portobello Suites – 11
VRBO (owned by HomeAway)– 11
Homeaway.com – 10
Tripadvisor - 5
Agoda (owned by Priceline)– 3
Expedia – 3&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do wish she had given us more of the report details, but there are some gems there, like this one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Unidentified Woman Opened Door And After Saying She Did Not Live There Attempted To Slam Door On Identified Police Officer. Woman In Back Screamed To Her Dont Let Them In. Male Came And Id Self As Owner Of Multiple Apts And Said We Should Be Going After Real Criminals Not What They Are Doing.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				What&#39;s going on with Airbnb in LA?		</title>
      <link>/post/whats-going-on-with-airbnb-in-la/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2015 05:08:22 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/whats-going-on-with-airbnb-in-la/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;            Today&#39;s LA Times says &amp;quot;[Airbnb cuts ties with vacation-rental firms in Los Angeles](http://www.latimes.com/business/la-fi-airbnb-rift-20150404-story.html)&amp;quot;. The story says that &amp;quot;Two of the home-sharing giant&#39;s largest Los Angeles-area hosts—vacation-rental firms with dozens of apartments apiece—said Friday that Airbnb had dropped them from its site this week, canceling upcoming bookings and scrubbing their listings.&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Airbnb rep called one of the affected landlords (AE Hospitality) and &amp;ldquo;mentioned the growth plans of Airbnb conflicts with us listing on their website… No explicit reason was given.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got a call from Tim Logan, one of the reporters on the story, asking if I could see anything going on, and was able to take a quick look and (at that time) it looked like 10 of the top 13 hosts (in terms of number of listings) were completely removed from the site, and I&amp;rsquo;m quoted in the story with that figure. Now I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to take a more complete look and can say a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two questions, of course. One is &amp;ldquo;What is happening?&amp;rdquo; What listings are being removed, whose are they, and what can we tell about those listings? The second question is &amp;ldquo;Why?&amp;rdquo; Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the &amp;ldquo;What?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran a survey of Los Angeles in October 2014, and another over the last couple of days. Here are the main findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is always a lot of flux in Airbnb listings, and much of that comes from people who give the service a try and then decide it&amp;rsquo;s not for them. But in Los Angeles there is something else. Here is a table showing the top   hosts (by number of listings) from October 2014, and the number of listings they now have on the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table rules=&#34;groups&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; frame=&#34;hsides&#34; border=&#34;2&#34; cellpadding=&#34;6&#34; &gt;Table 1: The top hosts (by number of listings) in October 2014, and the number of listings they had then (2nd column) and have now (3rd) on Airbnb. The link goes to the host page (if it exists) or is redirected to a generic Airbnb page if the host has been removed. 
&lt;tr &gt;
**Host ID**
**October 2014**
**April 2015**
Reviews
Average Rating
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tbody &gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[3965199](http://airbnb.com/users/show/3965199)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;74
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;15
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.50
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[1463129](http://airbnb.com/users/show/1463129)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;73
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;397
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.47
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[558295](http://airbnb.com/users/show/558295)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;50
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;113
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.54
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[293855](http://airbnb.com/users/show/293855)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;30
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;296
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.26
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[7954](http://airbnb.com/users/show/7954)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;26
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;47
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.60
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[295792](http://airbnb.com/users/show/295792)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;23
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;143
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.68
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[3281907](http://airbnb.com/users/show/3281907)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;23
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;25
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.50
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[66892](http://airbnb.com/users/show/66892)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;22
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;65
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.68
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[2917744](http://airbnb.com/users/show/2917744)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;22
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;1
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;291
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.85
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[4925293](http://airbnb.com/users/show/4925293)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;20
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;27
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.85
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[9088345](http://airbnb.com/users/show/9088345)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;20
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;120
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.41
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[465624](http://airbnb.com/users/show/465624)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;18
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;18
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;789
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.44
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[8608492](http://airbnb.com/users/show/8608492)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;18
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;39
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.42
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[3392276](http://airbnb.com/users/show/3392276)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;16
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;18
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;43
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.67
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[8518444](http://airbnb.com/users/show/8518444)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;16
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;21
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;23
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.52
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[49765](http://airbnb.com/users/show/49765)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;15
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;13
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;1
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0.00
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[148358](http://airbnb.com/users/show/148358)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;15
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;11
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;160
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.95
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[1497543](http://airbnb.com/users/show/1497543)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;15
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;15
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;252
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.76
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[3127239](http://airbnb.com/users/show/3127239)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;15
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;15
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;184
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.32
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[8206200](http://airbnb.com/users/show/8206200)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;15
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;15
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;109
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.39
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[57161](http://airbnb.com/users/show/57161)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;14
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;16
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;145
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.31
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[1466173](http://airbnb.com/users/show/1466173)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;14
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;15
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;517
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.30
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[3324376](http://airbnb.com/users/show/3324376)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;14
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;15
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;101
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;5.00
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[11907135](http://airbnb.com/users/show/11907135)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;14
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;39
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.18
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[1316725](http://airbnb.com/users/show/1316725)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;13
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;14
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;9
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.83
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[1458653](http://airbnb.com/users/show/1458653)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;13
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;13
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;291
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.60
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[3947940](http://airbnb.com/users/show/3947940)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;13
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;13
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;142
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.23
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[7266554](http://airbnb.com/users/show/7266554)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;13
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;24
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;127
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.58
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[16151602](http://airbnb.com/users/show/16151602)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;13
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;14
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;67
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.34
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[489690](http://airbnb.com/users/show/489690)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;12
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;12
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;46
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.72
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[1173362](http://airbnb.com/users/show/1173362)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;12
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;150
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.45
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[2324191](http://airbnb.com/users/show/2324191)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;12
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;15
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;173
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.32
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[3967730](http://airbnb.com/users/show/3967730)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;12
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;14
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;118
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.64
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[4265938](http://airbnb.com/users/show/4265938)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;12
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;8
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;42
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.11
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[5592355](http://airbnb.com/users/show/5592355)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;12
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;10
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;68
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.62
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[219283](http://airbnb.com/users/show/219283)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;11
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;16
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;34
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.78
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[239712](http://airbnb.com/users/show/239712)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;11
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;12
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;590
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.23
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[1221532](http://airbnb.com/users/show/1221532)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;11
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;12
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;25
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.30
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[1254174](http://airbnb.com/users/show/1254174)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;11
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;12
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;86
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;3.90
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[3097566](http://airbnb.com/users/show/3097566)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;11
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;11
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;88
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.45
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[9762413](http://airbnb.com/users/show/9762413)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;11
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;12
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;253
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.57
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[9928881](http://airbnb.com/users/show/9928881)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;11
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;20
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.40
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[19341612](http://airbnb.com/users/show/19341612)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;11
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;12
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.54
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[213865](http://airbnb.com/users/show/213865)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;10
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;9
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;158
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.46
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[2622454](http://airbnb.com/users/show/2622454)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;10
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;10
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;780
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.52
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[5281327](http://airbnb.com/users/show/5281327)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;10
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;212
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.65
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[5425196](http://airbnb.com/users/show/5425196)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;10
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;190
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.17
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[9505402](http://airbnb.com/users/show/9505402)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;10
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;19
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;247
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.65
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[9759851](http://airbnb.com/users/show/9759851)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;10
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;11
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;8
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.69
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr &gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;[3343353](http://airbnb.com/users/show/3343353)
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;9
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;14
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;14
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;4.89
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
Airbnb has basically removed all the top hosts (who had 20 or more listings) and also removed a smattering of others. (If you have a booking at [this listing](https://www.airbnb.com/rooms/1359998) I would make other plans.)
&lt;p&gt;So why has Airbnb done this? They made their usual bland, substance-free comment to the LA Times: that the company&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;mission is to connect hosts with guests and provide a quality, local and authentic experience. We routinely review our platform for market quality and adherence to this mission.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quality looks out: as a user to the site what you see is the rating of the listing, and many of the eliminated hosts have high average ratings. For example, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.airbnb.com/users/show/2917744&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Urban Flat Team&lt;/a&gt; have had their listings removed but had an average rating of 4.85 (out of five), while the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.airbnb.com/users/show/1254174&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Venice Beach Hostel&lt;/a&gt; has a rating of only 3.90 (which is pretty crap) but is still on the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also nothing to do with the type of listing. Most of the top listers are listing out mainly &amp;ldquo;Entire home/apt&amp;rdquo; listings (as opposed to a private room in a house or a shared room) but then so does &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.airbnb.com/users/show/8518444&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prive Luxury Rentals&lt;/a&gt; and they have actually increased their number of listings from 16 to 21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s left is the statement of the sales rep to the AE Hostel agency: that these listings are interfering (probably with no fault of their own) with Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s public image. The LA Times mentions the possibility
of maneuvering in advance of an IPO, and this must be in the minds of some of the Airbnb executives. Also, the LAANE report from last month may be having an impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My guess is that Airbnb knows it has to look after its image as a peer-to-peer company, and that they are removing some of the most high profile professional partners from the site in preparation. So all well and good (although hardly fair on those partners), but is it sincere?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably not. Here are a few facts that Airbnb will probably not publicise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October 2014 there were 49 hosts with 10 or more listings in LA. Now there are 60.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October 2014, visits to Airbnb hosts in LA were split evenly between &amp;ldquo;single-lister&amp;rdquo; hosts and &amp;ldquo;multi-lister&amp;rdquo; hosts. Now the balance has tilted slightly towards multi-listers: their percentage has increased from 50% to 52%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In New York, where Airbnb previously had a clean-up of large listers, the number of hosts with 10 or more listings has increased from 19 to 46 between October 2014 and March of this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, the professionalization of the Airbnb business continues, and this looks like just an attempt to remove some of the more obvious commercial companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could it be something else? Of course it could, but if Airbnb wants to be taken seriously as a company that can regulate itself (and it really does) then it needs to come clean with the reasons for its actions rather than hiding between vacuous PR speak and turning, seemingly at random, on its partners.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Yesterday in Airbnb		</title>
      <link>/post/yesterday-in-airbnb/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 19:01:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/yesterday-in-airbnb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;            First, [this report](http://www.laane.org/airbnb-report) on Airbnb in Los Angeles, by the Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy (LAANE), is fantastic, especially compared to Airbnb&#39;s [own study](http://blog.airbnb.com/airbnbs-positive-impact-in-los-angeles-2) from December. It mixes data with thoughtful commentary with investigative work that could only be carried out by someone who knows the city. (I did contribute a bit of help in the data collection area, but had nothing to do with writing or the report itself.) Here are some highlights.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s report has this to say about its impact on neighbourhoods (in total):&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Airbnb distributes economic impacts to neighborhoods that have not traditionally benefited from tourism spending. With Airbnb properties in more than 80 Los Angeles neighborhoods, Airbnb visitors are staying in and exploring places they might never have otherwise visited.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The LAANE report shows that the Airbnb business is, in fact, concentrated on areas that are already heavily affected by tourism: while &amp;ldquo;AirBnB has units listed throughout Los Angeles, but just nine of the City’s 95 neighborhoods are responsible for generating 73 percent of the company’s revenue.&amp;rdquo; In tourist hotspot Venice, one in eight units are now Airbnb rentals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1010 Wilshire is a high end apartment building with 227 units in Downtown Los Angeles; but 20% of its units are now listed as tourist accommodation on Airbnb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The host you see on the site, with a photo and personal note, may not actually be the host. &amp;ldquo;Danielle and Lexi&amp;rdquo; were two young women with &amp;ldquo;verified ID&amp;rdquo;, but it turns out that they are just a front for Ghc vacation property rentals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there&amp;rsquo;s a lot more. Worth a read if you have any interest in the subject. The report has been picked up by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.latimes.com/business/realestate/la-fi-airbnb-housing-market-20150311-story.html#page=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LA Times&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://la.curbed.com/archives/2015/03/airbnb_neighborhoods_los_angeles.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Curbed LA&lt;/a&gt;, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere, Inside Airbnb has extended its beautiful maps to &lt;a href=&#34;http://insideairbnb.com/portland/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Portland&lt;/a&gt;. They have also collaborated with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wweek.com/portland/article-24210-air_invasion.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Willamette Week&lt;/a&gt; to chart the shape of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business in the city, and the results will be familiar to readers of this site: Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s story of being a site where &amp;ldquo;regular people occasionally rent the home in which they live&amp;rdquo; is misleading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real Airbnb story is gradually getting out there, of a site that uses the heartwarming stories of a few of its hosts to provide a cover for a growing cadre of professional renters using the site to avoid municipal regulations around safety (no fire inspections), zoning (driving gentrification of tourist areas), and taxes. It&amp;rsquo;s good to see diligent, talented people like LAANE and Inside Airbnb push the debate forward.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Airbnb in Barcelona		</title>
      <link>/post/airbnb-in-barcelona/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2014 01:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/airbnb-in-barcelona/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;            So Airbnb is in trouble in Barcelona ([Guardian](http://www.theguardian.com/technology/2014/jul/07/airbnb-fined-illegal-tourist-lets-barcelona-catalonia), [El Pais](http://elpais.com/elpais/2014/07/07/inenglish/1404733914_341057.html), [El Pais again](http://blogs.elpais.com/trans-iberian/2014/07/a-take-on-airbnb-in-barcelona.html)). The company was fined €30,000 by Catalonia&#39;s local government the Generalitat &amp;quot;for illegally commercializing short-stay apartment rentals that are not listed on the Catalan Tourism Register.&amp;quot; Here are a few notes for context.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barcelona has a particular problem with tourists: it has &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/travel/2014/jun/15/barcelona-tourism-boom-economy-residents&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;too many of them&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;ldquo;The city&amp;rsquo;s 1.6 million residents have seen the number of visitors to the city skyrocket from 1.7 million in 1990 to more than 7.4 million in 2012.&amp;rdquo; As one besieged local says, &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re part of what they&amp;rsquo;re selling, but they&amp;rsquo;re destroying it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb has done its usual &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.airbnb.com/airbnb-economic-impact/#barcelona&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;lightweight study&lt;/a&gt; on the city. It&amp;rsquo;s interesting partly for what it doesn&amp;rsquo;t say, because as a city with a highly developed tourist industry, Barcelona is a sign of what is likely to be the pattern for Airbnb for the future. So, here&amp;rsquo;s a quick rundown on Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s usual economy with the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually found more hosts than the 4,000 that Airbnb claims: my recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://tomslee.net/2014/05/the-shape-of-airbnbs-business.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;scan&lt;/a&gt; of their site picked up 6442 hosts and 11284 listings. (part of a series of studies: &lt;a href=&#34;http://tomslee.net/2013/10/notes-on-airbnbs-new-york-business.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://tomslee.net/2013/11/airbnb-business-in-new-york-revisited.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and also &lt;a href=&#34;http://tomslee.net/2014/06/the-shape-of-airbnbs-business-ii.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb avoids its usual claim of &amp;ldquo;the overwhelming majority of Airbnb hosts in Sydney are ordinary residents who rent out the home they live in&amp;rdquo; because it&amp;rsquo;s just not true. 75% of hosts rent out a single listing, which is lower than in most other cities. And the majority of Airbnb listings come from people who are renting out more than a single offering, and I estimate that over 60% of Airbnb revenue comes from multiple listers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea that Airbnb is made up of hosts sharing a part of their home also fails in Barcelona. 59% of listings are &amp;ldquo;whole home&amp;rdquo;, and these make up a whopping 81% of Airbnb revenue from the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, Barcelona is exactly the kind of place that needs to regulate tourism, in order to keep a balance between the income from tourists and preserving the city as a place to live, work (and visit). Airbnb is promoting its &amp;ldquo;home-sharing&amp;rdquo; story to justify its lack of interest in these regulations, but the story has even less truth to it than in New York and elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				The shape of Airbnb&#39;s business (II)		</title>
      <link>/post/the-shape-of-airbnbs-business-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2014 17:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/the-shape-of-airbnbs-business-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Collecting data for several cities both in November 2013 and in May 2014 gives a look at some ways in which Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business is changing in these cities. The cities surveyed are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paris and New York (Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s two biggest markets)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;San Francisco (the home of Airbnb)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;London, Rome, Berlin (three European capitals and major tourist cities)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toronto and Chicago (two smaller markets).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&#34;http://tomslee.net/2014/05/the-shape-of-airbnbs-business.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;in Part I&lt;/a&gt;, the surveys were carried out by a two-stage method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stage 1 used the Airbnb search pages for a city to collect Room ID values (a number that uniquely identifies an individual listing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stage 2 visited the listing page for each Room ID and collected information about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data were stored in a database and the charts here are based on queries of that database. The survey code (and database) are available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tomslee/airbnbny&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main observations are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible that the number of listings has reached a maximum in some of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s largest cities, particularly in the USA, while other cities do continue to show significant growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a surprising amount of churn in Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business. Over a third of the listings on the site in November were no longer there in May, to be replaced by a similar (or, in some cases, greater) number of new listings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 90% of all ratings on the site are 4.5 stars or 5 stars (out of five).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These observations suggest some conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s move to professionalize its host base may be a reaction to the churn in the host population, a necessary step to generate continued growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April Airbnb expelled 2,000 listings from its New York offerings, claiming that they did not offer a positive experience. Many of those listings must have had either no ratings at all or were rated highly (4.5 or 5) by their guests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rating system does not provide a reliable assessment of host quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;churn&#34;&gt;Churn&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 1 shows the net change in the number of listings in each of the eight cities for which data was collected in both November and May, as a percentage of its November value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some cities seem to have maxed out in terms of listings. Six of the cities saw either decreases or increases of less than 10% in the total number of listings. Each of the three US cities in the study lost listings between November and May, while Berlin and Rome were big gainers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/wpid-nysuffer.png&#34; alt=&#34;nysuffer.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 1: Change in number of listings in cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The net gains or losses mask a bigger change. Figure 2 shows that in the six month period, well over a third of existing listings vanished from the site, and were replaced by a similar (or, in the case of Berlin and Rome, substantially greater) number of new listings. For both Paris and New York, well over 40% of listings vanished, only to be replaced by new ones. Figure 3 shows the total number of vanished and new listings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high churn rate must introduce uncertainty for Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s future, as it is relying on a steady stream of new listings to replace those that are vanishing from the site. Perhaps this is one of the motivators of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s efforts to professionalize its host base: hosts who make a commitment to the business being more likely to stick around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/wpid-churn.png&#34; alt=&#34;churn.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 2: New and vanished listings between November 2013 and May 2014, as a percentage of the November number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/wpid-example12.png&#34; alt=&#34;example1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 3: absolute number of new and vanished listings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Note: I did wonder whether this high churn rate could be an artefact: whether the displayed room ID values could have changed between the November and May data collections. A query showed that, of the 10597 listings that occur in both the November and May collections from New York, 10529 have the same host. I concluded that room ID values are stable.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can look a little closer at those vanished listings. Figure 4 shows that the vanishing listings have fewer reviews than the overall population in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/wpid-churn_reviewcount.png&#34; alt=&#34;churn_reviewcount.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 4: Mean number of reviews for vanished listings and for all listings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 5 shows the ratings that the vanished listings had received from guests. The overall distribution of ratings is investigated later in this report, but Figure 5 shows that, while many of the listings had no reviews at all (Airbnb recently claimed that reviews are left for 70% of visits, so it is likely that these listings had no visits either), of those that did have visits the average rating was overwhelmingly high (4.5–5).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/wpid-churn_lost_ratings.png&#34; alt=&#34;churn_lost_ratings.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 5: The number of vanished listings by average overall rating&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 6 emphasizes the point, showing that the average rating of listings leaving the site is within 0.1 of those that stay on the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/wpid-churn_rating.png&#34; alt=&#34;churn_rating.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 6: Average rating of listings that leave the site (red) and which have been on the site for the whole period (green). Note that the y axis &lt;strong&gt;starts&lt;/strong&gt; at 4.5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems likely that many hosts try Airbnb, have a few guests (or none at all) and then simply decide that, for whatever reason, the service is not for them. To repeat the conclusion from the overall churn rate, the high turnover rate does raise questions about what long-term population of hosts the site can support, and how it can ensure that those who try and leave the site are replaced by new hosts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;trust&#34;&gt;Trust&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trust has long been a key part of the Airbnb business, and technology has been seen as the magic ingredient. Airbnb CEO Brian Chesky expresses the company&amp;rsquo;s confidence when he &lt;a href=&#34;http://skift.com/2013/01/11/airbnb-responds-to-illegal-rentals-story-first-of-all-its-not-illegal-everywhere/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;says&lt;/a&gt; of city-level rules that &amp;ldquo;they&amp;rsquo;re primarily set up for screening. To protect consumers. Well it turns out that cities can&amp;rsquo;t screen as well as technologies can screen. Companies have these magical things called reputation systems… We think government should exist as the place of last recourse.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two sides to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.airbnb.ca/trust&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s trust system&lt;/a&gt;. There is &lt;em&gt;peer-to-peer trust&lt;/em&gt;, often described as a reputation system, which consists of ratings, personal profiles, and comments written by hosts or guests and seen by other hosts or guests. The other side is &lt;em&gt;centralized trust&lt;/em&gt;, which consists of central payment, verified ID, and a complaint system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the talk around the sharing economy focuses on reputation and peer-to-peer trust (as in Chesky&amp;rsquo;s comment above). That&amp;rsquo;s because it&amp;rsquo;s the peer-to-peer aspect that is new: after all, in one sense we have forever trusted strangers to deliver services from food to haircuts to regular taxis, and the centralized component of the system is not that different to many hospitality companies. Jason Tanz &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.com/2014/04/trust-in-the-share-economy/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Wired&lt;/em&gt; that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;We are entrusting complete strangers with our most valuable possessions, our personal experiences—and our very lives. In the process, we are entering a new era of Internet-enabled intimacy.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do the numbers have to say about peer-to-peer trust?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 7 shows the distribution of ratings for each listing. Airbnb provides ratings under a number of categories (cleanliness, accuracy of description etc) and collects them together as &amp;ldquo;overall satisfaction&amp;rdquo;. The site does not give the ratings for individuals (although individual comments are visible) but provides an aggregate, from 0 to 5 stars with a half-star granularity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/wpid-city_rating_distribution.png&#34; alt=&#34;city_rating_distribution.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 7: Overall satisfaction ratings for listings in each city. The ratings for 0-3 are so few that they are collected together. Listings with no ratings are excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of ratings are either 4.5 or 5 stars. The finding is consistent with ratings on other sites (e.g. an earlier look at &lt;a href=&#34;http://tomslee.net/2013/09/some-obvious-things-about-internet-reputation-systems.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BlaBlaCar&lt;/a&gt;, or more serious studies of eBay listed there). When we rate each other, ratings become more a courtesy than a judgment. Just as restaurant tips only weakly correspond to the quality of service, so a rating of 4.5 or 5 is more a way of politely concluding an exchange than it is of assessing the behaviour of a host or guest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ratings obviously fail to distinguish among the people on the site, and so are not providing the service for which they were intended. This is part of the reason why Airbnb and others have moved to emphasize the centralized trust aspect of their systems. But centralized trust is the same reason we trust the fast-food restaurant cook or the hotel cleaning staff. The major sharing economy sites rely on discipline and the potential for removal from the site to provide security for the users, just as traditional industries do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;churn-and-trust-in-new-york&#34;&gt;Churn and Trust in New York&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Airbnb court case in New York raised the profile of the service there, and resulted in Airbnb ejecting 2,000 listings from its service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb &lt;a href=&#34;http://publicpolicy.airbnb.com/new-york-airbnb-community/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;claims&lt;/a&gt; that &amp;ldquo;we found that some property managers weren’t providing a quality, local experience to guests. These hosts weren’t making their neighborhood stronger and they weren’t delivering the kind of hospitality our guests expect and deserve. In some cases, they were making communities worse, not better.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With 10,000 listings vanishing from Airbnb in the New York area, it is difficult to know which 2,000 were removed by Airbnb and which left for other reasons. Some individual hosts with large numbers of listings have been removed, but that still leaves many unaccounted for. Figure &lt;em&gt;ny-vanished&lt;/em&gt; shows that, despite Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://publicpolicy.airbnb.com/new-york-airbnb-community/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;suggestion&lt;/a&gt; that the hosts are not &amp;ldquo;delivering the kind of hospitality our guests expect&amp;rdquo;, most of the removed listings must have had either no ratings at all, or must have had good ratings from their guests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/wpid-ny-vanished.png&#34; alt=&#34;ny-vanished.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 8: The &amp;ldquo;overall satisfaction&amp;rdquo; ratings for listings in New York that vanished from the site between November 2013 and May 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest single category of the 10,000 New York listings that have vanished from the Airbnb site are listings with no ratings at all (shown as NULL). After that come the 5.0 and 4.5 ratings, leaving fewer than 800 with bad ratings (4 or lower). For at least 1200 of the listings that Airbnb removed, bad ratings is not the reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combined with the very high number of positive ratings shown in Figure 7, this result shows that the significance of peer-to-peer ratings is exaggerated for Airbnb. While the company proclaims that peer-to-peer rating systems set it apart from old-style methods, it is clear that their trust system is essentially a traditional complaint-based, centralized system. The peer-to-peer ratings may give warm feelings on the site, but Airbnb itself clearly does not trust it when it goes to remove listings from its site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data set suggests that there is a surprising amount of churn in Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s hosts. Over a third of the host population in November left the site, to be replaced by new listings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is likely that a large number of people experiment with being Airbnb hosts, and then decide that it is not for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will be interesting to see whether this becomes an issue for Airbnb as the number of ratings it has in the North American cities surveyed in November and May seems to have peaked. How will it continue the growth that is demanded of it by its backers in the face of the large number of hosts who drop off the platform?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While much is made of the novel peer-to-peer nature of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s reputation system, it appears that the company runs a complaint-based trust system that is not so different from other hospitality companies. In April Airbnb expelled 2,000 listings from its New York offerings, claiming that they did not offer a positive experience, but many of those listings had either no ratings at all or were rated highly (4.5 or 5) by their guests: it appears that Airbnb did not use its own ratings when judging who to remove from its platform.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				The shape of Airbnb&#39;s business		</title>
      <link>/post/the-shape-of-airbnbs-business/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2014 02:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/the-shape-of-airbnbs-business/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When Airbnb talks about its legal troubles in New York, Berlin, Amsterdam, and elsewhere, it claims that existing laws were never designed for its new brand of disruptive peer-to-peer business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case 1: CEO Brian Chesky told &lt;a href=&#34;http://online.wsj.com/news/articles/SB10001424052702304049704579321001856708992&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt; in January that:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;There were laws created for businesses, and there were laws for people. What the sharing economy did was create a third category: people as businesses… They don&#39;t know whether to bucket our activity as person or a business.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case 2: David Hantman wrote on &lt;a href=&#34;http://publicpolicy.airbnb.com/nyc-update/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the Airbnb public policy blog&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;In 2010, the State of New York passed a law designed to crack down on bad actors that operate illegal hotels—a goal we all share. Unfortunately, the 2010 law also had the unintended consequence of impacting regular New Yorkers.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are more. You get the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.airbnb.com/airbnb-economic-impact/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a series of studies&lt;/a&gt; designed to address regulators&#39; concerns, Airbnb talks about its hosts as &amp;ldquo;regular people&amp;rdquo; and focuses on the ways its business is different to the existing tourist business. It highlights the hotel industry as a point of comparison and emphasizes just how different Airbnb is. Here are a few typical quotations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;87 percent of hosts rent the homes they live in&amp;rdquo; (Amsterdam)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;87 percent of Airbnb hosts rent out the home they live in, and the typical host earns $7,530 per year&amp;rdquo; (in New York)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Airbnb is complementary to the existing tourism industry in Paris. 70 percent of Airbnb properties in Paris are located outside the central hotel corridor.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;73 percent of Airbnb properties in Amsterdam are located outside the eight central tourist districts.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s 5,600 local hosts are regular people who occasionally rent out their homes and use the income they earn to pay the bills.&amp;rdquo; (in Berlin)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;About 80% of Airbnb hosts rent out the home they live in&amp;rdquo; (in London and Edinburgh)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are more. You get the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The claim of novelty and of hosts as &amp;ldquo;regular people&amp;rdquo; has been widely accepted. For example, the thoughtful Kevin Roose wrote this in &lt;a href=&#34;http://nymag.com/daily/intelligencer/2014/05/how-should-we-regulate-start-ups.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;New York&lt;/a&gt; magazine the other day:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;There are no laws governing Airbnb because until very recently, there was nothing like Airbnb in the world—not of the same scale, not with the same guiding philosophy. And when Airbnb came onto the scene, regulators were forced to slot it into existing categories where it, arguably, didn&#39;t belong—treating a bachelor renting out his spare room to make rent, for example, with the same rules as a scuzzy landlord operating an illegal hotel. They&#39;ve been playing catch-up ever since.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or as &lt;em&gt;Wired&lt;/em&gt; Magazine &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.com/2014/04/trust-in-the-share-economy/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;We are hopping into strangers&#39; cars (Lyft, Sidecar, Uber), welcoming them into our spare rooms (Airbnb), dropping our dogs off at their houses (DogVacay, Rover), and eating food in their dining rooms (Feastly).&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are more. You get the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when it comes to thinking about and dealing with this and other sharing-economy companies, the kind of business that Airbnb operates matters. Does it match the company&amp;rsquo;s self-portrait? Is the company as novel as it claims to be? Are its hosts &amp;ldquo;regular people&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out there is an element of wishful thinking in the portraits of Airbnb. Last November, I took a look at Airbnb data from New York (&lt;a href=&#34;http://tomslee.net/2013/10/notes-on-airbnbs-new-york-business.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://tomslee.net/2013/11/airbnb-business-in-new-york-revisited.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). In February, travel web site Skift carried out a similar study (&lt;a href=&#34;http://skift.com/2014/02/13/airbnb-in-nyc-the-real-numbers-behind-the-sharing-story/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://skift.com/2014/02/13/the-10-airbnb-super-hosts-that-rule-new-york-city/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), which was part of the New York Attorney General&amp;rsquo;s case against Airbnb. The two studies took similar approaches, collecting listings from Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s public web site and gleaning what we could from that imperfect data set. Both studies concluded that, while it is true that a large number of hosts rent the homes they live in, hosts with multiple listings make up almost half of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business. Also that, while Airbnb makes great play of its origins in renting out an airbed, such rentals are now a negligible portion of its business. Even &amp;ldquo;spare rooms&amp;rdquo; are a minority of the business: the majority of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business in New York comes from the rental of entire homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data showed a company that was closer to orthodox models such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.homeaway.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;HomeAway&lt;/a&gt; and its subsidiary &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vrbo.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;VRBO&lt;/a&gt; than the narrative would have it. There are differences—HomeAway is focused on vacation rentals, and many of its properties are run by property managers—but the similarities cast doubt on Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s claims that existing regulations are inapplicable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now here we are: it&amp;rsquo;s six months on, and interest in Airbnb continues. Airbnb has &lt;a href=&#34;http://publicpolicy.airbnb.com/new-york-airbnb-community/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;kicked&lt;/a&gt; 2,000 New York listings off its site (10% of the total for the city). It handed over host data to the Attorney General (anonymized, the company &lt;a href=&#34;http://publicpolicy.airbnb.com/agreement-new-york/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;says&lt;/a&gt;). Meanwhile, the company is valued at $10 billion, having &lt;a href=&#34;http://online.wsj.com/news/articles/SB10001424052702304626304579509800267341652&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;raised&lt;/a&gt; $450 million in a new round of venture capital. The New York dispute is now &lt;a href=&#34;http://publicpolicy.airbnb.com/agreement-new-york/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;over&lt;/a&gt;, but the sharing economy poster child is still here, bigger than ever, and still a leading light in the wave of digital disruptors looking to shake things up and make a lot of money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So during May I collected data on over 90,000 hosts and 125,000 listings—about 20% of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s 600,000 total, according to &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2014/04/18/airbnb-has-closed-its-500m-round-of-funding-at-a-10b-valuation-led-by-tpg/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this TechCrunch estimate&lt;/a&gt;—from 18 cities around the world, to sketch a portrait of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business. The main questions I had in mind are the straightforward ones, starting with the same ones Skift and I asked about New York:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business based on &amp;ldquo;regular people&amp;rdquo; in a way that other part of the hospitality industry are not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business based on spare rooms and airbeds?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I looked again at several cities I had collected (but not posted about) in November, so that I could look at how the business has changed in some of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s key markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hoped that looking a second time at New York might have something to say about the 2,000 listings that Airbnb removed from the site in April, during its run-in with the Attorney General.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who don&amp;rsquo;t want to read the whole thing, here are the quick answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While a good part of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business is based on &amp;ldquo;regular people&amp;rdquo;, over 40% comes from hosts with multiple listings. This is different from Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s self-portrait. Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s claim that existing regulations don&amp;rsquo;t apply to it is at least exaggerated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s revenue comes from whole-home rentals. This makes the company much more like HomeAway and other vacation rental businesses. It casts further doubt on the company&amp;rsquo;s claim to be a new class of business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some of its biggest markets, Airbnb may have maxed out the number of listings it can achieve. What&amp;rsquo;s more, there is a high rate of churn as individual hosts put a property on the market, have a few guests, and then take the property off again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb does not appear to believe its own claim that customer ratings provide an assurance of good experience. Airbnb says it removed 2,000 New York listings from the site because of bad experience, but at least half of those listings had good (4.5 or 5 star) average ratings from customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to post this in two parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part 1 looks at the split between hosts with a single listing and those with multiple listings, and it also looks at how far Airbnb has moved from its &amp;ldquo;origin myth&amp;rdquo;, after which the company is named—the hosting of people on couches and in shared rooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part II looks at the change in Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business over the last six months, including the changes in New York where the legal strife has been the loudest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I have time and if there are requests, I&amp;rsquo;ll collect these three together and post a single PDF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background-and-method&#34;&gt;Background and Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to set out some basic information, Figure 1 shows the number of listings and of hosts in each city. The data was collected using a fairly straightforward two-stage search. The first stage goes through all the search pages for a specified city and collects the room_id values. The second stage visits the room page for each value and gets details about the listing. The code is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tomslee/airbnbny&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;on github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb has regularly said that is has about 20,000 listings in New York city. I find 19094 (and have over 20,000 from November) so the collection seems pretty complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2013, Airbnb claimed 5600 hosts in Berlin. I find 6141.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the run-up to the World Cup, Airbnb &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/world/rios-residents-seize-rental-oppourtunities-from-world-cup-allure/article18839981/#dashboard/follows/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;claims&lt;/a&gt; to have 9,000 listings in Rio. I find just over 10,000. Perhaps the borders of the search are different, or the number is growing. Still, 90% accuracy is not bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, the surveys for each city seem pretty accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/wpid-city_basics2.png&#34; alt=&#34;city_basics.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 1: Number of hosts and listings in the surveyed cities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-host-perspective&#34;&gt;The host perspective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 2 shows the percentage of hosts in each city that have a single listing on the site. The values for New York and Amsterdam match Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s claim for New York and Amsterdam to within a percentage point, which suggests that the sample is realistic and that the use of a single listing is a pretty good proxy for &amp;ldquo;regular people who occasionally rent out the home in which they live&amp;rdquo;. The graph also shows that the claim applies to most of the big cities. Barcelona, Rome, and Tokyo are the only Airbnb locations surveyed that have fewer than 80% of hosts with a single listing. So far, so good for Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s self-portrait. From here on I will call hosts who have a single listing &amp;ldquo;regular people&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/wpid-city_hosts1.png&#34; alt=&#34;city_hosts.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 2: Percent of hosts with a single listing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-marketplace-perspective&#34;&gt;The marketplace perspective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine that a city has 100 hosts, 99 are &amp;ldquo;regular people&amp;rdquo; with a single listing and one host has 99 listings, then the percent of hosts who are regular people would be 99%, but the percent of &lt;strong&gt;listings&lt;/strong&gt; on the market that come from regular hosts would be only 50%. Both percentages are important in gauging the kind of business that Airbnb is. Figure 3 shows the percent of &lt;strong&gt;listings&lt;/strong&gt; offered by regular people. The overall figure is 62%: still a significant majority, but a number that is 20% lower than the percentage of hosts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see that for a few cities, notably Barcelona (11,000 listings) and Rome (growing quickly, at 8,000 listings), the majority of listings come from hosts with more than one offering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/wpid-city_listings1.png&#34; alt=&#34;city_listings.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 3: Percent of listings from hosts with a single listing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-traveller-perspective&#34;&gt;The traveller perspective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The percentage of listings that come from different types of hosts corresponds to the experience of the potential guest browsing or searching the Airbnb site. The traffic generated by Airbnb is different, because not all listings are equally popular. There may be areas with many Airbnb listings but relatively few actual visits, while other areas may have listings that are visited very frequently. Airbnb does not give the number of actual bookings for each listing (or, nearly equivalently, the number of visits to the listing), but it does give the number of reviews that each listing has received, and this should be a reasonable proxy for the number of visits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over a third of all listings have no reviews at all, and some have many (the most-reviewed listing in my sample is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.airbnb.com/rooms/86456&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; San Francisco treehouse, a novel place to stay with 460 reviews.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 4 shows the percentage of visits that are to rooms listed by regular people. The numbers are getting significantly smaller now. No city has more than three quarters of its visits at properties of regular people, and several have a slim majority of visits to hosts with multiple listings. Overall, 45% of visits happen at places offered by hosts with multiple listings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/wpid-city_bookings1.png&#34; alt=&#34;city_bookings.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 4: Percentage of visits (bookings) to listings offered by hosts with a single listing, using reviews as a proxy for visits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-airbnb-perspective&#34;&gt;The Airbnb perspective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one more step to take, which is to look at Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s actual revenue. What fraction of its business comes from regular people and what fraction comes from multiple listers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get here, I multiply the bookings (proxied by reviews) with the listed nightly price. Again, it&amp;rsquo;s not a perfect measure but so long as regular hosts don&amp;rsquo;t overall have longer- or shorter-stay guests compared to other hosts, it should give a reasonable picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 5 shows the percentage of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s revenue that comes from regular cities. Only three cities have over 60% of their revenue coming from hosts with a single listing. Overall, 44% of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business comes from hosts with more than one listing, which is slightly up from 42% in November (the increase may not be significant).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/wpid-city_revenue1.png&#34; alt=&#34;city_revenue.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 5: Estimated percentage of Airbnb revenue from hosts with single-listings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;airbnb-listing-types&#34;&gt;Airbnb listing types&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story of Airbnb emphasizes the casual &amp;ldquo;airbed&amp;rdquo; rental, but this is a very small part of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business. Again, there are a couple of ways of looking at the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;listings-by-room-type&#34;&gt;Listings by room type&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every listing on the Airbnb site is listed as one of three categories: a private room, a shared room, or an entire home/apartment. Figure 6 shows the breakdown in each city. It is clear that shared rooms are a negligible portion of the total: about 1 in 50 listings are shared rooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/wpid-city_listing_roomtype1.png&#34; alt=&#34;city_listing_roomtype.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 6: Number of listings that are private rooms, entire homes or shared rooms&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;visits-by-room-type&#34;&gt;Visits by room type&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 7 shows the visits by room type, using reviews as a proxy for visits again. Shared rooms are an even smaller percentage of the whole: only 1.4% of Airbnb visits are made to shared rooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/wpid-city_booking_roomtype1.png&#34; alt=&#34;city_booking_roomtype.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 7: Number of visits to private rooms, entire homes or shared rooms&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;revenue-by-room-type&#34;&gt;Revenue by room type&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using reviews * price as a proxy, Figure 8 shows the percentage of revenue from each room type. The revenue that comes from spare couches and shared rooms is a mere 0.56%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tomslee.net/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/wpid-city_revenue_roomtype1.png&#34; alt=&#34;city_revenue_roomtype.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 8: Revenue from different types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-what&#34;&gt;So what?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data show that Airbnb is consistently economical with the truth when it describes its own business. It&amp;rsquo;s a long way from being just &amp;ldquo;regular people&amp;rdquo; and there is a lot more business coming from multiple-listing owners than they let on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data say that it&amp;rsquo;s time commentators and the media stopped using the&amp;quot;Couchsurfing&amp;quot; narrative for Airbnb. At less than 1% of its business, the couchsurfing model is irrelevant for what Airbnb is today. It&amp;rsquo;s far more like HomeAway than it is like Couchsurfing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is a novelty to Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business, it&amp;rsquo;s that it collects property managers, individual renters, and occasional renters under one roof, just as Amazon can offer best sellers, midlist authors and self-published obscura in the same place. And while much of the talk will be about the long tail of rooms, the reality is that Airbnb is pushing for the professionalization of its hosts, and we&amp;rsquo;ll see more of that over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other conclusions to come after we see the rest of the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				No True Airbnb Host...		</title>
      <link>/post/no-true-airbnb-host/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 00:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/no-true-airbnb-host/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;            After months of waiting, Airbnb and the Attorney General of New York finally face each other in court this week to argue over the Attorney General&#39;s [subpoena](https://www.eff.org/document/new-york-ag-subpoena-airbnb) for information on the 15,000 or so Airbnb hosts in New York City (summary [at the Guardian](http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/apr/21/airbnb-new-york-attorney-general-court), more opinion in the overview by Nitasha Tiku at [Valleywag](http://valleywag.gawker.com/new-york-wants-to-subpoena-15-000-users-after-airbnb-re-1565483113)). There&#39;s been a flurry of revealing activity and statements, and lots of commentary. So here&#39;s more.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The court case is about many things. But what makes it interesting for those of us who don&amp;rsquo;t live in New York is the broader implications of the case, which include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The breadth of the Attorney General&amp;rsquo;s subpoena and the proportionality of his actions. Does the subpoena blend into the general fear of government access to individual data in the light of the NSA scandals?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The illegality of some Airbnb rentals. If the subpoena succeeds and shows that a significant portion of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business is based on illegal rentals, then that&amp;rsquo;s a problem for a lot of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Airbnb rentals are illegal, who is responsible (legally and morally)? Is it the host or Airbnb itself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The validity of the law. Airbnb maintain the law is a bad law, inappropriately applied, and that the Airbnb hosts are a new class of business (&amp;ldquo;micro-entrepreneurs&amp;rdquo;) that need new rules. Does new technology render the old laws obsolete?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How will this affect the $10B valuation of Airbnb and its prospects for an IPO?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How will this affect the future of the sharing economy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main players are, obviously, Attorney General Eric Schneiderman and Airbnb. But other players appear on the stage, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb hosts and guests. Hosts have the most to lose if their information is handed over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrat Senator Elizabeth Krueger. Her position on the issue (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nysenate.gov/press-release/behalf-regular-new-yorkers-sen-krueger-responds-airbnbs-three-principles&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://nextcity.org/daily/entry/qa-new-york-senator-liz-krueger-airbnbs-doubter-in-chief&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;today&amp;rsquo;s interview by Nancy Scola&lt;/a&gt;) is a bit different from that of the Attorney General, but she is broadly on the same side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technology industries and advocates. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://internetassociation.org/11082013airbnbamicusbrief/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Internet Association&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eff.org/document/amicus-brief-airbnb-v-schneiderman-eff-and-cdt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Electronic Frontier Foundation&lt;/a&gt; have both spoken up about the subpoena, placing themselves broadly on the Airbnb side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neighbours, landlords, tenants, and housing co-ops. These are all affected by individuals renting out apartments through Airbnb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hotel industry. While Airbnb has painted hotels as one of the villains in the fight, their role seems to me peripheral.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with the narrowest issue: it seems pretty clear that about 2/3 of Airbnb rentals in the city are outside the law in New York, which forbids apartment rentals of under 30 days if the owner is not present. The New York Post report is &lt;a href=&#34;http://nypost.com/2014/04/21/two-thirds-of-citys-airbnb-rentals-are-illegal-apartments-state/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and is based on an affidavit by the Attorney General&amp;rsquo;s office (&lt;a href=&#34;http://tctechcrunch2011.files.wordpress.com/2014/04/sumanta-ray-affidavit-041814-final.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;). That affidavit is, in turn, based on an analysis of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s business carried out by consultants Connotate for travel site &lt;a href=&#34;http://skift.com/2014/02/13/airbnb-in-nyc-the-real-numbers-behind-the-sharing-story/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Skift&lt;/a&gt;. Their report is more extensive than, but similar to, the analysis I carried out a while ago &lt;a href=&#34;http://tomslee.net/2013/11/airbnb-business-in-new-york-revisited.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Airbnb and Peers recognize this by arguing that the law needs to be changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For what it&amp;rsquo;s worth, I find Elizabeth Krueger&amp;rsquo;s position on illegal rentals more reasonable than either the Attorney General&amp;rsquo;s or that of advocacy group Peers. The Attorney General gives the impression of (at least potentially, and despite avowals otherwise) going after all the hosts who have made illegal rentals. Given that law enforcement is usually complaint-based and that Airbnb has done little to warn its hosts of their responsibilities, this seems harsh. Krueger (see links above) puts Airbnb as the root of the problem—making a lot of money off hosts and letting the hosts take all the risk—and I agree with her. Airbnb may not be legally responsible, but it seems to me morally culpable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if the law is just a bad, obsolete law that shouldn&amp;rsquo;t apply to Airbnb hosts anyway, which is what Airbnb has been arguing? Here the onus switches to Airbnb: has it made the case that it can do better than New York&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;bad law&amp;rdquo;? It needs to do more than say &amp;ldquo;because Technology&amp;rdquo; if it&amp;rsquo;s going to justify a change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the Airbnb case is made in its public policy blog posts (&lt;a href=&#34;http://publicpolicy.airbnb.com/update-airbnb-ny-ag/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://publicpolicy.airbnb.com/new-york-airbnb-community/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), in its report on New York (&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.airbnb.com/airbnbs-economic-impact-nyc-community/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;her&lt;/a&gt;e), and in its new sharing cities initiative (&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/life-learning/db9746750a3a&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). What these posts show is a remarkable lack of content, and a reliance on heartwarming words and spin that is, in the end, cheap talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s description of its own hosts is at least consistent. They repeatedly describe their &amp;ldquo;community&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;regular New Yorkers who occasionally rent out their homes&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;regular New Yorkers just trying to make ends meet&amp;rdquo;. They emphasize that &amp;ldquo;87 percent of Airbnb hosts rent out the home they live in&amp;rdquo;. These are all phrases that invoke the &amp;ldquo;sharing economy&amp;rdquo; vision. When anything goes wrong, Airbnb refers to occasional, incredibly rare &amp;ldquo;bad apples&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s homespun language is carefully chosen. The 87% figure is the most obviously economical with the truth. It may be true as a percentage of hosts, but only about 63% of &lt;em&gt;listings&lt;/em&gt; are single-listing hosts, and as much as anyone can tell, almost half of actual &lt;em&gt;bookings&lt;/em&gt; are from hosts who have multiple listings. It&amp;rsquo;s not easy to get definitive answers from scraping the public web site, but Airbnb has consistently refused to challenge these numbers, and so it&amp;rsquo;s a good guess that they are not too far off the truth. They could release their own statistics if they chose, but they don&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, they put out &amp;ldquo;reports&amp;rdquo; that have no methodology, no definitions of key terms, and about 300 words of actual text. Airbnb makes a lot of the fact that it &amp;ldquo;supports more than 4,500 jobs&amp;rdquo; but it never says what &amp;ldquo;support&amp;rdquo; means. It claims to have &amp;ldquo;generated $104 million in economic activity outside of Manhattan&amp;rdquo;, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t say what &amp;ldquo;generated&amp;rdquo; means. This may seem like nit-picking, but it isn&amp;rsquo;t: it&amp;rsquo;s just asking for facts instead of spin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But where things get really bad — for Airbnb hosts who drive the company&amp;rsquo;s revenue as well as for Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s claim to be a responsible provider of safe and well-managed accommodation — is in Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s slippery definition of its own &amp;ldquo;community&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb continually claims to speak for its hosts, as in &amp;ldquo;our hosts want to pay taxes&amp;rdquo;, and repeatedly characterizes its community of &amp;ldquo;amazing&amp;rdquo; hosts as &amp;ldquo;regular&amp;rdquo; people. It also describes them as &amp;ldquo;micro-entrepreneurs&amp;rdquo;, suggesting that they are independent. But Airbnb hosts, who are asked increasingly to invest in their own property in order to put it on Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s marketplace, are precariously dependent on Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s whims in order to make money from their investment, which is not an entrepreneurial role at all. If anything goes wrong, the host gets turfed off the market without appeal. If you&amp;rsquo;re a host, how do you know if you are a &amp;ldquo;bad apple&amp;rdquo; or a &amp;ldquo;regular New Yorker&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most dramatically, this has happened today. After insisting for months that concerns about multiple listings were exaggerated, Airbnb today &lt;a href=&#34;http://publicpolicy.airbnb.com/new-york-airbnb-community/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;permanently removed&lt;/a&gt; no fewer than 2,000 New York listings from its platform – roughly 10% of the total. They claim the process has been going on for months, and that it demonstrates their responsibility. But the fact that it happened today of all days, the fact that identifying multiple listings is a trivial exercise, and the fact that the criteria for expulsion are still woefully unclear, makes it difficult to take them seriously (&lt;a href=&#34;http://skift.com/2014/04/21/airbnbs-settlement-talks-with-new-york-state-fall-apart-court-case-to-continue/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jason Clampet at Skift&lt;/a&gt; is excellent on the removals). Here is an excerpt of Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s explanation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;But when we examined our community in New York, we found that some property managers weren&#39;t providing a quality, local experience to guests. These hosts weren&#39;t making their neighborhood stronger and they weren&#39;t delivering the kind of hospitality our guests expect and deserve. In some cases, they were making communities worse, not better. We took a hard look at our community in New York to identify these hosts and we took action.
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, we began notifying these hosts that they and their more than 2,000 listings would be permanently removed from the Airbnb community. While we are allowing these hosts to support their existing  bookings, all are now prohibited from accepting new reservations and if you search for a place to stay in New York, you won’t find these listings.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine you are an Airbnb host in New York reading these words. How would you know if you are living up to Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s requirements? Are you making your neighbourhood stronger? Are you delivering the kind of hospitality your guests expect? This is a &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No_true_Scotsman&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;No True Scotsman&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; argument: the Airbnb community is trustworthy because if you do anything Airbnb decides is wrong then you are not part of the community. The lack of clarity is remarkable and shows that they are not ready to provide the kind of security and accountability that any replacement for rentals regulation would need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My skepticism over Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s sincerity is heightened because, apparently, one blocking point in the negotiations with New York is that (according to Clampet), &amp;ldquo;Airbnb would not agree to limits on how many listings a person could have in New York City.&amp;rdquo; It&amp;rsquo;s clear that a large number of bookings is essential to the venture capital model, and goes against the spirit of the &amp;ldquo;sharing economy&amp;rdquo; that Airbnb so consistently invokes. But it looks like they&amp;rsquo;re going where the money is. That makes them untrustworthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s evocative but meaningless cheap talk (for more, see their &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/life-learning/db9746750a3a&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Shared Cities initiative&lt;/a&gt;) is cynical. I fear that, instead of promoting any realistic idea of sharing, Airbnb will pollute the whole idea as a consequence of the high-return venture capital model it has pursued.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Airbnb Stories		</title>
      <link>/post/airbnb-stories/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 01:39:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/airbnb-stories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;            Telling stories is a powerful, personal way to communicate. That&#39;s why Airbnb collects stories from its hosts and puts them [on its web site](https://www.airbnb.ca/stories) and uses them liberally in its publicity.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;When the economic crash hit, [Tama](https://www.airbnb.ca/stories/new-york/one-way-forward)’s livelihood as a painter and real estate broker was threatened. A serious health condition was only increasing her expenses, with prescription costs at times topping $1000 per month. Receiving guests not only introduced her to new friends—it allowed her to eat, pay her bills, and stay in her home.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Chris&amp;rsquo;s story is not on the Airbnb web site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;In San Francisco, [Chris](http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/Airbnb-profits-prompted-S-F-eviction-ex-tenant-5164242.php?t=d6c1c46efd3c100abe#/0) lost his home so that his landlord could make more money by renting out apartments on Airbnb. Chris says: &#34;They forced me out of a home I loved. It was incredibly difficult to find a place, especially because I have a really old dog. I ended up paying over double what I was paying there.&#34; Chris is now suing his landlord and his attorney says: &#34;Airbnb is contributing to the displacement of long-term tenants in San Francisco... It has made it so easy to go into the short-term rental business; it is ubiquitous.&#34;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most stories on the Airbnb web site are about people renting out the homes in which they live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;[Lisa and Byron](https://www.airbnb.ca/stories/new-york/full-house) are both artists, and have been their whole lives. They first met at an art residence in 1986, were married in 1993, and their family home in a Park Slope brownstone is where they raised their three kids.
&lt;p&gt;This past fall, when their son headed off to university, their downstairs sat empty, so when tuition bills started rolling in, Lisa realized Airbnb was a great solution to help pay for them.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But not all Airbnb hosts rent the house in which they live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;In New York, [Chris](http://www.wnyc.org/story/two-true-stories-airbnb-wars/) lives in Brooklyn but rents out two bedrooms in a separate apartment he leases in Manhattan, at $100 per night.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sounds like a nice little earner. Some Airbnb hosts are generous, and are on the Airbnb web site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;When New York City was hit by one of the worst hurricanes in history, [Shell](https://www.airbnb.ca/stories/new-york/sandys-impact), a long time host on Airbnb, realized that the loss for some people was devastating. As the waters rose and people had to evacuate their homes, many of them couldn’t return for days, if at all. Shell decided to go online and list her space for free for those who were in need.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb is quick to claim Shell as part of its &amp;ldquo;community&amp;rdquo;. It has&amp;rsquo;t been so quick to claim everyone. Not Ken&amp;rsquo;s tenant, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Also in New York, [Ken](http://www.wnyc.org/story/two-true-stories-airbnb-wars/) owns a few buildings in Nolita. He runs a nonprofit that teaches people how to ride bicycles. Now he&#39;s hiring private investigators to see what his tenants are doing. Ken doesn&#39;t like it: “It’s so not me. It’s like how did I become that guy?” But Apartment 3 had become a kind of hotel, charging $250 a night and he suspects the tenant made half a million dollars before he evicted her. He says of Airbnb that  “They see how lucrative her business was... And they refuse to take it down. So they’re not good guys.&#34;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the Airbnb stories are about friendliness and about connections between people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;[Jonathan](https://www.airbnb.com/stories/los-angeles/the-art-of-receiving) is a single dad raising three kids in Echo Park, Los Angeles. For years he worked 60-80 hour weeks at a job that was unfulfilling, scrambled to care for his three children, and had let his own ceramics studio fall by the wayside. When his schedule was cut back at work, Jonathan decided to list an extra room in his home on Airbnb. His first guest gave him such a positive review that more lined up, and he was soon renting out a second room as well.
&lt;p&gt;Hosting has become not only an extra source of income, it’s also allowed him to be more available to his own family.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Jerry&amp;rsquo;s story isn&amp;rsquo;t on the Airbnb web site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nola.com/politics/index.ssf/2013/03/new_orleans_residents_slam_ill.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jerry&lt;/a&gt; lives in New Orleans. He says that &amp;ldquo;In the French Quarter it is increasingly difficult to know your neighbors because they change every weekend.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have resisted telling stories when writing about the sharing economy, even though almost every media report leads with one and even though I&amp;rsquo;ve been asked to use them. I&amp;rsquo;ll continue to avoid them, in general, even though it probably limits the audience I&amp;rsquo;ll reach. Why? Because selective storytelling is manipulative and I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be a manipulator and I don&amp;rsquo;t want my readers to be manipulated. (Trust me.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you read a heart-warming story promoted by someone with a vested interest, you&amp;rsquo;re being sold a bill of goods. It really is as simple as that. The people in the story may be genuine; the story may be true, and they may be lovely people doing wonderful things. But there are millions of stories in every city, and the magic is in the selection (and the photography). By themselves, stories tell us nothing about the bigger picture, and it&amp;rsquo;s occasionally worth remembering that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
