<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Book News | Tom Slee</title>
    <link>/category/book-news/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/book-news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Book News</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 May 2007 13:31:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Book News</title>
      <link>/category/book-news/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				A response to Alex Tabarrok		</title>
      <link>/post/marginal_revolu/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2007 13:31:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/marginal_revolu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At Marginal Revolution, Alex Tabarrok has posted a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2007/05/no_one_makes_yo.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;fine review&lt;/a&gt; of No One Makes You Shop at Wal-Mart: I&amp;rsquo;ll be keeping this paragraph somewhere to cheer me up when I&amp;rsquo;m feeling gloomy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Slee&#39;s book is the best of the anti-market books: it is well written, serious, and knowledgeable about economics. In fact, I regard Slee&#39;s book as an excellent primer on asymmetric information, free riding, externalities, herding, coordination problems and identity - Economics 301 for all those budding young Ezra Klein&#39;s of the world who think that Economics 101 isn&#39;t quite right.
&gt; 
&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very nice. But coming from his libertarian point of view, it&amp;rsquo;s not surprising he has some criticisms. Let&amp;rsquo;s skip right past the lesser ones to the Most Serious Of All:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The chapter on power is terrible, I did throw the book against the wall. Perhaps in order to prepare us to welcome government as the deliverer of our true preferences, Slee wants to diminish the distinction between liberty and coercion. But a true liberal should never write things like this:
&gt; 
&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt;...the formal structure of democracy and free markets is not enough to rule out exploitation and plunder - characteristics usually associated with repressive regimes.
&gt;&gt; 
&gt;&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&gt; 
&gt; If Tom visits GMU (I happen to know he reads MR) he should watch out because I shall kick him in the shins stating, &#34;I refute you thus.&#34;
&gt; 
&gt; 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More seriously, repressive governments around the world threaten, rob, torture and murder with impunity. Courageous individuals have died trying to escape such regimes while others have died fighting for their rights. No matter how great are differences in wealth, it is morally wrong to equate what goes on in repressive regimes with capitalist acts between consenting adults.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strong stuff, and it hits home because I always thought that chapter to be the weakest in the book. But blogs are no place for mild-mannered agreement so let me try to return the kick in the shins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us see many problems of this world in shades of grey, but there are always a few issues that are starker and more elemental, which we see as black or white. The &amp;ldquo;shades of grey&amp;rdquo; issues are questions of nuance and detail - these are questions where reasonable people can reasonably disagree, where we look to modest reform to improve matters, and where we look for technical solutions. It&amp;rsquo;s the dichotomies where we stand our ground - these are the things that define our politics; they are matters of principle - it&amp;rsquo;s right vs. wrong and communication across these divides is difficult. So what are these fundamental, black vs white issues?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karl Marx knew what he thought was fundamental:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The history of all hitherto existing society is the history of class struggles.
&gt; 
&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My brother once relayed to me a very short conversation he had in a pub with a radical feminist:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Brother: throughout history the fundamental oppression is that of one class by another.  
Feminist: throughout history the fundamental oppression is that of women by men.  
Imagined Next Line By Both: who else can I sit with?
&gt; 
&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Singer (in &amp;ldquo;A Darwinian Left&amp;rdquo;, page 8) sets out what he sees as &amp;ldquo;fundamental to the left&amp;rdquo;: it is to be &amp;ldquo;on the side of the weak, not the powerful; of the oppressed, not the oppressor; of the ridden, not the rider.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where do libertarians draw their line? It&amp;rsquo;s coercion versus liberty: the state versus markets, laws versus bargains. That&amp;rsquo;s why a typical Cato Institute &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cato-unbound.org/2007/05/07/daniel-b-klein/economics-and-the-distinction-between-voluntary-and-coercive-action/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; is something like &amp;ldquo;Is the Minimum Wage Coercive?&amp;rdquo; Small wonder then, that it&amp;rsquo;s a chapter setting out to recast this dichotomy as shades of grey that makes Alex Tabarrok throw the book against the wall. You can see elsewhere in Alex&amp;rsquo;s review that this is the fundamental dichotomy he has in mind as he reads. When I talk about collective action he assumes I&amp;rsquo;m talking about government intervention in the economy because that&amp;rsquo;s where he sees me, as his ideological opposition, coming from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a mark of the success of the libertarian project that the left has bought into this false dichotomy of state versus markets. We (the left) are the victim of our own success - the post-war construction of the welfare state, the achievements of social democracy, the provision of public education, and of public healthcare. We&amp;rsquo;ve let ourselves be identified with these achievements, and so now stand as conservative defenders of the state against the market-favouring radicals. Yet things need not be so. I look on my bookshelves and see some books from the UK of the late &amp;rsquo;70s and early &amp;rsquo;80s: &amp;ldquo;In and Against the State&amp;rdquo;, Ralph Miliband&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The State in Capitalist Society&amp;rdquo; and so on. Those on the left have a long history of opposition to the state, and a recognition of its problems. The difference is, we on the left don&amp;rsquo;t see the state as the root of the problems. The state may be a hammer, but it&amp;rsquo;s the arm holding it we need to worry about. &amp;ldquo;The executive of the modern state is but a committee for managing the common affairs of the whole bourgeoisie&amp;rdquo; wasn&amp;rsquo;t it?.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of my chapter is to remind us that the state is not the sole source of coercion, and that libertarians have a blind spot to coercion in the non-state sector. In the comments section of a recent Marginal Revolution &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2007/05/is_the_minimum_.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about the Cato Institute Minimum Wage article I said &amp;ldquo;_My employer requires that I follow instructions from my manager or I can be fired. Is that also coercive? Yes.&amp;rdquo; _and another commenter responded _&amp;quot;_No, refusing to buy future labor from you is not coercive.&amp;quot; I can see what he or she means, but you can also see the false dichotomy here - the law is coercive, everything else is a matter of choice. Tell that to (among many many examples) workers &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/18/national/18WALM.html?ex=1389762000&amp;amp;en=659ee9a0025b35de&amp;amp;ei=5007&amp;amp;partner=USERLAND&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;locked-in overnight&lt;/a&gt; at Wal-Mart stores. Was slavery coercion? Yes, and it would surely be a stretch to see slavery as a problem rooted in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex writes &amp;ldquo;If there were no asymmetric information, no herding, no coordination problems and so forth I guarantee that there would still be plenty of inequality.&amp;rdquo; True enough, but if there were no state, no laws, no public health standards, and so forth I guarantee that there would still be plenty of coercion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are obviously speaking from very different points of view. Are there paths across the divide? I would suggest there are. Alex claims that I have &amp;ldquo;no appreciation that what some of us MarketThink people really advocate is civil society which includes non-profits and voluntary collective action of all kinds.&amp;rdquo; Compare that assertion with Erik Olin Wright&amp;rsquo;s rather wordy but still worth reading &amp;ldquo;Taking the Social in Socialism Seriously&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ssc.wisc.edu/%7Ewright/Published%20writing/Taking%20the%20social.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;), which also focuses on civil society as a way out of the market/state dichotomy. Or the way in which both communitarian left and libertarian right took Jane Jacobs to their hearts. There is a phrase there (voluntary collective action) that we all seem to favour, even as some of us focus on the collective and others on the voluntary. Perhaps a focus on the possibilities of that phrase would be worth exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Update: **Brad DeLong links to AT&amp;rsquo;s review &lt;a href=&#34;http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2007/05/tyler_cowen_on_.html#comments&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (but credits the review to AT&amp;rsquo;s partner in marginal crime Tyler Cowen). The comment thread has quite a different set of sympathies!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 2:&lt;/strong&gt; The other day I was pleased that my amazon.com Sales Rank was around 42,000. It is now 3634 - entirely due to the review.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				42,334		</title>
      <link>/post/42334/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2007 21:44:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/42334/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s my book&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/No-one-Makes-You-Shop-Wal-Mart/dp/189707106X&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amazon.com&lt;/a&gt; number right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the lowest (best) I&amp;rsquo;ve seen it in the year since publication, which is pretty encouraging. Usually it&amp;rsquo;s up in the 100,000 to 500,000 range, but a series of about three purchases this week knocked it down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, I still check it far too much.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Bad Reviews: What&#39;s a Novice Author To Do?		</title>
      <link>/post/another_review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2006 17:28:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/another_review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hooray! I thought all the book reviews were done some time ago, but one more appeared in the December 2006 edition of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reviewcanada.ca&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Literary Review of Canada&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boo! Not only is the review (not available online) almost entirely negative, but it also misrepresents the book entirely. I don&amp;rsquo;t mind the negative, but the misunderstanding and misrepresenting pisses me off something terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a response forthcoming in the January/February 2007 edition, in which I do what you are supposed to do and take the high road. It seems to be common wisdom that it is Not The Done Thing to argue with reviewers, although Peter Woit does it all the time (that is, argues with reviews of his string theory book &lt;em&gt;Not Even Wrong&lt;/em&gt;) regularly in his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;, and it comes over OK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So should I post what I really think here on this little corner of the Internet or not? Do I descend into the gutter, biting and scratching and swearing and generally lowering the tone of the neighbourhood, or do I stay up here, tight-lipped and dignified on the lofty high ground, breathing the etherial air that we morally pure people breathe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the right thing for a novice author to do?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Best Seller!		</title>
      <link>/post/best_seller/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2006 13:11:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/best_seller/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Not quite the New York Times best seller list, but I am on the nearly-as-important &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wordsworthbooks.com/BestSellers.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Words Worth Books best seller list&lt;/a&gt;, appearing at number 5 on their paperback nonfiction list (ahead of Al Gore&amp;rsquo;s Inconvenient Truth but behind Stephen Lewis, Jane Jacobs and &amp;ldquo;Waterloo Trails and Bikeways&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paperback Non Fiction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;212 - Race Against Time 2/E - Stephen Lewis&lt;br&gt;
116 - Waterloo Trails &amp;amp; Bikeways&lt;br&gt;
87 - Fantastic Realities - Frank Wilczek&lt;br&gt;
80 - Dark Age Ahead - Jane Jacobs&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;63 - No One Makes You Shop at Wal-Mart&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;- Tom Slee&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
61 - Inconvenient Truth - Al Gore&lt;br&gt;
61 - End of Food - Thomas Pawlick&lt;br&gt;
50 - Guidebook to Woolwich Trails - Trails Group&lt;br&gt;
49 - Manitoulin Rocks - Peter Russell&lt;br&gt;
45 - Temperament - Stuart Isacoff&lt;br&gt;
42 - Sophie&amp;rsquo;s World - Jostein Gaarder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that part of the reason is that the staff has been helping to sell the book (Dave, this means you), so many thanks to Words Worth Books for their support of &lt;em&gt;No One Makes You Shop At Wal-Mart&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wordsworthbooks.com/BestSellers.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Best Sellers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also see the Words Worth blog, called (I have no idea why) &lt;a href=&#34;http://howtofurnisharoom.blogspot.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How To Furnish a Room&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				On Doing My Homework		</title>
      <link>/post/on_doing_my_hom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2006 00:29:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/on_doing_my_hom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Story So Far&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthony Evans and I, as well as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dorsetdipper.blogspot.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dorset Dipper&lt;/a&gt;,
got into a bit of argy-bargy in the comments following Chris Dillow&amp;rsquo;s
review of No One Makes You Shop At Wal-Mart. The story so far is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://stumblingandmumbling.typepad.com/stumbling_and_mumbling/2006/10/noone_makes_you.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Chris Complained&lt;/a&gt;
that I didn&amp;rsquo;t address Hayek&amp;rsquo;s argument &amp;ldquo;that markets are a way of
processing countless dispersed pieces of information on people&amp;rsquo;s tastes
and technologies.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://whimsley.typepad.com/whimsley/2006/10/book_review_at_.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;I Indicated&lt;/a&gt;
that &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve never read much of [Hayek]. The bits I have always seemed to
be talking about a reality I didn&amp;rsquo;t recognize. So I can&amp;rsquo;t really
address the point, and will go and read. Mea culpa.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://stumblingandmumbling.typepad.com/stumbling_and_mumbling/2006/10/noone_makes_you.html#comment-24465759&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Anthony Asserted&lt;/a&gt;
that &amp;ldquo;To write a book on the subject of individualism and free markets
without reading Hayek is shocking&amp;rdquo;, and on that basis he wouldn&amp;rsquo;t read
my book and I&amp;rsquo;m poorer by $2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now &lt;a href=&#34;http://thefilter.blogs.com/thefilter/2006/11/no_one_makes_yo.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Anthony has followed up&lt;/a&gt; with a full-length post of his own, arguing &amp;ndash; well, a whole bunch of things actually, which I am going to argue back at in&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This weeks episode.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthony says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The focus of his book is individualism and competition, and you can&#39;t understand either without knowing about Hayek&#39;s [Individualism and Economics Order](http://www.amazon.co.uk/Individualism-Economic-Order-F-Hayek/dp/0226320936/sr=8-1/qid=1162638779/ref=sr_1_1/202-7284881-2859013?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books), and [The Use of Knowledge in Society](http://www.virtualschool.edu/mon/Economics/HayekUseOfKnowledge.html). 
&gt; 
&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, as he now puts it &amp;ldquo;you should read up on a topic if you&amp;rsquo;re writing a book on it&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this little dispute has its roots in the difference between an education in
the natural sciences and one in the social sciences. No one ever asked
me if I had &amp;ldquo;read Heisenberg&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;read Pauling&amp;rdquo; or even &amp;ldquo;read
Einstein&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s just not a question that makes sense. Their discoveries
get absorbed into the subject; new terminology arises around their
work; new ways of expressing their insights are formulated. Pretty
quickly reading the original is redundant, and is something you do for
historical interest alone. Mathematics, of course, takes this tendency
to the extreme, consciously purging every ounce of historical context
from its theorems as it moves forward in the search for stark elegance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the idea that you need to &amp;ldquo;read Hayek&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;read Marx&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;read
Weber&amp;rdquo; is really a bit odd. The insights they had have either faded or
become part of the discipline &amp;ndash; or at least, in the more fractious
world of economics, one strand of it. So yes, I&amp;rsquo;ve &amp;ldquo;read Friedman&amp;rdquo;, and
yes I&amp;rsquo;ve &amp;ldquo;read Becker&amp;rdquo; and so on. And I&amp;rsquo;ve even read a bit of Hayek (I
did just say I haven&amp;rsquo;t read much).
But really, unless you are interested in the historical context of the
arguments at the time &amp;ndash; the whole Lange-Lerner market socialism thing
for example, or where Margaret Thatcher got her inspiration &amp;ndash; I should
not have missed a lot if economics as a discipline has done its job,
and I trust it has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I did go and read the essay on Knowledge in Society,
about the price system and how it captures and coordinates specialized
local knowledge and expertise, and why central planning is doomed to
fail. Fine. These are arguments that have indeed become part of the
mainstream of economics and yes, for the record, I&amp;rsquo;m familiar with
them. But let&amp;rsquo;s face it, a lot has become understood since 1945 when he
wrote this essay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One reason I dislike Hayek&amp;rsquo;s writing in this essay, from a personal
point of view, is its consciously broad-brush approach. This is what I
meant when I said &amp;ldquo;The bits
I have [read] always seemed to be talking about a reality I didn&amp;rsquo;t recognize.&amp;rdquo;
Journalists know there are two ways to tell a story: from the particular to
the general and from the general to the particular. Hayek starts big (look at that
title &amp;ldquo;The Use of Knowledge in Society&amp;rdquo;). Myself, I like to start small
and specific (which is why I called my book after an everyday happening
like shopping). When the devil is in the details, the &amp;ldquo;think big&amp;rdquo;
approach is likely to miss important things, and I think this is a
lesson that most economists have learned since Hayek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;George Akerlof, for example, wrote in his Nobel lecture that &amp;ldquo;In the
late 1960s there was a shift in the job description of economic
theorists&amp;hellip; Since that time, both micro and macroeconomics have
developed a Scarry-ful book of models designed to incorporate into
economic theory a whole variety of realistic behaviors.&amp;rdquo; To read Hayek
now is to read an essay that overreaches. It does not tell me what
happens in any one situation. Stiglitz gets it right when he says that
assuming away market failures is like leaving Hamlet out of the play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthony disagrees I&amp;rsquo;m sure, and we are left with what Dipper described as &amp;ldquo;my assumptions against your assumptions&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up, there is nothing in what I wrote that I would change having
read this essay. It is true that I don&amp;rsquo;t talk directly in the book
about the role of markets as a mechanism for processing information and
social knowledge, but hey, it&amp;rsquo;s only 240 pages, you can&amp;rsquo;t write about
everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthony says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;It&#39;s ludicrous [for me] to say that a cover-to-cover reading of the book is a pre-requisite for any opinion to be formed.
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just for the record, what I actually wrote was&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I might say that dismissing a book without reading **any of it **is shocking too, if I hadn&amp;rsquo;t done it so many times myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So relax, we all have to choose what we pay attention to and what we
don&amp;rsquo;t. Go ahead, have opinions, I know I do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I still think it&amp;rsquo;s a
bit cheeky to accuse me of not doing my homework on the basis of what I
wrote about not reading much Hayek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about those toilets?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthony says I don&amp;rsquo;t know much about &lt;a href=&#34;http://whimsley.typepad.com/whimsley/2006/10/the_state_versu.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;toilets&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I&amp;rsquo;m not going to work too hard to defend a blog post. There are
indeed inconsistencies there - fair enough. But I actually don&amp;rsquo;t think
the biggest cause of water-wasting toilets is flat-rate water payment
(which has, I think, receded anyway over the years). The costs of
information are at least as significant. Quick, what portion of your
water bill is from toilet flushes? So I stand by my basic argument that
in this case neither state nor market succeeded until our individual
hero came along and solved the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s it for now. Thanks to Anthony for letting me know about his post and for the free publicity to his readers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Radio Interview		</title>
      <link>/post/radio_interview/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2006 21:24:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/radio_interview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had a radio interview this morning courtesy of Phil Johnson, host of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kelowna.okoldies.ca/shows/phil-johnson-show&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a daily morning show&lt;/a&gt; (6am to 9am) in Kelowna, BC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has apparently been running a series talking about consumer choices. One of his regular guests is Michael Neill, who (together with Michelle Neill) owns &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mosaicbooks.ca/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mosaic Books&lt;/a&gt; in Kelowna, and who has apparently been referring to No One Makes You Shop At Wal-Mart from time to time. Clearly a man of intellect and perception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phil Johnson is an articulate host with strong opinions, and we seem to look at the world in a similar kind of way, so the interview was fun once it got started. I say &amp;ldquo;once it got started&amp;rdquo; because the phones went on the blink just before he called. Panic! Anyway, it got sorted thanks to a colleague with a mobile phone (thank you Roger). Fifteen minutes later we were all done. It seemed to go by very quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my thanks to Phil Johnson and Michael Neill and to Kelowna Oldies 1150. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to celebrate with a glass of the Okanagan&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jacksontriggswinery.com/en/pdf/IWSCSF_2006_%20Best_Shiraz.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;world beating 2004 Shiraz&lt;/a&gt; from Jackson-Triggs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Book News: Review		</title>
      <link>/post/book_news_revie/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2006 22:57:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/book_news_revie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The enigmatic &lt;a href=&#34;http://elephantstrunk.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Elephantstrunk&lt;/a&gt; has some &lt;a href=&#34;http://elephantstrunk.net/2006/10/05/marginal-counter-revolutionary/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;good things to say&lt;/a&gt; about No One Makes You Shop At Wal-Mart. I hope he or she does not mind if I reproduce it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Tom Slee’s [“No one makes you shop at Wal-Mart”](http://www.web.net/%7Etslee/)
should be bundled with every copy of “The Wisdom of Crowds”. I like
“The Wisdom of Crowds” but it always seemed dangerously incomplete.
NOMYSAW is not exactly a counter argument but shows that life is a lot
more complicated than the TWoC might suggest.  
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Slee is clearly exercised by the free ride given to arguments
resting on offers of “choice”. Starting with the Prisoner’s Dilemma the
book shows ways that the seemingly obvious good of giving people the
opportunity to decide what is best for themselves can sometimes make
everyone worse off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not an original point but nor is it in fact a controversial
one. What is new is the articulation of what it means and what some
popular arguments don’t. The book uses the Prisoner’s Dilemma as a
simple example of individuals each seeking to maximise their personal
situation and suffering as a result but the most potent are at some
level examples of “The Tragedy of the Commons” but in places where the
Coasian solution of applying property rights is a less comfortable
propositions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding a whole book, especially one so articulate and clear, about
a persistent but only half formed idea is quite a thrill. I liked it a
lot. Whimsley mentioned on the right is the author’s occasional blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks very much Mr/Ms Trunk.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Book News: Speaking Engagements		</title>
      <link>/post/book_news_speak/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2006 22:51:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/book_news_speak/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s time to say something about the book again. I&amp;rsquo;ve been invited to give a few talks recently - some have already happened, and some coming soon. Thanks to those who have invited me - the ones so far have been very rewarding (for me at least).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Car Free Day was an event sponsored by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wpirg.org/wpirg/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;WPIRG&lt;/a&gt; in September. They invited me to speak at the outdoor event in Victoria Park and also at the University. Speaking outside with a small audience is difficult - the surrounding noise makes it feel as if you are shouting at people sitting a few feet from you. If you weren&amp;rsquo;t there to hear me, I don&amp;rsquo;t think you missed anything. The University event was better, with about 20 people there and some good discussion afterwards. Most interesting was a comment about an intriguing high-tech public bicycle system in Lyon named &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.velov.grandlyon.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Velo&amp;rsquo;v&lt;/a&gt;, which seems to be a big success according to a Guardian article reprinted &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.peopleandplanet.net/pdoc.php?id=2516&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kitchener NDP recently hosted &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.peggynash.ca/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Peggy Nash&lt;/a&gt;, a new MP for Parkdale- High Park in Toronto. I was very impressed. She spoke for 45 minutes with no notes on a wide variety of topics, from a recent fact-finding visit to Lebanon to the ins and outs of Parliamentary committees and was obviously smart and very well informed. I was asked to present her with a copy of my book as a thank you for the visit, which was a privilege.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the meeting I met two philosophy profs from the University of Waterloo. Dave DeVidi is using No One Makes You&amp;hellip; in a Decision Theory course, and Tim Kenyon may be using it next year in a Critical Thinking course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a week and a half I&amp;rsquo;ll be speaking as part of a panel at an event at York University named _Social Justice: From Rhetoric to Action _put on by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.socialjustice.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Centre for Social Justice&lt;/a&gt;. The programme is still in a draft form - I&amp;rsquo;ll post more when it gets closer. It&amp;rsquo;s a challenge to condense a piece of the book into an edible-sized chunk for talks, but I think I&amp;rsquo;m slowly getting better at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I&amp;rsquo;m an invited speaker next month in an Engineering and Society course that is being run at McMaster University as part of the Peace Studies program. It is called &amp;ldquo;War and Natural Resources: The Case of Oil&amp;rdquo; ****which is being run by Graeme MacQueen and Jack Santa Barbara. I&amp;rsquo;m sure the course is a fascinating one - I just hope I can hold people&amp;rsquo;s interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One trouble with writing a book that covers quite a wide range of topics is that you don&amp;rsquo;t get to give the same talk twice &amp;ndash; transit, social justice, and warfare. But the best way to learn more about something is to tell others about it, so this has been very rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				&#34;How&#39;s the Book Doing?&#34; Entrails and Tea Leaves		</title>
      <link>/post/entrails_and_te/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2006 20:04:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/entrails_and_te/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Having a book published has turned me into a brain addled validation junkie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure that when Margaret Atwood or Malcolm Gladwell release a book they have a lot of work to do - book signings, tours, interviews, and so on. But when you&amp;rsquo;re a no name author those kind of events just don&amp;rsquo;t make much sense for anyone - publisher, author, or bookstore. And book sales are notoriously difficult to track: just because a bookstore has ordered the book doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean a reader has actually bought it, so those copies may just be sitting on a shelf, waiting to be returned. So there is something of a void.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How&amp;rsquo;s the book doing?&amp;rdquo; people ask, and while (on the advice of LS) I usually respond optimistically, the truth is I have no idea. What, anyway, would be good and what would be bad? I mean, being invited on the Daily Show or appearing on the New York Times bestseller list would be unambiguously good, but below that it&amp;rsquo;s just a matter of what my expectations are. Is 1,000 copies good? 10,000? Who is to say? And as it&amp;rsquo;s my first time around at this particular game, I have no expectations whatsoever. So LS is right in her advice: the optimistic response is better than the blank stare and shrug of the shoulders that I would otherwise give.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this void of information, any and all scraps are welcome to the starved author. The internet, of course, is a vast source of entrails and tea leaves that have to be prodded, scried (?) and stirred to reveal their Nostradamus-clear prophecies. But something is better than nothing so, data addict that I am, I autogoogle and troll for all those scraps it provides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, then, are some of the nicer-smelling entrails I have found so far (in addition to those I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned earlier in this weblog).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That someone would pick up your book and read it is a great compliment. If they reach the end, more so. If they actually put finger to keyboard to say something about it, then that&amp;rsquo;s very heartwarming indeed. I&amp;rsquo;ve got lots of great feedback from friends, but there is of course every reason for the sceptical author to suspect these people of gilding the lilly a bit when they tell me what a fine book it is. Not that I&amp;rsquo;m ungrateful, you understand - far from it. Bring on those compliments! I just reserve my judgement sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So particular thanks goes to people I don&amp;rsquo;t know. People like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.persephonesboxblog.blogspot.com/2006/08/book-meme.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Persephone&lt;/a&gt;, who wrote this in answer to one of those book Q&amp;amp;A topics that go around the weblogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;8. **One book you are currently reading?**
&gt; 
&gt; 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No-One Makes You Shop at Wal-Mart&lt;/em&gt;
by Tom Slee. Well, actually I finished it a while ago, but I&amp;rsquo;m still
paging through it thinking about the arguments he presents. It&amp;rsquo;s very
provocative. Out of all these books, read that one first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can tell you, that makes great reading. Thanks a million Persephone - you are indeed a sage. Other recent weblog mentions include the &lt;a href=&#34;http://progecon.wordpress.com/2006/08/18/the-economics-of-wal-mart/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Relentlessly Progressive Economics&lt;/a&gt; blog and the Danish &lt;a href=&#34;http://observationsandstories.blogspot.com/2006/08/nobody-makes-you-shop-at-wal-mart.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Observations and Stories&lt;/a&gt;, who both reproduce a bit from my online &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tomslee.net/excerpt.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;excerpt&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks to both of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there are people who use the title for their own purposes. Kerry Howley is assistant editor of Reason Online, the libertarian-capitalist online magazine. Her article &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reason.com/links/links080106.shtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Has Wal-Mart Peaked?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; argues that Wal-Mart&amp;rsquo;s recent setbacks in Germany and Korea may be a harbinger of troubles to come for the beast of Bentonville, and that those who fear Wal-Mart may therefore be worrying without reason. &lt;del&gt; &lt;/del&gt;She says&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The fear Wal-Mart inspires is nicely encapsulated in the title of Tom Slee&#39;s recent book [_No One Makes You Shop At Wal-Mart: The Deception of Personal Choice._](http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ISBN=189707106X%20/ref=nosim/reasonmagazineA/) Slee argues that Wal-Mart is a scourge we bring upon ourselves by
forsaking the good of the community for the false idol of individual
choice. But it was the individual choices of individual consumers in
Germany and South Korea that sent Wal-Mart packing.
&gt; 
&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t actually disagree with her on this. Wal-Mart&amp;rsquo;s global dominance is certainly not a foregone conclusion, as (among others) the Guardian recently &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/comment/story/0,,1856891,00.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;mentioned&lt;/a&gt; its less-than-stellar progress with Asda in the UK, speculating that Wal-Mart may be too American to succeed globally. I don&amp;rsquo;t think that weakens my book, mind you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another libertarian who has (more deliberately) helped to promote the book is the open-minded Alex Tabarrok of Marginal Revolution, who said this in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2006/08/market_failure_.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a recent post&lt;/a&gt; about a story I pointed him to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Thanks to Tom Slee for the pointer. I hope to say more about his interesting new book,[ No one Makes You Shop at Wal-Mart](http://www.web.net/%7Etslee/), in the future. Contrary to the title it&#39;s about how markets fail, not a defense of Wal-Mart!
&gt; 
&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether or not he does say more (and I hope he does, of course, but hey, he&amp;rsquo;s a busy guy), here is the effect on my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tomslee.net&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;main web site&lt;/a&gt; of that one little mention (click for a clearer image).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://whimsley.typepad.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/daily_usage_200608.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://whimsley.typepad.com/whimsley/images/daily_usage_200608.png&#34; alt=&#34;Daily_usage_200608&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I track my sales on amazon.com (I haven&amp;rsquo;t been tracking them on .ca and .co.uk yet, but there&amp;rsquo;s time for that to start.) During August my ranking has been bouncing around between 60,000 and 300,000 (probably 60,000 means someone has bought a copy, and 300,000 means no one has bought one for a while). Here is what the graph looks like (from my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zohosheet.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zohosheet&lt;/a&gt;); a low point is a good thing. Not very legible I fear, but this is about as clear as I can make it - right click and choose View Image to see it more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.zohosheet.com/publicgraphs/27654.png&#34; alt=&#34;Amazon Sales Ranking - http://www.zohosheet.com&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another fine thing is that you get to mix with eminent neighbours. I get a kick out of looking in bookstores and libraries at who is next to me on the shelves. At a local store, philosopher Peter Singer (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rodalestore.com/webapp/wcs/stores/servlet/ProductDisplay?catalogId=10002&amp;amp;storeId=10051&amp;amp;productId=47486&amp;amp;langId=-1&amp;amp;nav_wt=search&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Way We Eat&lt;/a&gt;) of Animal Liberation fame is my neighbour. At the local library, Anthony Giddens (&lt;a href=&#34;http://old.lse.ac.uk/collections/meetthedirector/RunawayWorldPR.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Runaway World&lt;/a&gt;) is right next door. In the online list of &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.uvic.ca/eqhr/calendar/resources-books.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Working for Change&lt;/a&gt; resources at the University of Victoria I&amp;rsquo;m hanging out with Vandana Shiva, author of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southendpress.org/2004/items/Biopiracy&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Biopiracy&lt;/a&gt;. This is all pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s about it I think. Or wait, maybe someone has mentioned the book in the last twenty minutes. Wait a sec, I&amp;rsquo;ll just check google again&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No? Oh well. Maybe again&amp;hellip;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Update: **apparently if you can write about sex with some panache, then going to the book store is &lt;a href=&#34;http://girlwithaonetrackmind.blogspot.com/2006/08/shopping.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;far more rewarding&lt;/a&gt; (not safe for work!). Good for her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Update again: **I assumed Kerry Howley was a he. Wrong. I&amp;rsquo;ve corrected the references above; thanks to David Weigel for putting me right.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				I wish...		</title>
      <link>/post/i_wish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2006 08:37:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/i_wish/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;No idea who this is, except he calls himself &amp;ldquo;Psychomike&amp;rdquo;. He must have some information about book sales that I don&amp;rsquo;t have&amp;hellip;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;There is even a book out now, NO ONE MAKES YOU SHOP AT WAL-MART: THE DECEPTION OF PERSONAL CHOICE. It&#39;s by Tom Slee, and it has become the rallying cry for liberal city councils all over the nation.
&gt; 
&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link: &lt;a href=&#34;http://linkfilter.net/?s=j;user=1792&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;linkfilter.net - fresh links daily&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Book Review in Winnipeg Free Press		</title>
      <link>/post/book_review_in_/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2006 09:22:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/book_review_in_/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to MC for letting me know about this. From Sunday&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.winnipegfreepress.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Winnipeg Free Press&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;**A different take on consumer power**
&gt; 
&gt; 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sunday, July 30th, 2006. Reviewed by Lindsey Wiebe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;WE
make choices every day,&amp;quot; writes Ontario author Tom Slee. &amp;ldquo;We choose the
clothes we wear, the way we travel, the movies we watch, and the places
we shop.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even with all this choice, Slee says, the rich are getting richer, while the middle class and poor are losing ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;What has gone wrong?&amp;rdquo; he asks in this thought-provoking mix of academic and social critique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why is it that with more choices than any in society in history, we do not get what we want?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These basic questions form the underpinnings of this first book by the Waterloo software professional and researcher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In
it, Slee explores the pitfalls of a free-market economy; in particular,
what he refers to as &amp;ldquo;MarketThink,&amp;rdquo; the idea that consumers control the
market, and can hold corporations accountable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slee does his
best to debunk this mindset, arguing that even the most reasonable of
individual decisions can produce negative results for the general
public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the book revolves around the fictional foibles of Jack and Jill, who live in the made-up town of Whimsley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slee uses the characters to illustrate the routine conflicts between personal and public gain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should
Jack support a downtown department store, or visit a newly opened
big-box development? And does it really matter if Jill leaves litter in
a public park, when surely others will be more environmentally
conscious?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No One Makes You Shop at Wal-Mart also draws on
real-world examples of difficult choices, tackling everything from the
issue of herd mentality to the problem of &amp;ldquo;free-riders,&amp;rdquo; those who act
in their own best interests while assuming, often mistakenly, that
others will work for the public good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slee&amp;rsquo;s reasoning is
persuasive, and his examples numerous and far-reaching: the contentious
subject of international pollution credits, for one, or the perennial
public vs. private school debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But although No One Makes You
Shop at Wal-Mart is more accessible than the average academic text, it
still falls short of mass-market appeal, and those unfamiliar with game
theory might find some sections slower than others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slee&amp;rsquo;s
pacing is often sluggish, and the overall arrangement of material feels
unfocused. The sheer number of examples to deconstruct is also a little
daunting, an ironic flaw in a book about the dilemmas of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slee may have been better off focusing on fewer but more detailed examples to plead his case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On
the positive side, Slee&amp;rsquo;s in-text citations are clear and easy to
follow, and readers hoping to learn more about the complexities of
decision-making will come out with a solid list of followup books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No
One Makes You Shop at Wal-Mart doesn&amp;rsquo;t qualify as light summer reading.
However, the book does offer an intriguing critique of dominant ideas
on consumer power, and puts forward a valid argument for the benefits
of collective decision-making and regulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;_Lindsey Wiebe is a Free Press reporter._
&gt; 
&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				bytech is a discerning individual		</title>
      <link>/post/bytech_is_a_dis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2006 21:26:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/bytech_is_a_dis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Doing one of my periodic googles for the book title, I came across this post by one &amp;ldquo;bytech&amp;rdquo; on a webmasters&#39; forum. Obviously a Manitoban of taste and insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Quote:
Originally Posted by blind2web:
&gt;&gt; 
&gt;&gt; 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Nobody forces American or British companies to move to low cost countries; these decisions are made in Britain and America by Britains and Americans. &amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;bytech says: &amp;ldquo;While I agree with you, there is a hook to this. I discovered it after reading &amp;ldquo;No One Makes You Shop At Wal-Mart&amp;rdquo;. It put a whole new meaning to the word &amp;ldquo;choice&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;d recommend the book to almost anyone. You&amp;rsquo;ll see your life from there-on in a whole new way.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you bytech!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.v7n.com/forums/forum-lobby/33924-indian-webmasters-2.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Indian Webmasters - Page 2 - Webmaster Forum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Featured Item		</title>
      <link>/post/featured_item/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2006 21:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/featured_item/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a featured item in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rabble.ca/bookstore/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;rabble bookstore&lt;/a&gt;. Nice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Book Review in This Magazine		</title>
      <link>/post/book_review_in_-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2006 11:22:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/book_review_in_-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thismagazine.ca/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This Magazine&lt;/a&gt; reviews_ No One Makes You Shop at Wal-Mart_ in its July/August 2006 edition. Here is what _This_ has to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;In our free society, even socially and economically progressive outlooks buy into the notion of personal consumer choice. Don&#39;t like Wal-Mart&#39;s labour practices? If that&#39;s the case, they say, vote with your feet and shop somewhere else. But, ironically, this belief reinforces the unrealistically simplified world view Tom Slee calls MarketThink -- the philosophical bedrock of capitalism -- which claims that rational choices will always lead to good outcomes. By examining the complications arising from the choices we make, Slee shows that free choice is actually a deception, and that instead of consistently achieving the best results, a society based on individual choice will often collectively experience negative outcomes, such as, ironically, a limit to the amount of choice we are offered. The solution? In framing the ideas of social philosophers and economists in an accessible way that brings the philosophical to the realm of the practical, Slee makes a solid case for collective action in a world of choice that is inherently interconected, putting to shame the simplistic assumptions of the free market world view. -- _Vladi Ivanov_
&gt; 
&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Update: **The review is now &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thismagazine.ca/issues/2006/07/walmart.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Book Review		</title>
      <link>/post/book_review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2006 23:31:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/book_review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Good news! the first review of &lt;em&gt;No One Makes You Shop At Wal-Mart&lt;/em&gt; has appeared!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bad news: it&amp;rsquo;s not what I&amp;rsquo;d call glowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, in the interests of full and fair disclosure, and gritting my teeth, I hereby reproduce the whole thing. I understand that the protocol for real authors is that you don&amp;rsquo;t criticize reviews, and I&amp;rsquo;ll do my best imitation of a real author and bite my tongue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s from the June 2006 edition of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quillandquire.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Quill &amp;amp; Quire&lt;/a&gt;, p. 51.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Anyone who has tried to shepherd a child through the endless rows of toys in a department store with the proviso that only one item may be purchased knows the emotional devastation that can be wrought from the dilemma of too many choices. It&#39;s the deceptive nature of choice in our society that provides the focal point for Tom Slee&#39;s philosophical inquiry into how and why we do certain things, even when our decisions conflict with our moral compass.
&gt; 
&gt; 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slee, a research scientist and software professional, is intrigued by the notion that a society marketing itself as full of wondrous choices is nonetheless marked by a happiness quotient that&amp;rsquo;s in continual decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do have choices, from whether or not to smoke, drive vehicles with poor safety records, eat foods high in trans fats, or buy certain brands of shoes and clothing. But Slee wonders whether those choices are determined by free will or are driven by a hidden hand, a cultural subtext that provides only the illusion of freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate his points, Slee creates a number of scenarios in the fictitious community of Whimsley, where Jack and Jill deal with issues such as the conflict between shopping in a suburban big box or supporting downtown independent stores, or the pros and cons of using lawyers during a divorce. All of these things, Slee argues, involve different levels of choice, and in some situations, a lack of choice actually results in a better outcome. He also explores the world of game theory with respect to choice, and analyzes the role of what he calls MarketThink &amp;ndash; the logic of the so-called free market that has driven economics for the past few decades (also known as globalization or corporate control).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Slee&amp;rsquo;s approach is often difficult to follow as he tries to piece together these various strands. It&amp;rsquo;s almost as if Slee falls victim to having too many choices with regard to settling on a writing style, making for an uneven text that could have benefited from more coherence and continuity. Slee also makes numerous references to the notion of collective action as an alternative to MarketThink, but this thesis is never really developed, leaving the reader wondering why Slee chose not to explore what seems like a logical conclusion to the book&amp;rsquo;s central issue. - &lt;em&gt;Matthew Behrens, a writer and editor in Toronto.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oddly enough, I actually knew Mr. Behrens slightly many years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How could this review be rephrased? how about this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;emotional ... philosopical ... moral.
&gt; 
&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh well. On to the next one!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>
				Book Launch!		</title>
      <link>/post/book_launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2006 22:46:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/book_launch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://whimsley.typepad.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/wm_launch.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://whimsley.typepad.com/whimsley/images/wm_launch.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Wm_launch&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The date for a book launch at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wordsworthbooks.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the local bookstore&lt;/a&gt; has been set. Here&amp;rsquo;s the poster (click to enlarge).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
