<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>airbnb-data | Tom Slee</title>
    <link>/category/airbnb-data/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/airbnb-data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>airbnb-data</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2017 19:06:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>airbnb-data</title>
      <link>/category/airbnb-data/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Airbnb data collection: announcement</title>
      <link>/post/airbnb-data-collection-announcement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2017 19:06:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/airbnb-data-collection-announcement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;            I&#39;ve been doing the Airbnb data collection thing for about four years now, off and on, with my first post being on [October 19, 2013](http://tomslee.net/2013/10/notes-on-airbnbs-new-york-business.html).
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been interesting, rewarding, and useful for quite a few people, and I think it has helped to push the debate on Airbnb forward in some cases. But there is a time for every season and I think this effort has done what it can, and it&amp;rsquo;s time to move on. I&amp;rsquo;ll continue until the end of the year, and I&amp;rsquo;ll complete any commitments I have made to individuals and groups, but as of the end of the year I will stop running regular data collections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few notes / reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve already fallen behind on responding to requests, and I won&amp;rsquo;t be taking more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My code is on github (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tomslee/airbnb-data-collection&#34;&gt;https://github.com/tomslee/airbnb-data-collection&lt;/a&gt;) for anyone who wants to continue and the bulk of the data I have collected will remain at http://tomslee.net/airbnb-data-collection-get-the-data. It could be much better, but it&amp;rsquo;s there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others are doing a better job of making public data accessible (including the excellent Murray Cox at &lt;a href=&#34;http://insideairbnb.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Inside Airbnb&lt;/a&gt; obviously).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People doing serious research tend to roll their own (it&amp;rsquo;s not rocket science) or go to commercial outfits like AirDNA who collect more detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cities looking for a partner in managing short-term rentals may consider groups like Host Compliance &lt;a href=&#34;https://hostcompliance.com&#34;&gt;https://hostcompliance.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the feedback and contributions, and all the fascinating conversations I&amp;rsquo;ve had through this project. Onwards and upwards&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
