<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Tom Slee</title>
    <link>https://tomslee.github.io/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Tom Slee</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2006--{year}</copyright>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://tomslee.github.io/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Workarounds in decision support systems</title>
      <link>https://tomslee.github.io/publication/workaround-medical/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2019 21:48:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tomslee.github.io/publication/workaround-medical/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div class=&#34;ABSTRACT&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers from Harvard and MIT warn us about &amp;ldquo;Adversarial attacks on medical machine learning&amp;rdquo;, in which &amp;ldquo;a small, carefully designed change in how inputs are presented to a system&amp;hellip; completely alter its output, causing it to arrive at manifestly wrong conclusions.&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6433/1287&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;) That&amp;rsquo;s only half the story&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adversarial-attacks-and-workarounds-in-medical-machine-learning&#34;&gt;Adversarial attacks and workarounds in medical machine learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not like the Harvard/MIT article is &lt;em&gt;purely&lt;/em&gt; about adversarial attacks. Early on the authors point out that the American medical claims approval process is plagued by many competing financial interests, &amp;ldquo;providers [i.e. doctors and hospitals] seeking to maximize and payers [insurance companies] seeking to minimize reinbursement.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the remainder of the paper focuses almost exclusively on the problem of adversarial attacks by healthcare providers. Deep learning algorithms may be uncannily accurate over a well-defined data set, but they are also fragile if a sample steps in an unexpected direction, and this fragility leaves them open to &amp;ldquo;attack&amp;rdquo;. Most blatantly, the authors show, doctors could modify medical images to change the diagnosis, even as the image appears unchanged to the human eye. Then there are grey areas, like rotations of an image, or a careful choice of words in notes, that pushes the system to give unexpected results. How should the medical system handle a techique that seems so accurate and yet so easily misled?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;workarounds&#34;&gt;Workarounds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adversarial attacks are &amp;ldquo;inputs to a machine learning model that are intentionally crafted to force the model to make a mistake&amp;rdquo;: that is, you take an input that the model classifies correctly and you tweak it so that it is classified incorrectly. &lt;em&gt;Workarounds&lt;/em&gt; are the opposite of adversarial attacks: inputs that are intentionally crafted to force the model to &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt; a mistake. That is, you take an input that is incorrectly classified by the model and tweak it so that it is correctly classified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the best machine learning systems are, after all, statistical engines with non-zero error rates, so incorrectly classified examples will always be with us. And of course in the real world there are ambiguities in any data set, to the boundaries between classes are not as sharp as a labelled training set may make it seem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adversarial examples may be novel, but in the automated workplace workarounds have become routine, even if they are often overlooked. Automated systems shift decision-making from &amp;ldquo;front line&amp;rdquo; workers to a system, but as these systems have entered the workplace, many professionals have learned a new and often unacknowledged skill: they have become experts at making the system work properly.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://tomslee.github.io/ox-hugo/tensorflow-playground.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 1: Schematic view of a machine learning model. The data points are shown with their &amp;#34;true&amp;#34; values of blue or orange, and the background shade marks the areas that the model categorizes as &amp;#34;blue&amp;#34; or &amp;#34;orange&amp;#34;. The adversarial example changes a correctly-classified &amp;#34;orange&amp;#34; data point into an incorrectly-classified one, while the _workaround_ changes an incorrectly-classified data point into a correctly classified one. The image was built from  [Tensorflow Playground](https://playground.tensorflow.org))&#34; /&gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Figure 1: Schematic view of a machine learning model. The data points are shown with their &amp;ldquo;true&amp;rdquo; values of blue or orange, and the background shade marks the areas that the model categorizes as &amp;ldquo;blue&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;orange&amp;rdquo;. The adversarial example changes a correctly-classified &amp;ldquo;orange&amp;rdquo; data point into an incorrectly-classified one, while the &lt;em&gt;workaround&lt;/em&gt; changes an incorrectly-classified data point into a correctly classified one. The image was built from  &lt;a href=&#34;https://playground.tensorflow.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tensorflow Playground&lt;/a&gt;)
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As just one example, legal scholar Jennifer Raso explored the changing jobs of Ontario case workers when a new automated decision system was introduced. Instead of making their own judgements about client needs, case workers are now to enter data into the system, which would make a decision according to well-defined rules. She &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssrn.com/abstract=3062620&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;writes about how the social service case workers responded&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While new technologies may attempt to deskill and decentre front-line decision-makers, transforming them into data entry clerks, caseworkers learn how to expertly translate and input client data to produce decisions that more closely match their interpretation of clients’ needs and welfare laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea will be familiar to anyone who has read James C. Scott&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://yalebooks.yale.edu/book/9780300078152/seeing-state&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Seeing Like a State&lt;/a&gt;: certain schemes to improve the human condition assume, and impose, a simplified and idealized way of working and living that neglects the unruly irregularities of real life. Managed systems commonly rely on a certain level of workaround to even function: hence the effectiveness of the &amp;ldquo;work to rule&amp;rdquo; as a form of protest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;American healthcare systems have their own workarounds. The rigidities of automated billing systems recently produced a memorable essay by Atul Gawande entitled &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2018/11/12/why-doctors-hate-their-computers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Why Doctors Hate Their Computers&lt;/a&gt;, documenting many of the challenges experienced by physicians as new decision support systems have been introduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said that adversarial attacks and workarounds are opposites, but in another way they are very similar. Surprisingly there is no way to distinguish unambiguously between an adversarial attack and a workaround in real-world environments within machine learning theory. Attempts to define &amp;ldquo;attacks&amp;rdquo; refer to &amp;ldquo;intent&amp;rdquo;, but who is to say what that is? Many examples focus on cases where &amp;ldquo;ground truth&amp;rdquo; is unambiguous (a picture of a bus is &amp;ldquo;obviously&amp;rdquo; not a picture of a monkey). Examples that are clearly artificial and intentional are reflections of lab research, not of how systems will play out in the wild. Some machine learning practitioners have gone so far as to define &amp;ldquo;attacks&amp;rdquo; as any attempt by a subject to influence the outcome of a machine learning system, which makes an attacker of anyone who has put effort into writing their resume in the hopes of getting a job. But don&amp;rsquo;t take all this from me: if you want to hear an expert opinion on this definition problem, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sFhD6ABghf8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this talk by David Evans&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes down to it, both adversarial examples and workarounds are deliberate changes to inputs in order to generate desired outputs. Machine learning systems are statistical, and however accurate they may be over a large data set, statistics will not say whether any one individual answer is correct. For complex tasks such as medical diagnosis certified &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; answers are often not available. And if the &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; answer is not well-defined, who is to say whether an intentional change is correcting a mistake or corrupting a correct answer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will workarounds be needed for the next generation of deep learning medical systems? We can&amp;rsquo;t say for sure yet, but history suggests that they will. There is a long history of technical innovations that are designed around idealized and simplified models of behaviour, and which underestimate the complexities of &amp;ldquo;edge cases&amp;rdquo; in real life. Witness the over-enthusiasm around self-driving cars a couple of years ago, that is now being confronted with the messiness of reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article is not completely silent on the topic of workaroudns: it does reference a paper from almost 20 years ago titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/192577&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Physician Manipulation of Reimbursement Rules for Patients: Between a Rock and a Hard Place&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, which says this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been suggested that some insurers are &amp;ldquo;gaming&amp;rdquo; patients and physicians&amp;mdash;tricking them into paying for covered services by routinely denying coverage but then approving services that are subsequently appealed, knowing that time and other constraints will prevent some appeals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So doctor workarounds may be responses not only to technical deficiencies in the system, but also to real or perceived bad faith on the part of the insurers (or their suppliers) who are responsible for the system itself. And why should doctors have faith in these systems? Big money is at work on both sides, and the incentives for insurance companies to &amp;ldquo;optimize&amp;rdquo; is at least as strong as for the doctors. They face incentives to fix inaccuracies that lead to overbilling, but not those blind spots that lead to underpayments; to label edge cases in training sets in such a way as to minimize payments; to redefine payment schedules around the observed behaviour of the systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to interventions, Finlayson et al make two recommendations. The first is to procrastinate: to avoid stifling innovation by prematurely enforcing demands for robustness. The second is to increase supervision of medical practitioners, to check that they do not &amp;ldquo;tamper&amp;rdquo; with the data. Such an approach not only neglects any consideration of insurance companies, but it also rules out workarounds. It removes any room for doctors&amp;rsquo; discretion and judgement, and reduces the role of physician to that of a managed and supervised data entry technician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssrn.com/abstract=3363342&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;written elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;, most machine learning systems of any interest are &lt;em&gt;incentive incompatible.&lt;/em&gt; The subjects who provide the inputs and the consumers of the outputs have different and conflicting interests. And in such an arrangement additional rules are not just likely, but inevitable. The problem with procrastination is that it favours the consumers and, more than anyone, the providers of the system. A natural response to problems is to demand more complete data, better data, and closer supervision of data entry. Without a check on insurance companies, medical machine learning systems will not be a cure for a damaged health system.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The incompatible incentives of private sector AI</title>
      <link>https://tomslee.github.io/publication/oup_private_sector_ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tomslee.github.io/publication/oup_private_sector_ai/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Tom Slee&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;ABSTRACT&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Algorithms that sort people into categories are plagued by incompatible incentives. While more accurate algorithms may address problems of statistical bias and unfairness, they cannot solve the ethical challenges that arise from incompatible incentives.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Subjects of algorithmic decisions seek to optimize their outcomes, but such efforts may degrade the accuracy of the algorithm. To maintain their accuracy, algorithms must be accompanied by supplementary rules: &amp;ldquo;guardrails”&amp;rdquo;that dictate the limits of acceptable behaviour by subjects. Algorithm owners are drawn into taking on the tasks of governance, managing and validating the behaviour of those who interact with their systems.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The governance role offers temptations to indulge in regulatory arbitrage. If governance is left to algorithm owners, it may lead to arbitrary and restrictive controls on individual behaviour. The goal of algorithmic governance by automated decision systems, social media recommender systems, and rating systems is a mirage, retreating into the distance whenever we seem to approach it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;performances-and-ethics&#34;&gt;Performances and ethics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individuals present themselves to the world in a set of performances,
and tune their presentation depending on the setting.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We may not
believe there is a single “real” person behind these performances, but
we do expect to see a &amp;ldquo;coherence among setting, appearance, and manner&amp;rdquo;
(p.25). Individuals whose performances differ too much between one
setting and another risk being called dishonest or two-faced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since branding became important to companies, they too have presented
themselves to the world in a set of performances. Financial incentives
demand they tune their performance to the setting&amp;mdash;offering a generous
and humane face in their public communications and a harsher and less
empathetic one when managing the bottom line&amp;mdash;while the ethical demand
for coherence remains. Two decades ago the movement against
corporate-led globalization highlighted these presentation gaps,
captured in the dissonance between Nike&amp;rsquo;s empowering “Just Do It” to
those who bought their sneakers, and the far-from-empowering sweatshop
conditions endured by those who made them.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One legacy of that
movement is a set of ethical consumption initiatives, in which
independent fair trade and sustainability certifications provide an
opportunity for companies to demonstrate a coherent set of values behind
their performances.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in the debates over AI ethics, it is technology companies who find
themselves accused of being two-faced, of presenting themselves through
their brands as value-driven organizations while deploying
algorithms&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that are too often biased, opaque, and unfair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debates have taken on new importance following the explosion of
&amp;ldquo;deep learning&amp;rdquo; techniques.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Private sector investment in what is
now often broadly labelled “AI” is dominated by major internet platform
companies such as Facebook, Amazon, Apple, Google, and Microsoft: while
seven billion dollars have been invested in start-ups, these companies
have invested four to five times that amount.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Platform companies
are also leaders in deploying deep learning algorithms: deployments in
other industries are in their early stages, yet many of us encounter
deep learning algorithms daily through Google search, Facebook News
Feed,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Apple Siri, Amazon Alexa, Uber pricing,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Airbnb
search,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and more.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If this chapter focuses on the major
platform companies, it is because they are charting paths and setting
precedents that more traditional industries will follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to a series of scandals and compelling arguments from
critics and academics,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the platform companies have recognized
that they must establish reputations as responsible stewards of these
powerful technologies if they are to avoid a costly backlash. They have
issued public commitments to ethical AI, asserted their belief in
fairness and transparency, and proclaimed their commitment to building
diverse organizational cultures to prevent bias from creeping in to
their technological services and products.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; They have set up
ethics boards and industry organizations such as &lt;em&gt;Partnership on
AI,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-14&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and participated in governmental bodies such as the EU&amp;rsquo;s
High-Level Expert Group on Artificial Intelligence.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The platform companies have also taken on the task of designing fairness
into their systems,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-16&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; investing in research into fairness and
transparency in machine learning, articulating statistical criteria for
fairness, designing mechanisms for explaining machine-learning results,
assembling unbiased data sets for key problems, and more. The technical
approach is a good fit: technical criteria play to the strengths of
technology companies. Standards set public benchmarks and provide
protection from future accusations. Auditable criteria incorporated into
product development and release processes can confirm compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also financial incentives to adopt a technical approach:
standards that demand expertise and investment create barriers to entry
by smaller firms, just as risk management regulations create barriers to
entry in the financial and healthcare industries.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-17&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenges of bias and fairness are far from solved, and critics
continue to play an essential role. External investigations, audits and
benchmarks reveal deficiencies missed by internal efforts.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-18&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But
auditable algorithms and data sets do promise mechanisms for closing the
presentation gap between brand and algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charges of bias and unfairness expose AI algorithms that are, in some
sense, not good enough, and emphasize that the solution is better
algorithms. But another set of problems may become &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; significant as
algorithms become more accurate: when they become too good not to use.
This chapter focuses on this second gap, which cannot be translated into
research projects to be solved by computer scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;algorithms-create-incentives&#34;&gt;Algorithms create incentives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much debate around AI ethics imagines an algorithm as a camera,
recording and portraying some aspect of the external world. It asks:
does the system portray the world fairly and faithfully? When it
categorizes things, does it do so in a way that corresponds to the real
world?&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social scientists have long known that algorithms do not just portray
the world, they also change it. In the words of Donald MacKenzie, an
algorithm is &amp;ldquo;an engine, not a camera&amp;rdquo;.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-20&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-20&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Introducing a new
algorithm means sorting people differently; if people care about how
they are sorted, they respond.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-21&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-21&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once people respond, the dynamic between algorithms and their subjects
becomes strategic: economists are familiar with such situations and
developed the tools of game theory to think about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sociologists have shown that responses to algorithms are ubiquitous and
subtle. The most seemingly innocuous decisions prompt changes in what is
being measured. In 1927 Dutch authorities separated the cause of death
entered into statistical records from that recorded on the public death
certificate, a change that was followed by “a considerable increase in
Amsterdam of cases of death from syphilis, tabes, dementia paralytics,
&amp;hellip; and suicide.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-22&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-22&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Why? Because these causes of death could now be
entered into the statistical record without adding to the pain of
newly-bereaved relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sociologists have also shown how surprisingly powerful algorithmic
engines can be. In their book &lt;em&gt;Engines of Anxiety&lt;/em&gt;, Wendy Espeland and
Michael Sauder describe the impact of US News and World Report rankings
on US law schools.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-23&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-23&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Employers use the rankings to identify good
students, so students rely on them when choosing where to apply, so law
schools who want the best students must play the game, and rankings end
up dominating many aspects of law school life. The dynamic is described
beautifully by Kieran Healy in a review of Espeland and Sauder&amp;rsquo;s book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The academic legal establishment did not so much fall into this trap
as become entangled in it. Like a fly touched by the thread of a
spider&amp;rsquo;s web, they were at first only lightly caught up, but then
found that each move they made in response only drew them in more
tightly.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-24&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-24&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://tomslee.github.io/ox-hugo/2019-ai-incentives.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 1: A schematic algorithm that takes input from subjects and sorts them into output categories, which in turn have consequences for the subject.&#34; /&gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Figure 1: A schematic algorithm that takes input from subjects and sorts them into output categories, which in turn have consequences for the subject.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chapter draws loosely on social science perspectives to sketch what
can happen when we respond to algorithms, and the consequences of our
responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine an algorithm that sorts individual subjects into categories. If
subjects care about their assigned category, then they have an incentive
to optimize how they present themselves: changing their inputs to
achieve a better output. Their decision to invest in this presentation
depends on three factors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presentation cost.&lt;/strong&gt; The subject must be able to afford to change
their presentation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sensitivity.&lt;/strong&gt; Changing an input feature is worthwhile only if it
affects the output.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact.&lt;/strong&gt; Changing an output is worthwhile only if it has significant
consequences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Algorithms with high impact, high sensitivity, and low presentation
costs give subjects strong incentives to change their presentation.
Following the terminology of economics, we can loosely say that such
algorithms have high &lt;strong&gt;elasticity&lt;/strong&gt;. The data distributions on which
elastic algorithms operate when deployed will differ from those on which
it was trained. When data distributions change, accuracy is lost:
elastic algorithms may also be &lt;strong&gt;fragile&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are reasons to believe that machine learning systems, and
specifically deep learning systems, may be particularly elastic and
fragile, mapping on to each of the factors above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First is the low cost of experimentation around presentation. Deep
learning techniques called Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs)&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-25&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-25&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
have become excellent at generating images or videos or text that look
as if they were created by humans or depict &amp;ldquo;real world&amp;rdquo; artefacts.
These uses have been grouped together under the name &amp;ldquo;deep
fakes&amp;rdquo;.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-26&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-26&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is growing evidence that the remarkable accuracy of deep learning
models may be accompanied by high sensitivity. In 2013 a phenomenon
called &amp;ldquo;adversarial examples&amp;rdquo; was discovered: certain image
perturbations, undetectable to the human eye, nevertheless caused deep
learning algorithms to make obvious mistakes when classifying the image
(as measured by human judgment).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-27&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-27&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; An example is given in Figure 2.
The original examples were curiosities,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-28&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-28&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but the more it has been
studied, the more general the phenomenon appears to be.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-29&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Fragility
could be a general feature of deep learning models:&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-30&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-30&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; they
typically optimize millions of parameters, and the more parameters, the
bigger the &amp;ldquo;attack surface&amp;rdquo; as each parameter provides a new opportunity
for subjects to tweak.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://tomslee.github.io/ox-hugo/2019-ai-adversarial-macaw.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 2: A slight perturbation of this picture of a macaw causes it to be classified as a bookcase.[fn:30]&#34; /&gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Figure 2: A slight perturbation of this picture of a macaw causes it to be classified as a bookcase.[fn:30]
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many machine learning systems have high impact because they are deployed
at scale. We may not want to invest in optimizing our LinkedIn profile,
but if we are seeking work and that&amp;rsquo;s where employers look we have
little alternative but to put our best foot forward. Scale also creates
market opportunities for cost-lowering intermediaries who can assist
with optimization, as with search-engine optimization, reputation
management or, come to that, tax accountancy. Scale makes algorithmic
flaws matter more than those of any one human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As deep learning drives the next generation of decision support systems
and recommender systems, their elasticity and fragility may become
increasingly important. To make matters more serious, these weaknesses
will not show up in proofs of concept or early stage deployments, where
the output has little impact on subjects. It is only when algorithms are
operating at scale that the incentive to invest becomes large, making
the system more fragile.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://tomslee.github.io/ox-hugo/2019-ai-response-landscape.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 3: Responses to algorithms include combinations of valid and invalid input, which may sustain or erode the intent of the algorithm.&#34; /&gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Figure 3: Responses to algorithms include combinations of valid and invalid input, which may sustain or erode the intent of the algorithm.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;incentives-drive-responses&#34;&gt;Incentives drive responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 3 classifies responses to algorithms. Algorithms require &lt;em&gt;valid&lt;/em&gt;
input if they are to give correct output. Algorithms also have an
&lt;em&gt;intent&lt;/em&gt; that can be affected positively or negatively by the actions of
subjects. In general, the output is a proxy for this less well-defined
intent.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-31&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-31&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Each input arrow may be paired with each output arrow,
giving four classes of response. While algorithm designers may prefer to
permit only valid inputs which sustain the intent of the system, all
four combinations can have ethical justifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valid inputs can be understood by thinking about a simple rule-based
system, such as a hiring filter that sorts applicants based solely on
educational achievements. The input is a subject&amp;rsquo;s educational
achievements: genuine achievements are valid and fake achievements are
not. The intent of the system is to give the hiring manager a good set
of interviewees: if he or she is happy with their applicants the
system&amp;rsquo;s intent is satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In cases that economists describe as separating equilibria for
signalling and screening games,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-32&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-32&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; valid inputs sustain the intent
of the algorithm. If the applicant pool consists of two qualities from
an employment perspective (high and low), and if getting a degree is
easier for high quality people than for low quality people, then only
high-quality people find it worth investing in a degree. The beauty of
such an arrangement is that it is &amp;ldquo;incentive compatible&amp;rdquo;: an “invisible
hand” guides subjects so that, if they respond to incentives, the
algorithm continues to satisfy its intent without additional governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it is equally costly for low quality applicants to obtain a degree as
for high quality applicants, then the degree ceases to be a useful
signal. Applicants may continue to invest in degrees, but the algorithm
will no longer separate the wheat from the chaff. This is the
game-theoretic case of a &amp;ldquo;pooling equilibrium&amp;rdquo;, where valid responses
erode the intent of the algorithm. We know how the verb describing valid
responses in pooling equilibria declines: I follow the letter of the
law, you teach to the test, he or she games the system. The problems of
pooling equilibria have been elevated to the status of a Law:
&amp;ldquo;Goodhart&amp;rsquo;s Law&amp;rdquo; states that &amp;ldquo;When a measure becomes a target, it ceases
to be a good measure&amp;rdquo; to which we might add a corollary that becomes
important below: “When a measure is not a target, it ceases to be
optimized”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ethics of optimizing responses using valid input is not simple. One
reason Google keeps its search algorithms secret is to prevent gaming by
the search-engine optimization industry,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-33&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-33&#34;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but when it comes to the
tax system their attitude is different. A secret tax system would be
unacceptable, of course. Accused of dodging taxes by moving $23bn to
Bermuda, Google responded simply: &amp;ldquo;We pay all of the taxes due and
comply with the tax laws in every country we operate in around the
world&amp;rdquo;.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-34&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-34&#34;&gt;34&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Workarounds&lt;/em&gt; are a class of invalid inputs that nevertheless sustain
the intent of the system. Legal scholar Jennifer Raso investigated the
operation of Ontario Works, a welfare-eligibility decision
system,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-35&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-35&#34;&gt;35&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and found that case workers became experts at working
with the system, on occasions entering false data to coax results that
line up with their professional judgment. Whether dealing with bugs in
the program (an inapplicable field for some applicants would also be a
required field in the system) or with weaknesses in the model, case
workers break the letter of the law to follow the spirit. Similar
behaviour has been seen among US doctors seeking to provide their
patients with good outcomes from insurance systems.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-36&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-36&#34;&gt;36&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any statistical algorithm has error cases, and many systems cannot
function without workarounds from those it manages or their agents,
which is why &amp;ldquo;work to rule&amp;rdquo; actions in some industrial settings are
common: if you follow the letter of the law too strictly, nothing gets
done. The unappreciated role of workarounds is one reason why James C.
Scott argues that “certain schemes to improve the human condition have
failed.”&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-37&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-37&#34;&gt;37&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Scott is arguing against top-down “high-modernist”
schemes, and algorithmic platforms certainly fall into this category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final case is invalid input that also erodes an algorithm&amp;rsquo;s intent,
often described in security terms, as &lt;em&gt;attacks&lt;/em&gt; on the algorithm. There
are an increasing number of algorithms for which “opting out” is not an
option, including ratings platforms. &lt;em&gt;Botto Bistro&lt;/em&gt; is a San Francisco
restaurant which was unhappy with what they saw as unethical treatment
by Yelp, who also refused the restaurant&amp;rsquo;s request to be removed from
the platform. In response, &lt;em&gt;Botto Bistro&lt;/em&gt; encouraged its customers to
enter over-the-top one-star reviews, seeking to achieve the lowest
rating on Yelp. The campaign called attention to some dubious practices
and contradictions in Yelp&amp;rsquo;s operations: perhaps a case of principled
protest or subversive humour, sabotaging one system in pursuit of a
higher goal.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-38&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-38&#34;&gt;38&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more sophisticated and complex the algorithm, the more the lines
between these four categories blur. Once algorithms move beyond simple
inputs such as birth dates and educational qualifications, the criteria
for distinguishing valid from invalid input become uncertain. Reputation
systems such as Yelp, eBay, and Uber replace &amp;ldquo;true or false&amp;rdquo; criteria
with more nebulous notions of &amp;ldquo;authenticity&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;honesty&amp;rdquo; and defend
them not by appeals to correctness but to free speech.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-39&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-39&#34;&gt;39&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Who can
say what a “four-star” rating really means?&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-40&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-40&#34;&gt;40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the output side too, an unambiguous “ground truth” output is often
unavailable outside the labelled training sets of the laboratory, so the
distinction fades between an attack and a workaround. Even adversarial
examples, which seem so obvious, have resisted definition. One technical
attempt is to say they are input “that an attacker has intentionally
designed to cause the model to make a mistake”&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-41&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-41&#34;&gt;41&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but for an
individual real-world case identifying “intent” or “mistake” may both be
impossible, and so the classification of “attacker” fails too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;responses-demand-guardrails&#34;&gt;Responses demand guardrails&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, algorithms that classify people are
“incentive-incompatible”: if subjects follow their incentives then the
algorithm ceases to function as designed. To sustain their accuracy,
algorithms need external rules to limit permissible responses. These
rules form a set of &lt;em&gt;guardrails&lt;/em&gt; which implement value judgments,
keeping algorithms functioning by constraining the actions of
subjects.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-42&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-42&#34;&gt;42&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Move fast and break things” norms of disruptive innovation encourage
algorithm designers to postpone thinking about guardrails. They may not
be needed in low-elasticity environments such as proofs of concept or in
early-stage deployments. Still, successful deployments at scale will
require guardrails and so, even if problems of bias and fairness could
be solved, the grail of algorithmic governance&amp;mdash;of impartial and
automatic algorithmic data-driven and evidence-based
decision-making&amp;mdash;would fall at this hurdle. Algorithms and their
guardrails form an inseparable pair. Code is law, until it is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existence of a scalable algorithm does not imply the existence of
equally scalable guardrails: guardrails must deal with specific contexts
and factors outside the original model, which only grow in number as
algorithms draw on an ever-increasing volume and variety of data in
pursuit of accuracy. Attempts to implement automated moderation have
repeatedly failed, and companies have resorted instead to what Astra
Taylor calls &amp;ldquo;fauxtomation&amp;rdquo;: behind the scenes real people do the work
to simulate the effects of an algorithm, because the technology is not
up to the task.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-43&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-43&#34;&gt;43&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The work of content moderators has been described
recently by Sarah Roberts&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-44&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-44&#34;&gt;44&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and Tarleton Gillespie.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-45&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-45&#34;&gt;45&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Algorithms without guardrails may become ungovernable. Social media
recommender algorithms, for example, have all three qualities needed for
high elasticity. Experimentation is affordable, content producers can
discover the kind of content to which the recommendation algorithm is
sensitive because they get fast feedback in the form of view counts, and
the impact of the recommendation system is high. High elasticity means
strong incentives to optimize individual outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The YouTube recommendation algorithm&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-46&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-46&#34;&gt;46&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; suffers from
ungovernability. In a widely read article, James Bridle provided a tour
through the long tail of bizarre content appearing on YouTube Kids as
producers experiment to gain views.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-47&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-47&#34;&gt;47&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As just one example, they
would rely on keyword/hashtag association when generating new content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When some trend, such as Surprise Egg videos, reaches critical mass,
content producers pile onto it, creating thousands and thousands more
of these videos in every possible iteration&amp;hellip; branded content and
nursery rhyme titles and “surprise egg” all stuffed into the same word
salad to capture search results, sidebar placement, and “up next”
autoplay rankings&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A striking example of the weirdness is the Finger Family videos&amp;hellip; I
have no idea where they came from or the origin of the children&amp;rsquo;s
rhyme at the core of the trope, but there are &lt;strong&gt;at least 17 million
versions&lt;/strong&gt; of this currently on YouTube, and again they cover every
possible genre, with billions and billions of aggregated views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, it was Bridle&amp;rsquo;s essay going viral that made YouTube act, and
they did so by invoking community guidelines. The response seems like an
ethical platform making best efforts to implement guardrails that eject
malicious actors, but the story is not so simple. One channel removed
for violating the &amp;ldquo;family friendly&amp;rdquo; rule was that of Johnny
Tanner.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-48&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-48&#34;&gt;48&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Tanner said he could not discover what had prompted the
punishment, because he had no person to talk to. In defence of his
channel, he said, &amp;ldquo;The algorithm is the thing we had a relationship with
since the beginning. That&amp;rsquo;s what got us out there and popular&amp;hellip; We
learned to fuel it and do whatever it took to please the algorithm.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same article quotes Davey Orgill, who left his job to make superhero
parody videos, and whose channel reached two million viewers before
being shut down. He argued that &amp;ldquo;the platform is responsible for
encouraging&amp;hellip; objectionable, sexual, and violent superhero content
ostensibly oriented toward children&amp;hellip; YouTube blames it on these people
that were doing it, but for a year their algorithm pushed this
content&amp;hellip; People were doing it because it was creating millions and
millions and millions of views. They created a monster.&amp;rdquo; The left hand
of the recommendation algorithms promotes videos that the right hand of
the Community Guidelines would later forbid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bridle ends his essay this way: “The architecture they have built to
extract the maximum revenue from online video is being hacked by persons
unknown to abuse children, perhaps not even deliberately, but at a
massive scale,” but the disturbing videos are not “hacking” any more
than minimizing tax payments is hacking, they are responses driven by
the algorithm itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook&amp;rsquo;s News Feed algorithm also suffers from high elasticity and its
problems have also been framed as those of defence against malicious
actors. Former Facebook executive Antonio Garcia Martinez complained on
Twitter that &amp;ldquo;The same FB [Facebook] critics who call on the company to
take on responsibility for moderating content (an operational job they
(Facebook) don&amp;rsquo;t want, and had to be pressed to perform), will of course
be shocked, shocked at the human cost in reviewing billions of pieces of
random content&amp;rdquo;.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-49&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-49&#34;&gt;49&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But the requirement for guardrails .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intent of News Feed has changed over time and remains operationally
vague. Mark Zuckerberg announced in January 2018 that “I&amp;rsquo;m changing the
goal I give our product teams from focusing on helping you find relevant
content to helping you have more meaningful social interactions”.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-50&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-50&#34;&gt;50&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Facebook designed News Feed as a system with large rewards for high
circulation, so encouraging participants to invest heavily in optimizing
their outcomes. Attempting to move on from the resulting Clickbait
headlines, Facebook has doubled down on building in-house algorithmic or
fauxtomatic solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook&amp;rsquo;s entire project, when it comes to news, rests on the
assumption that people&amp;rsquo;s individual preferences ultimately coincide
with the public good, and that if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t appear that way at first,
you&amp;rsquo;re not delving deeply enough into the data.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-51&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-51&#34;&gt;51&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assumption fails. An elastic system based on “the data” causes the
foundations on which it is built to shift. The incentive-incompatible
News Feed algorithm demands guardrails to police the content it
generates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Facebook does not want the job of managing news content, it could
hand it to the news industry. Emily Bell of the Columbia Journalism
School explains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At some point, if they really want to address this, they have to say,
‘This is good information&amp;rsquo; and ‘This is bad information.&amp;lsquo; They have to
say, ‘These are the kinds of information sources that we want to
privilege, and these others are not going to be banned from the
platform, but they are not going to thrive.&amp;rsquo; In other words, they have
to create a hierarchy, and they&amp;rsquo;re going to have to decide how they&amp;rsquo;re
going to transfer wealth into the publishing market.”&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-52&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-52&#34;&gt;52&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook does want the job, or at least the money that comes with it.
Financial incentives demand that Facebook keep responsibility for News
Feed content, while insisting it has no accountability for the outcome
beyond making best efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media algorithms may be particularly prone to driving “gaming”
behaviour, but others are not immune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Allegheny Family Screening Tool (AFST) is a decision support system
used to predict child abuse or child neglect at the time of birth, and
to alert child services to children who may be at risk. The attentions
of child services can have a large effect on the lives of families whose
risk score is high. Contact with social services is one factor that may
lead to a high predictive score, so some families feel they must engage
in self-harming behaviour, withdrawing from “networks that provide
services, support, and community” to optimize their score. AFST might
“create the very abuse it seeks to prevent.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-53&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-53&#34;&gt;53&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facial recognition has long prompted civil liberties concerns.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-54&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-54&#34;&gt;54&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Guardrails are one of these concerns: is covering one&amp;rsquo;s face acceptable
behaviour around facial recognition software in public spaces? In a
trial deployment in London, police fined a man after he covered his face
and objected to subsequent police questioning.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-55&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-55&#34;&gt;55&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; More generally, as
the data sources used by insurance companies, potential employers, and
others expand, the potential for unusual or unorthodox behaviour
patterns to trigger inferences, for example based on outlier detection
algorithms, expands in tandem. Without protection against such
inferences, the unusual becomes the suspicious.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-56&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-56&#34;&gt;56&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If the guardrail
question: “what have you got to hide” becomes legitimate for authorities
to ask, the technology will have altered public norms for the worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Autonomous vehicles will need new guardrails to manage pedestrian
behaviour. At current levels of deployment, pedestrians will behave much
as they do around cars with drivers, but if self-driving becomes
commonplace then some may optimize their experience by stepping out
ahead of autonomous cars, in full confidence that the car will stop.
Should such pedestrian assertion become the norm, &amp;ldquo;autonomous vehicle
adoption may be hampered by their strategic disadvantage that slows them
down in urban traffic&amp;rdquo;.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-57&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-57&#34;&gt;57&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Perhaps, says Drive.ai board member
Andrew Ng, &amp;ldquo;we should partner with the government to ask people to be
lawful and considerate&amp;hellip; Safety isn&amp;rsquo;t just about the quality of the AI
technology.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-58&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-58&#34;&gt;58&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We can expect the self-driving car industry to seek
new guardrails that protect their own algorithms, yet discussion of
these guardrails are largely missing from conversations about the ethics
of autonomous vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, guardrails limit the autonomy of algorithmic subjects.
Algorithmic governance may encourage platforms to innovate with A/B
testing on their subjects, but the subjects themselves are constrained.
Some may be punished twice over: once by the algorithm for unorthodox
behaviour that it does not properly model, and a second time if they
fall foul of the guardrails while trying to avoid the first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;guardrails-create-temptation&#34;&gt;Guardrails create temptation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The algorithm-guardrail pairing creates temptations for platform owners
to indulge in arbitrage: exploiting presentation gaps to circumvent
regulation and to avoid brand damage. When algorithms encourage
behaviour that the guardrails forbid, platform companies may choose
whether to present themselves through their algorithm or through the
values imposed by their guardrails. Ethics calls for a consistent
presentation, but companies have a financial incentive to keep the gap
wide, and many activities can be seen in this light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One response is to frame problems in terms of the software development
lifecycle. Problems are bugs, and the software industry knows how to
deal with bugs: they are reported, they are fixed, and fixes are rolled
out to customers. It is a statement of faith that bugs are temporary,
and software improves through iterative refinement. If algorithmic
failings are bugs, external authorities have neither the jurisdiction
nor the expertise to fix them. But as we have seen, guardrail failures
are features not bugs: they are created by the incentives built into the
algorithm. In her book “Uberland”, Alex Rosenblat talks of Uber drivers
seeing &amp;ldquo;phantom requests&amp;rdquo; that appear briefly on the driver app but
vanish before they can respond.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-59&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-59&#34;&gt;59&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Phantom requests damage drivers&amp;rsquo;
prospects of earning bonuses that depend on maintaining a high
acceptance rate. Uber&amp;rsquo;s response to driver complaints was to blame it on
network problems and promise a fix. Without effective person-to-person
driver support, Uber denies drivers the option of a workaround, while
the language and practices of software development helps the company
avoid what would, in other companies, be a breach of contract with their
drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second response is to invoke value-based guardrails in an ad-hoc
manner. If algorithmic governance leads to behaviour on the part of
subjects that may damage the brand, it is tempting to let it go until
the prospect becomes too dangerous. YouTube&amp;rsquo;s actions around the YouTube
Kids channel fall into this pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Airbnb is an algorithmically-governed platform with a stated intent of
the building a community of regular people who live in their own home
and occasionally share it with strangers. Any guardrails to keep
behaviour within this mandate runs the risk of affecting Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s
earnings, and so there has been nothing in Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s systems to stop
hosts creating multiple listings, setting up organizations with
different &amp;ldquo;hosts&amp;rdquo; as fronts,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-60&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-60&#34;&gt;60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; or renting out listings for 365
nights a year. When the gap between algorithmic practices and stated
aims became too large in New York City, bringing the threat of
restrictions on Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s market, the company invoked guardrails to expel
a thousand hosts off its platform,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-61&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-61&#34;&gt;61&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; claiming that they were not
providing the experience their community expected.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-62&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-62&#34;&gt;62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Code was
overruled by brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A third temptation is to use the platform&amp;rsquo;s information resources to
hide or muddy the waters regarding algorithmic failures. Ryan Calo and
Alex Rosenblat have detailed the many ways in which Uber has used its
information to shape the behaviour of its drivers.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-63&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-63&#34;&gt;63&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The selective
and judicious release of data on an exclusive basis for collaboration
with academics or industry experts may also serve to shape the overall
perception of the company, whether individual papers are written
independently or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally: companies that become embedded into the infrastructure of our
lives have leverage when it comes to the presentation gap. Uber seeks to
become a privately-owned part of city transit infrastructure and uses
the data it has accumulated as a resource to be licensed back to the
cities in which they operate. Once integrated, cities cannot easily walk
away from the platform, problems on the platform become public concerns
regarding malicious actors, and cities&amp;rsquo; leverage regarding governance on
the Uber platform is lost. Smart City initiatives such as the Toronto
project led by Google subsidiary Sidewalk implicitly adopt this same
approach.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-64&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-64&#34;&gt;64&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;temptation-needs-policing&#34;&gt;Temptation needs policing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more powerful algorithms have become, the more it is clear that
market forces alone cannot solve the problems arising from the
incompatible incentives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Platform companies can sustain a gap between algorithm and guardrail in
part because Section 230 of the CDA absolves them of much responsibility
for the consequences of their governance failures, in the USA at least.
Chesney and Citron&amp;rsquo;s recent paper on Deep Fakes&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-65&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-65&#34;&gt;65&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; identify the
platform companies as the &amp;ldquo;least cost avoider&amp;rdquo;: the actor who is in the
best position to fix problems of incompatible incentives. The previous
section claimed that platforms currently have an incentive to take
ownership of the problem, but not to fix it: that taking ownership is
currently a way to ward off regulation. Revisiting Section 230 and its
equivalents in other jurisdictions does the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of society&amp;rsquo;s most serious classification problems is that of
“innocent or guilty”, and it worth remembering that data-driven
statistical methods are not permitted in this venue: evidence is instead
strictly limited in scope. One reason is that people should not be
punished for factors that, while they may correlate with criminality,
lie outside their control. Another is that it would demand that people,
especially members of less privileged groups, invest in optimizing their
risk scores for fear of contact with the criminal system.
“Evidence-based” statistical decision-making has become increasingly
used in areas of the justice system such as parole and even sentencing
and its use raises both problems. While the trend remains towards
data-driven decisions, voices are being raised against use of actuarial
risk assessment in the justice system.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-66&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-66&#34;&gt;66&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Restricting data use goes
against the grain of the current drive to a data-driven society, but as
the impact of algorithmic decisions grows, ideas from this venue where
decisions matter the most may become more prominent in the years to
come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition rules provide another avenue to resolving incentive
problems. Algorithmic ranking systems can become powerful institutions
in and of themselves: part of the infrastructure of society. Advantages
accrue to the company that owns the infrastructure when it is also
competing in the market for services that exploit that
infrastructure.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-67&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-67&#34;&gt;67&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some industries the essential infrastructure is heavily regulated and
controlled, while services built on that infrastructure are opened for
innovation. Airport infrastructure is separated from the operation of
airlines. Core banking functions are strictly regulated &amp;ndash; perhaps not
as strictly as some would like &amp;ndash; while many countries are experimenting
with open banking laws to permit innovation on top of this
infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside the realm of regulation, we can look to alternative models.
Wikipedia is the only non-profit in the top ranks of web sites, and it
has been significantly less affected by the problems of incompatible
incentives. Many, the present author included, thought that Wikipedia
would be unable to maintain quality over nearly two decades, but it has
proven sceptics wrong. Perhaps the anonymous nature of contributions
removes many of the distorting incentives associated with
self-promotion, perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s because Wikipedia is largely free of
“viral” phenomena, but something is working on Wikipedia that is not
working at YouTube, Facebook, or Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, deep learning algorithms may be more intelligent than
previous generations of machine learning, but they are not more robust.
There may be a faint technical path forward for problems of bias and
unfairness, but algorithms are engines, not cameras, and pervasive
incompatible incentives will remain. Algorithms require guardrails, and
technology companies are ill-suited and ill-positioned to design or
implement these value-based rules. Guardrails become constraints on
people&amp;rsquo;s behaviour and yet, in cases of high elasticity, effective
governance may still be elusive. The pairing of the algorithm and
guardrails tempts companies to engage in regulatory arbitrage, providing
a requirement for external action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank the editors for their invitation and guidance, and
the other contributors who took part in the Toronto workshop for their
inspiration and expertise. I acknowledge helpful conversations with John
Slee and Lynne Supeene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essential texts concerning the mechanisms and consequences of sorting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Geoffrey C. Bowker and Susan Leigh Star, &lt;em&gt;Sorting Things Out: Classification and Its Consequences&lt;/em&gt; (The MIT Press, 1999)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wendy Nelson Espeland and Michael Sauder, &lt;em&gt;Engines of Anxiety: Academic Rankings, Reputation, and Accountability&lt;/em&gt; (Russell Sage Foundation, 2016)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bernard E. Harcourt, &lt;em&gt;Against Prediction&lt;/em&gt; (University of Chicago Press, 2006)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jane Jacobs, &lt;em&gt;The Death and Life of Great American Cities&lt;/em&gt; (New York: Random House, 1961)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Donald MacKenzie, An Engine, Not a Camera: How Financial Models Shape Markets (MIT Press, 2007).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;James C. Scott, &lt;em&gt;Seeing Like a State: How Certain Schemes to Improve the Human Condition Have Failed&lt;/em&gt; (Yale University Press, 1998)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thomas C. Schelling, &lt;em&gt;Micromotives and Macrobehavior&lt;/em&gt; (W.W. Norton and Company, 1978)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-1&#34;&gt;Draft of a chapter contributed to the &lt;em&gt;Oxford Handbook of Ethics of Artificial Intelligence&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Markus Dubber, Frank Pasquale, and Sunit Das, Oxford University Press 2019. This version March 31, 2019. The opinions expressed in this chapter are those of the author and do not represent the views or policies of SAP. This essay is also available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssrn.com/abstract=3363342&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://ssrn.com/abstract=3363342&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-2&#34;&gt;Erving Goffman, &lt;em&gt;The Presentation of Self in Everyday Life&lt;/em&gt; (Garden City, New York: Doubleday, 1959).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-3&#34;&gt;Naomi Klein, &lt;em&gt;No Logo&lt;/em&gt; (Toronto: Knopf Canada, 2000).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-4&#34;&gt;Kimberley Ann Elliott and Richard B. Freeman, &lt;em&gt;Can Labor Standards Improve Under Globalization?&lt;/em&gt; (Washington DC: Institute for International Economics, 2003).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-5&#34;&gt;In this chapter, &lt;em&gt;algorithm&lt;/em&gt; is shorthand for any automated data-driven sorting systems, including classifying, scoring, rating, and ranking. Algorithms may be implemented by computers but may also be implemented through organizational policies and practices.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-6&#34;&gt;Alex Krizhevsky, Ilya Sutskever, and Geoffrey Hinton, “Imagenet Classification with Deep Convolutional Neural Networks,” in &lt;em&gt;Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems&lt;/em&gt;, 2012, 1097&amp;ndash;1105, &lt;a href=&#34;https://papers.nips.cc/paper/4824-imagenet-classification-with-deep-convolutional-neural-networks.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://papers.nips.cc/paper/4824-imagenet-classification-with-deep-convolutional-neural-networks.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-7&#34;&gt;McKinsey Global Institute, “Artificial Intelligence: The Next Digital Frontier?” (McKinsey &amp;amp; Company, June 2017), &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mckinsey.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.mckinsey.com/&lt;/a&gt; /media/McKinsey/Industries/Advanced%20Electronics/Our%20Insights/How%20artificial%20intelligence%20can%20deliver%20real%20value%20to%20companies/MGI-Artificial-Intelligence-Discussion-paper.ashx.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-8&#34;&gt;K. Hazelwood et al., “Applied Machine Learning at Facebook: A Datacenter Infrastructure Perspective,” in /2018 IEEE International Symposium on High Performance Computer Architecture (HPCA)/, 2018, 620&amp;ndash;29, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/HPCA.2018.00059&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1109/HPCA.2018.00059&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-9&#34;&gt;Alexander Sergeev and Mike Del Balso, “Horovod: Fast and Easy Distributed Deep Learning in TensorFlow,” &lt;em&gt;ArXiv:1802.05799 [Cs, Stat]&lt;/em&gt;, February 15, 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1802.05799&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/1802.05799&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-9&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-10&#34;&gt;Malay Haldar et al., “Applying Deep Learning To Airbnb Search,” &lt;em&gt;ArXiv:1810.09591 [Cs, Stat]&lt;/em&gt;, October 22, 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1810.09591&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/1810.09591&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-10&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-11&#34;&gt;Nicola Jones, “Computer Science: The Learning Machines,” &lt;em&gt;Nature News&lt;/em&gt; 505, no. 7482 (January 9, 2014): 146, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/505146a&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/505146a&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-11&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-12&#34;&gt;Frank Pasquale, The Black Box Society: The Secret Algorithms That Control Money and Information (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 2015); Cathy O&amp;rsquo;Neill, Weapons of Math Destruction: How Big Data Increases Inequality and Threatens Democracy (Crown Random House, 2016); Safiya Umoja Noble, Algorithms of Oppression: How Search Engines Reinforce Racism (New York University Press, 2018); Solon Barocas and Andrew Selbst, “Big Data&amp;rsquo;s Disparate Impact,” California Law Review 104 (2016): 671, &lt;a href=&#34;https://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2477899&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2477899&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-12&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-13&#34;&gt;Google, “Our Principles,” Google AI, accessed February 1, 2019, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ai.google/principles/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://ai.google/principles/&lt;/a&gt;; Microsoft, “Our Approach: Microsoft AI Principles,” Microsoft, accessed February 1, 2019, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/ai/our-approach-to-ai&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/ai/our-approach-to-ai&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-13&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-14&#34;&gt;The Partnership on AI, “The Partnership on AI,” The Partnership on AI, accessed February 1, 2019, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.partnershiponai.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.partnershiponai.org/&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-14&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-15&#34;&gt;European Commission, “High-Level Expert Group on Artificial Intelligence,” 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ec.europa.eu/digital-single-market/en/high-level-expert-group-artificial-intelligence&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://ec.europa.eu/digital-single-market/en/high-level-expert-group-artificial-intelligence&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-15&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-16&#34;&gt;Margaret Mitchell et al., “Model Cards for Model Reporting,” in &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency&lt;/em&gt;, FAT* &amp;lsquo;19 (New York, NY, USA: ACM, 2019), 220&amp;ndash;229, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1145/3287560.3287596&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1145/3287560.3287596&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-16&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-17&#34;&gt;Malcolm Campbell-Verduyn, Marcel Goguen, and Tony Porter, “Big Data and Algorithmic Governance: The Case of Financial Practices,” &lt;em&gt;New Political Economy&lt;/em&gt; 22, no. 2 (March 4, 2017): 219&amp;ndash;36, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1080/13563467.2016.1216533&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/13563467.2016.1216533&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-17&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-18&#34;&gt;Joy Buolamwini and Timnit Gebru, “Gender Shades: Intersectional Accuracy Disparities in Commercial Gender Classiﬁcation,” n.d., 15; Inioluwa Deborah Raji and Joy Buolamwini, “Actionable Auditing: Investigating the Impact of Publicly Naming Biased Performance Results of Commercial AI Products,” n.d., 7.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-18&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-19&#34;&gt;Sam Corbett-Davies and Sharad Goel, “The Measure and Mismeasure of Fairness: A Critical Review of Fair Machine Learning,” &lt;em&gt;ArXiv:1808.00023 [Cs]&lt;/em&gt;, July 31, 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1808.00023&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/1808.00023&lt;/a&gt;; Alexandra Chouldechova, “Fair Prediction with Disparate Impact: A Study of Bias in Recidivism Prediction Instruments,” &lt;em&gt;Big Data&lt;/em&gt; 5, no. 2 (June 2017): 153&amp;ndash;63, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1089/big.2016.0047&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1089/big.2016.0047&lt;/a&gt;; Arvind Narayanan, &lt;em&gt;Tutorial: 21 Fairness Definitions and Their Politics&lt;/em&gt;, accessed January 27, 2019, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jIXIuYdnyyk&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jIXIuYdnyyk&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-19&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-20&#34;&gt;Donald MacKenzie, &lt;em&gt;An Engine, not a Camera: How Financial Models Shape Markets&lt;/em&gt; (MIT Press, 2007).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-20&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-21&#34;&gt;Danielle Keats Citron and Frank A. Pasquale, “The Scored Society: Due Process for Automated Predictions,” SSRN Scholarly Paper (Rochester, NY: Social Science Research Network, 2014), &lt;a href=&#34;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=2376209&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=2376209&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-21&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-22&#34;&gt;Geoffrey C. Bowker and Susan Leigh Star, &lt;em&gt;Sorting Things Out: Classification and Its Consequences&lt;/em&gt; (The MIT Press, 1999). p 141
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-22&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-23&#34;&gt;Wendy Nelson Espeland and Michael Sauder, &lt;em&gt;Engines of Anxiety: Academic Rankings, Reputation, and Accountability&lt;/em&gt; (Russell Sage Foundation, 2016).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-23&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-24&#34;&gt;Kieran Healy, “By the Numbers - Wendy Espeland and Michael Sauder, Engines of Anxiety: Academic Rankings, Reputation, and Accountability (New York, Russell Sage, 2016),” &lt;em&gt;European Journal of Sociology / Archives Européennes de Sociologie&lt;/em&gt; 58, no. 3 (December 2017): 512&amp;ndash;19, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1017/S0003975617000315&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S0003975617000315&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-24&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-25&#34;&gt;Ian Goodfellow et al., “Generative Adversarial Networks,” in &lt;em&gt;Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 27&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Z. Ghahramani et al. (Curran Associates, Inc., 2014), 2672&amp;ndash;2680, &lt;a href=&#34;http://papers.nips.cc/paper/5423-generative-adversarial-nets.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://papers.nips.cc/paper/5423-generative-adversarial-nets.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-25&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-26&#34;&gt;Robert Chesney and Danielle Keats Citron, “Deep Fakes: A Looming Challenge for Privacy, Democracy, and National Security,” SSRN Scholarly Paper (Rochester, NY: Social Science Research Network, July 14, 2018), &lt;a href=&#34;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=3213954&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=3213954&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-26&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-27&#34;&gt;Ian J. Goodfellow, Jonathon Shlens, and Christian Szegedy, “Explaining and Harnessing Adversarial Examples,” &lt;em&gt;ArXiv:1412.6572 [Cs, Stat]&lt;/em&gt;, December 19, 2014, &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1412.6572&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/1412.6572&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-27&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-28&#34;&gt;Christian Szegedy et al., “Intriguing Properties of Neural Networks,” &lt;em&gt;ArXiv:1312.6199 [Cs]&lt;/em&gt;, December 20, 2013, &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1312.6199&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/1312.6199&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-28&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-29&#34;&gt;Nicholas Carlini and David Wagner, “Audio Adversarial Examples: Targeted Attacks on Speech-to-Text,” &lt;em&gt;ArXiv:1801.01944 [Cs]&lt;/em&gt;, January 5, 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1801.01944&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/1801.01944&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-29&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-30&#34;&gt;Adi Shamir et al., “A Simple Explanation for the Existence of Adversarial Examples with Small Hamming Distance,” &lt;em&gt;ArXiv:1901.10861 [Cs, Stat]&lt;/em&gt;, January 30, 2019, &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.10861&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.10861&lt;/a&gt;; Alexandru Constantin Serban and Erik Poll, “Adversarial Examples - A Complete Characterisation of the Phenomenon,” &lt;em&gt;ArXiv:1810.01185 [Cs]&lt;/em&gt;, October 2, 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1810.01185&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/1810.01185&lt;/a&gt;; Ali Shafahi et al., “Are Adversarial Examples Inevitable?,” September 27, 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;https://openreview.net/forum?id=r1lWUoA9FQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://openreview.net/forum?id=r1lWUoA9FQ&lt;/a&gt;; David Stutz, Matthias Hein, and Bernt Schiele, “Disentangling Adversarial Robustness and Generalization,” &lt;em&gt;ArXiv:1812.00740 [Cs, Stat]&lt;/em&gt;, December 3, 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1812.00740&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/1812.00740&lt;/a&gt;; Dimitris Tsipras et al., “Robustness May Be at Odds with Accuracy,” May 30, 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1805.12152v3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/1805.12152v3&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-30&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-31&#34;&gt;Cathy O&amp;rsquo;Neill, &lt;em&gt;Weapons of Math Destruction: How Big Data Increases Inequality and Threatens Democracy&lt;/em&gt; (Crown Random House, 2016).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-31&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-32&#34;&gt;Michael A. Spence, “Job Market Signaling,” &lt;em&gt;The Quarterly Journal of Economics&lt;/em&gt; 87, no. 3 (1973): 355&amp;ndash;74; Joseph E. Stiglitz, &lt;em&gt;Whither Socialism?&lt;/em&gt;, The Wicksell Lectures (Cambridge Massachusetts, London England: The MIT Press, 1994).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-32&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-33&#34;&gt;Jonathan Rosenberg, “The Meaning of Open,” December 21, 2009, &lt;a href=&#34;http://googleblog.blogspot.ca/2009/12/meaning-of-open.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://googleblog.blogspot.ca/2009/12/meaning-of-open.html&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-33&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-34&#34;&gt;Reuters, “Google Shifted $23bn to Tax Haven Bermuda in 2017, Filing Shows | Technology | The Guardian,” &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;, January 3, 2019, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2019/jan/03/google-tax-haven-bermuda-netherlands&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2019/jan/03/google-tax-haven-bermuda-netherlands&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-34&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-35&#34;&gt;Jennifer Raso, “Displacement as Regulation: New Regulatory Technologies and Front-Line Decision-Making in Ontario Works,” &lt;em&gt;Canadian Journal of Law &amp;amp; Society / La Revue Canadienne Droit et Société&lt;/em&gt; 32, no. 1 (April 2017): 75&amp;ndash;95, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1017/cls.2017.6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1017/cls.2017.6&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-35&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-36&#34;&gt;Matthew K. Wynia et al., “Physician Manipulation of Reimbursement Rules for Patients: Between a Rock and a Hard Place,” &lt;em&gt;JAMA&lt;/em&gt; 283, no. 14 (April 12, 2000): 1858&amp;ndash;65, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.283.14.1858&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.283.14.1858&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-36&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-37&#34;&gt;James C. Scott, &lt;em&gt;Seeing Like a State: How Certain Schemes to Improve the Human Condition Have Failed&lt;/em&gt; (Yale University Press, 1998).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-37&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-38&#34;&gt;Tom Slee, “In Praise of Fake Reviews,” &lt;em&gt;The New Inquiry&lt;/em&gt;, October 29, 2014, &lt;a href=&#34;https://thenewinquiry.com/in-praise-of-fake-reviews/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://thenewinquiry.com/in-praise-of-fake-reviews/&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-38&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-39&#34;&gt;James Grimmelmann, “Three Theories of Copyright in Ratings,” &lt;em&gt;Vanderbilt Journal of Entertainment and Technology Law&lt;/em&gt; 14, no. 4 (2012): 85&amp;ndash;887.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-39&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-40&#34;&gt;Abbey Stemler, “Feedback Loop Failure: Implications for the Self-Regulation of the Sharing Economy,” SSRN Scholarly Paper (Rochester, NY: Social Science Research Network, April 1, 2016), &lt;a href=&#34;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=2754768&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=2754768&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-40&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-41&#34;&gt;Justin Gilmer et al., “Motivating the Rules of the Game for Adversarial Example Research,” &lt;em&gt;ArXiv:1807.06732 [Cs, Stat]&lt;/em&gt;, July 17, 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1807.06732&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/1807.06732&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-41&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-42&#34;&gt;The metaphor adopts the designer&amp;rsquo;s point of view; from a subject&amp;rsquo;s point of view, “straitjacket” may be more appropriate.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-42&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-43&#34;&gt;Astra Taylor, “The Automation Charade,” Logic Magazine, October 2, 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;https://logicmag.io/05-the-automation-charade/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://logicmag.io/05-the-automation-charade/&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-43&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-44&#34;&gt;Sarah Roberts, “Commercial Content Moderation: Digital Laborers&amp;rsquo; Dirty Work,” in &lt;em&gt;Intersectional Internet: Race, Sex, Class and Culture Online&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Safiya Umoja Noble and Brendesha M Tynes, Digital Formations Series (Peter Lang Publishing, Inc., 2016), &lt;a href=&#34;https://intersectionalinternet.com/about/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://intersectionalinternet.com/about/&lt;/a&gt;; Sarah T. Roberts, &lt;em&gt;Behind the Screen: Content Moderation in the Shadows of Social Media&lt;/em&gt; (Yale University Press, 2019), &lt;a href=&#34;https://yalebooks.yale.edu/book/9780300235883/behind-screen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://yalebooks.yale.edu/book/9780300235883/behind-screen&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-44&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-45&#34;&gt;Tarleton GIllespie, /Custodians of the Internet: Platforms, Content Moderation, and the Hidden Decisions That Shape Social Media/ (Yale University Press, 2018), &lt;a href=&#34;https://yalebooks.yale.edu/book/9780300173130/custodians-internet&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://yalebooks.yale.edu/book/9780300173130/custodians-internet&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-45&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-46&#34;&gt;Paul Covington, Jay Adams, and Emre Sargin, “Deep Neural Networks for YouTube Recommendations,” in &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 10th ACM Conference on Recommender Systems&lt;/em&gt;, RecSys &amp;lsquo;16 (New York, NY, USA: ACM, 2016), 191&amp;ndash;198, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1145/2959100.2959190&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1145/2959100.2959190&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-46&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-47&#34;&gt;James Bridle, “Something Is Wrong on the Internet,” &lt;em&gt;James Bridle&lt;/em&gt; (blog), November 6, 2017, &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@jamesbridle/something-is-wrong-on-the-internet-c39c471271d2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://medium.com/@jamesbridle/something-is-wrong-on-the-internet-c39c471271d2&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-47&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-48&#34;&gt;Charlie Warzel, “YouTube Is Addressing Its Massive Child Exploitation Problem,” &lt;em&gt;BuzzFeed News&lt;/em&gt;, November 22, 2017, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/charliewarzel/youtube-is-addressing-its-massive-child-exploitation-problem&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/charliewarzel/youtube-is-addressing-its-massive-child-exploitation-problem&lt;/a&gt;; Davey Alba, “YouTube Has A Massive Child Exploitation Problem. How Humans Train Its Search AI Is Partly Why.,” &lt;em&gt;BuzzFeed News&lt;/em&gt;, December 28, 2017, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/daveyalba/youtube-search-rater-algorithms-children-disturbing-videos&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/daveyalba/youtube-search-rater-algorithms-children-disturbing-videos&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-48&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-49&#34;&gt;Tweet since deleted.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-49&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-50&#34;&gt;Mark Zuckerberg, “One of Our Big Focus Areas for 2018,” Social Media, &lt;em&gt;Mark Zuckerberg&amp;rsquo;s Facebook Posts&lt;/em&gt; (blog), January 11, 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/zuck/posts/10104413015393571&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/zuck/posts/10104413015393571&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-50&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-51&#34;&gt;Farhad Manjoo, “Can Facebook Fix Its Own Worst Bug?,” &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt;, April 25, 2017, sec. Magazine, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/04/25/magazine/can-facebook-fix-its-own-worst-bug.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/04/25/magazine/can-facebook-fix-its-own-worst-bug.html&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-51&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-52&#34;&gt;Manjoo.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-52&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-53&#34;&gt;Virginia Eubanks, &lt;em&gt;Automating Inequality: How High-Tech Tools Profile, Police, and Punish the Poor&lt;/em&gt; (St. Martin&amp;rsquo;s Press, 2017), 169.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-53&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-54&#34;&gt;Lucas Introna and David Wood, “Picturing Algorithmic Surveillance: The Politics of Facial Recognition Systems,” &lt;em&gt;Surveillance &amp;amp; Society&lt;/em&gt; 2, no. &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; (2004): 177&amp;ndash;98, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1.1.117.7338&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1.1.117.7338&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-54&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-55&#34;&gt;Lizzie Dearden, “Man Fined £90 after Covering Face during Facial Recognition Trial in London,” &lt;em&gt;The Independent&lt;/em&gt;, January 31, 2019, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/crime/facial-recognition-cameras-technology-london-trial-met-police-face-cover-man-fined-a8756936.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/crime/facial-recognition-cameras-technology-london-trial-met-police-face-cover-man-fined-a8756936.html&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-55&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-56&#34;&gt;Sandra Wachter and Brent Mittelstadt, “A Right to Reasonable Inferences: Re-Thinking Data Protection Law in the Age of Big Data and AI,” SSRN Scholarly Paper (Rochester, NY: Social Science Research Network, September 13, 2018), &lt;a href=&#34;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=3248829&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=3248829&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-56&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-57&#34;&gt;Adam Millard-Ball, “Pedestrians, Autonomous Vehicles, and Cities,” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Planning Education and Research&lt;/em&gt; 38, no. 1 (2018), &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0739456X16675674&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0739456X16675674&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-57&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-58&#34;&gt;Russell Brandom, “Self-Driving Cars Are Headed toward an AI Roadblock,” The Verge, July 3, 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theverge.com/2018/7/3/17530232/self-driving-ai-winter-full-autonomy-waymo-tesla-uber&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.theverge.com/2018/7/3/17530232/self-driving-ai-winter-full-autonomy-waymo-tesla-uber&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-58&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-59&#34;&gt;Alex Rosenblat, &lt;em&gt;Uberland: How Algorithms Are Rewriting the Rules of Work&lt;/em&gt; (University of California Press, 2018), &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucpress.edu/book/9780520298576/uberland&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.ucpress.edu/book/9780520298576/uberland&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-59&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-60&#34;&gt;Luis Ferré-Sadurní, “Inside the Rise and Fall of a Multimillion-Dollar Airbnb Scheme,” &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt;, February 23, 2019, sec. New York, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/02/23/nyregion/airbnb-nyc-law.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/02/23/nyregion/airbnb-nyc-law.html&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-60&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-61&#34;&gt;Murray Cox and Tom Slee, “How Airbnb Hid the Facts in New York City,” February 7, 2016, &lt;a href=&#34;http://tomslee.net/how-airbnb-hid-the-facts-in-nyc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://tomslee.net/how-airbnb-hid-the-facts-in-nyc&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-61&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-62&#34;&gt;Kristen V. Brown, “Airbnb Admits That It Purged 1,500 Unflattering New York Listings Right before Data Release,” Splinter, accessed March 30, 2019, &lt;a href=&#34;https://splinternews.com/airbnb-admits-that-it-purged-1-500-unflattering-new-yor-1793854942&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://splinternews.com/airbnb-admits-that-it-purged-1-500-unflattering-new-yor-1793854942&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-62&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-63&#34;&gt;Ryan Calo and Alex Rosenblat, “The Taking Economy: Uber, Information, and Power,” &lt;em&gt;Columbia Law Review&lt;/em&gt; 117 (March 9, 2017), &lt;a href=&#34;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=2929643&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=2929643&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-63&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-64&#34;&gt;See the chapter by Ellen Goodman in this book.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-64&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-65&#34;&gt;Chesney and Citron, “Deep Fakes.”
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-65&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-66&#34;&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-66&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-67&#34;&gt;Lina M Khan, “Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Antitrust Paradox,” &lt;em&gt;The Yale Law Journal&lt;/em&gt; 126 (2017): 710&amp;ndash; 805.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-67&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Rise and Fall of the Sharing Economy</title>
      <link>https://tomslee.github.io/publication/rise_and_fall/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tomslee.github.io/publication/rise_and_fall/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Essay based on a presentation to the Symposium of the Ernst Schmidheiny Foundation,
Friday November 23, 2018. 9:20am—10am.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now ten years since some of the best known Sharing Economy
companies were founded, and about six years since the name &amp;ldquo;Sharing
Economy&amp;rdquo; became used to identify this wave of internet companies. In
that time we have seen claims that this is a new model of employment,
even that it is the future of work, and that it is fundamentally
changing the cities in which we live. But in recent years we&amp;rsquo;ve also
seen signs of a bubble. A few years ago the story of the Sharing Economy
would have been simple: here is a new model, and some people like it and
some do not, but it works. Now there is more scepticism, and the phrase
itself may be fading from public discourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This essay gives a quick tour of the sharing economy, from its
beginnings after the 2008 financial crash to today. I will walk through
some of the business models and some of the economics of this sector,
and sketch some of the controversies. There is another theme to the
essay, which is &amp;ldquo;who makes the future?&amp;rdquo; Is the world of work, for
example, built by technology companies in Silicon Valley, or can the
rest of the world have a say as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;2008-beginnings&#34;&gt;2008: Beginnings&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look at three companies which each started just about ten years
ago and which had a similar business model in common, even though the
people involved did not know each other at all. There was no name for it
at the time, but there was something in the air&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with Airbnb, which you will probably know is the
controversial short-term rental or holiday accommodation company, where
people rent out residential homes for use by tourists and other
visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2007, newly graduated design students Brian Chesky and Joe Gebbia
were looking for ways to make their end-of-month rental payments in San
Francisco when an industry conference came to town. They bought some
inflatable airbeds and offered accommodations to attendees looking for a
cheap place to stay. They were inundated with requests and realized
there may be a market for this kind of thing, and so &amp;ldquo;Airbed &amp;amp;
Breakfast&amp;rdquo; was born. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, the story has been one of hard work and growth. Running up
the limit on multiple credit cards to finance the very beginnings, they
got an early investment from Paul Graham&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Y-Combinator&lt;/em&gt; fund.
Struggling to get the site to take off, they went out to their biggest
city (New York) and got the hosts to have professional photos taken of
their rooms to make them more appealing; the bookings increased, and
professional photography continues to be the most effective way for a
host to attract guests. Other maneuvers included a breakfast-cereal
pitch around the Democratic convention in Chicago and a widely
criticized email campaign via Craigslist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the early tribulations, the now-trio of Chesky, Gebbia, and Nathan
Blecharczyk found themselves at the head of a phenomenon. In 2011 Airbnb
had 50,000 listings; in 2012 that number more than doubled to 120,000;
by the end of 2013 it was 550,000; in 2018 it is nearly 5 million
listings. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For comparison, the largest hotel company in the world by
number of rooms is the InterContinental Group with 775,000 rooms. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as Airbnb was getting started, two entrepreneurs were attending a
conference in Paris, and had a hard time finding a cab. These two were
Travis Kalanick, who was to go on to be the controversial CEO of Uber,
and Garrett Camp. They didn&amp;rsquo;t need to worry about paying rent, as both
were already rich from earlier technology ventures. Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be
great, they thought, if you could get a cab just by pressing a button on
the newly released iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its early days, Uber worked with limo companies to provide drivers,
but then they realized that a competitor named Lyft was using amateur
drivers rather than professionals, and Uber did not want to be left out.
So they set up Uber X, which is Uber Pop in most of Europe, and opened
up their business to independent drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uber&amp;rsquo;s growth has been even more dramatic than that of Airbnb. The
company has raised investment money like no other, raising tens of
billions of dollars in investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our third example is less well known now, but it was often talked about
as another archetype of the Sharing Economy. Here is how the company&amp;rsquo;s
web site described the founding story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a cold night in Boston in February of 2008 when Leah Busque
realized she was out of dog food for her 100-lb yellow lab, Kobe. Leah
thought to herself, &amp;ldquo;Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be nice if there was a place online I
could go to connect with my neighbors&amp;mdash;maybe one who was already at the
store at that very moment&amp;mdash;who could help me out?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this experience, TaskRabbit (formerly RUNmyERRAND), an online and
mobile marketplace that connects neighbors to get things done, was born
&amp;hellip; Neighbors helping neighbors&amp;mdash;it&amp;rsquo;s an old school concept
reimagined for today. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the typical tasks that people helped with was assembling Ikea
furniture. TaskRabbit had early successes and attracted a lot of
attention, but in the end it did not become the kind of global company
that Airbnb and Uber have become. Instead, after several years as an
independent company, it sold itself to Ikea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people&amp;rsquo;s problems don&amp;rsquo;t turn into multi-billion dollar companies.
Timing --- whether by luck or by skill &amp;ndash; was essential to their
success. Here is a set of things that had been put in place in the few
years before 2008, each of which was needed for Airbnb and Uber to take
off:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Broad-band internet. Many homes had computers, and many people were
increasingly comfortable with the Internet as a part of their daily
lives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Online payments. People were also getting used to using credit cards
on the Internet to pay for their purchases at Amazon, eBay, Expedia
and other early successes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mobile computing. Beyond that, we were entering the era of the
smartphone. The iPhone was released in 2007 and Uber, for one, could
not have been invented before the iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Social media. In the early years, pseudonyms and anonymity were the
norm on the Internet. As the famous cartoon caption went: &amp;ldquo;On the
Internet, nobody knows you&amp;rsquo;re a dog&amp;rdquo;. But starting with Facebook in
2006, many people were getting used to the idea of using real names.
TaskRabbit and Uber&amp;rsquo;s competitor Lyft both hooked into Facebook&amp;rsquo;s
user identification system as a part of their business model, and
Airbnb and others used Facebook accounts as proof of identity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rating systems. The use of ratings, particularly for Netflix movies
and Amazon books, but also through sites such as Yelp and
Travelocity, had spread and the five-star rating that is now
ubiquitous was becoming common.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cloud computing. Starting in 2006 Amazon started renting out
computer usage from its own massive data centres at bargain prices,
starting the era of cloud computing. This meant that new companies
could start up without buying expensive hardware: they could use
Amazon for their computing needs and get started much more cheaply.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crowdsourcing. The basic computing architecture of the Sharing
Economy is the &amp;ldquo;platform&amp;rdquo; where the company itself runs the
software, but those who provide the content come from outside. The
success of Wikipedia showed this could be done, and eBay showed you
could build a valuable company that way. YouTube was and continues
to be a remarkable example of this crowdsourced structure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though these were all present, the Sharing Economy brought with it
the shock of the new --- pressing a button on your phone and seeing a
car appear seemed like magic, and booking to stay in somebody&amp;rsquo;s house
half way around the world opened up new possibilities for travel. The
novelty of the experiences gave the new services an aura of cool, and
many people immediately thought: this is the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;2010-2015-rise&#34;&gt;2010 &amp;ndash; 2015: Rise&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Airbnb and Uber were not founded as Sharing Economy companies, because
the name did not exist. In the years 2010 to 2012 a set of other
companies were founded using a similar business model and commentators
looked for names to describe this trend. &amp;ldquo;Collaborative economy&amp;rdquo;^1^,
&amp;ldquo;circular economy&amp;rdquo;, &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and &amp;ldquo;the mesh&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; were all put forward, but in
the end the Sharing Economy won.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is a one-sentence description of the Sharing Economy, it may be
&lt;em&gt;Internet platforms for real-world services&lt;/em&gt;. The first few years of the
century had seen internet platforms for retail (Amazon and eBay), for
social media exchanges and advertising (Google and Facebook), and for
media (Netflix, Apple, YouTube). Of particular interest were eBay and
YouTube: crowdsourced platforms where the content seemed to appear by
magic. The Sharing Economy takes this model, but instead of uploading
videos the platform is used for people who provide real-world services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How far can crowdsourced Internet platforms go? Can their economic
benefits be applied to the service economy too? That&amp;rsquo;s what the Sharing
Economy phenomenon asks us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 2017 report for the World Economic Forum gives a three-point
definition.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; First is &amp;ldquo;The use of digital technologies to match
buyers and sellers,&amp;rdquo; which is similar to the point above. But they add
two other components. One is &amp;ldquo;Capitalizing on idle capacity&amp;rdquo;: the
service providers are generally offering something they already own, but
which they are not using right now. So the service providers are not
employees of the platform owners, they are independent actors who are
making use of their own assets. To go back to our three stories: perhaps
they have a car, and can drive for Uber; perhaps they have some spare
time and can run some errands for TaskRabbit; perhaps they have a spare
room and can put it on Airbnb. The other additional point is &amp;ldquo;trust
verification&amp;rdquo;, to which I&amp;rsquo;ll return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this framework, let&amp;rsquo;s look at some examples of companies that
started up in those years of 2010 to 2012. This was the era when
seemingly a million start-up plans were pitched as the &amp;ldquo;Uber for this&amp;rdquo;
or the &amp;ldquo;Airbnb for that&amp;rdquo;. But I want to start with something that is the
opposite. The Toronto Tool Library&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is a non-profit organization that
lets people rent tools for home projects. The organization is
geographically limited and community focused: it has no plans to drive
major stores out of business or to become a global behemoth. But it
matters to the story of the Sharing Economy because it draws on one of
the early images that promoted the idea, which is the story of the power
drill.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Many of us have a hand drill that sits on a shelf and is
hardly ever used and Rachel Botsman, who was one of the early promoters
of the Sharing Economy and helped to articulate it as a new development,
says: we don&amp;rsquo;t really want a drill, what we want is the hole it makes.
So why not share a drill instead of owning it? Sharing is sustainable,
it helps us get off the consumerist track of ownership, weighed down by
our goods. The drill was the embodiment of using &amp;ldquo;idle capacity&amp;rdquo;. It has
an appealing sustainability angle to it and also hints to a concept
called &amp;ldquo;access over ownership&amp;rdquo;: we don&amp;rsquo;t have to buy in to the bourgeois
and consumerist culture of ownership, we can tread more lightly on the
earth by dipping in and out of these sharing arrangements instead. It
was a catchy and attractive image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013 Airbnb was already taking off, and a natural extension of that
idea was to share meals. Airbnb said &amp;ldquo;you don&amp;rsquo;t need hotels, you just
need a platform where you can connect with other people.&amp;rdquo; Cookening,
Feastly and other sites applied the same logic to restaurants. If you
are travelling to a new city, why not eat like a local in their own
house? Again, the appeal here is to authenticity, to personal connection
rather than institutions and companies, and to the unusual combination
of small and big that crowdsourcing requires: many small individual
exchanges building a global platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tools and meals are fairly low risk, banged thumbs and food poisoning
aside, but finance is surely something different. Remember that we are
talking about a period right after the financial crisis, when personal
finances were stretched and banks were viewed with suspicion. So
companies like Lending Club took a lead from charities such as Kiva,
which focused on direct person-to-person donations, as well as from
initiatives like the Grameen bank, which used social lending to pioneer
the idea of microfinance, and whose founder Mohammed Yunus won the Nobel
Peace Prize in 2006. The idea behind peer-to-peer lending was that
individuals could lend to each other, combining social purpose and sound
investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the question of trust is at its most severe. What happens if I take
a loan from you and don&amp;rsquo;t pay it back? How do you assess credit? The
early players in this industry like Lending Club and Prosper were
experimenting with a variety of approaches, and we&amp;rsquo;ll see how that
worked out later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to finish, let&amp;rsquo;s go back to household services like TaskRabbit. A
lot of companies started in this area. One is Homejoy, which was
Google&amp;rsquo;s venture into housecleaning &amp;ndash; an eyebrow-raising idea in
itself. Another was Handy, which looked to broaden from cleaning to
other services like plumbing and carpentry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there were lots of others. A short list would include DogVacay,
which was often written about to show the quirky and personal aspect of
the market. Instacart and Deliveroo highlighted the food delivery area,
which is still going strong. BlaBlaCar is a French service for taking
rides from city to city. ZipCar was important as one of the first
carsharing companies, and it preceded most of the others here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013 to 2015 various lists of Sharing Economy companies were
published, and they often had hundreds of examples. But for some
analysts, this was just the beginning. PwC is one of the most
consistently upbeat forecasting agencies around the Sharing Economy, and
have forecast markets sizes well into the hundreds of billions of
dollars in a few years time. It looks like the Sharing Economy is taking
off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With those specific examples in mind, let&amp;rsquo;s take one more look at a
definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we have the platform, and that&amp;rsquo;s the Sharing Economy company.
Perhaps it is Homejoy, or DogVacay, or Lending Club. It matches service
providers to consumers. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t take on providing the service itself,
but it does handle payments, identity verification, and ratings. Rating
systems were often called out as one of the main innovations of the
Sharing Economy. &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; columnist Thomas Friedman lauds
&amp;ldquo;Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s real innovation&amp;mdash;a platform of &amp;lsquo;trust&amp;rsquo;&amp;mdash;where everyone could
not only see everyone else&amp;rsquo;s identity but also rate them as good, bad or
indifferent hosts or guests. This meant everyone using the system would
pretty quickly develop a relevant &amp;lsquo;reputation&amp;rsquo; visible to everyone else
in the system.&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Friedman was writing just a couple of weeks after
his &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; stablemate David Brooks described &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;How Airbnb and
Lyft Finally Got Americans to Trust Each Other&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ldquo;: &amp;ldquo;Companies like Airbnb
establish trust through ratings mechanisms &amp;hellip; People in the Airbnb
economy don&amp;rsquo;t have the option of trusting each other on the basis of
institutional affiliations, so they do it on the basis of online
signaling and peer evaluations.&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the consumer side we have seen that the Sharing Economy fits into and
help to shape a trend of particularly young people as valuing
experiences over ownership, and choosing access over ownership. Your
books and music may already be on devices: why buy a car when you can
take an Uber? Everything you need is on your phone or your computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there are the service providers, who are presented as partners
rather than employees. The word that used early on was
&amp;ldquo;micro-entrepreneurs&amp;rdquo;: not really companies, not really private
individuals, but somewhere in between. And by making the most of their
unused assets they were being green, building community, and making a
little money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;business-models-and-strategy&#34;&gt;Business models and strategy&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all sharing economy business models are novel, or successful, but
when it comes to strategy there are some distinctive features for this
sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appeal of platforms to investors lies in the idea of increasing
returns to scale. There is a popular phrase that you may have seen. The
biggest hotel company -- Airbnb -- owns no property. The biggest taxi
company -- Uber -- owns no cars. This mimics the way that Facebook and
YouTube own no content. Each is as big as the biggest company in their
market. The value, it seems, is in the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the benefits of this model is that if a company sees demand, it
can grow very quickly and globally. Just as other Internet companies
have spread around the world, so can Airbnb and Uber. If a hotel chain
wants to add another 100 rooms it has to build a hotel, but for Airbnb
it&amp;rsquo;s just another row in a database. So on the supply side there are
benefits here, sometimes labelled as a &amp;ldquo;zero marginal cost&amp;rdquo; business
structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are increasing returns on the demand side as well as on the supply
side, and they go under the name network effects. Renters want to be
where travellers are, and travellers want to be where renters are. So
just like social media, every person who takes a trip on Airbnb, and
every person who adds a listing, makes it more attractive for everyone
else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things about increasing returns to scale is that it makes it
difficult for new companies to enter the market: it favours a natural
monopoly, or at least oligopoly. Facebook, Amazon, Netflix have few real
competitors. And this industrial organization makes profits possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zero marginal costs and network effects: put the two together and you
can see why investors are enthusiastic. Can Airbnb and Uber do for
services what Amazon has done for retail, what Wikipedia did for the
encyclopedia, and Apple and Spotify have done for music? Is the market
in these services a winner-take-all? The large scale of venture capital
investment shows that a lot of people are prepared to bet that it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a real pressure among startups to grow quickly, and one of the
strategies that gained prominence early was a piece of advice given to
Airbnb by their early investor Y Combinator: do things that don&amp;rsquo;t scale.
&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a company starts, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the benefit of network effects so
it can&amp;rsquo;t rely on them. Instead it needs something different to set
itself apart and get growth started. For Airbnb that was visiting hosts
in its first significant market, and helping them present their listings
in an attractive way on the site. Paying for a photographer was a big
step forward: it made a big difference to those early listings and got
the idea of homesharing started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course in business everyone wants a winning formula, and applying
it blindly is rarely successful. Another Sharing Economy company,
Washio, set out to do the same as Airbnb but for laundry: the company
was going to &amp;ldquo;demolish laundry&amp;rdquo;. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; They gave each customer cookies,
and packaged the laundry with sleek black bags. But it turned out that
the ideas of the Sharing Economy don&amp;rsquo;t really work for laundry. To start
with the cost side: most of the cost is involved in actually doing the
laundry and digital technology doesn&amp;rsquo;t help with that. On the demand
side: just because other people are doing their laundry through Washio
doesn&amp;rsquo;t make a big difference to me, so network effects were limited.
And because of that, the strategy was just losing money on every sale.
Washio ceased operations in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another aspect of business strategy that was central to the
growth of the Sharing Economy. I&amp;rsquo;ve touched on it a couple of times.
Many of these companies did not just see themselves as businesses, they
were also a movement: brands with a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The companies fostered a community of so-called micro-entrepreneurs and
leaned heavily on ideas of democratization. Instead of relying on
faceless corporations we can now provide services to each other, in a
&amp;ldquo;peer to peer&amp;rdquo; fashion. You don&amp;rsquo;t need a bank to get a loan, you don&amp;rsquo;t
need a hotel to take a holiday, you don&amp;rsquo;t need a taxi to get across
town, you just go to the Internet and click or tap. The idea appeals to
those already invested in new technologies: the old rules don&amp;rsquo;t apply,
we have a better way now. Airbnb CEO Brian Chesky said that most of the
reasons for regulation in the accommodation and transport spaces were
consumer protection, and reputation systems could carry out that task
better than cities. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the Sharing Economy shared a moment with the growth of Wikipedia,
with the Arab Spring uprisings in 2011 and the idea of Facebook
revolutions and social media as a democratizing force in politics. The
internet was no longer this place you went to when you sat at a desk, it
was moving into the real world, and taking its values with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But from the beginning there were tensions built into the Sharing
Economy, and the name captures the problem. Is this about a community or
a business?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the one hand it&amp;rsquo;s about sharing: it&amp;rsquo;s social, it&amp;rsquo;s community-focused,
and personal. On the other hand, it&amp;rsquo;s an economy: it&amp;rsquo;s about market
transactions and prices, where scale is the key to profit and perhaps to
monopoly rents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tensions were captured in an organization set up in 2013 called
Peers. It called itself a grassroots movement set up to clear out
old-fashioned regulations and clear a path for the new sharing economy
companies. But it was founded by Airbnb, whose goal was to make money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same way, the companies were touted as democratizing, but were
set up with the goal of making money for investors, including some of
the richest people on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s an attitude that has been called the Californian Ideology, &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
which is that you can have both. You can be rebellious,
anti-establishment, and against hierarchy; but you can also make a big
pile of money while doing it. You can be ethical, and live a life of
purpose, and you can be rich beyond your wildest dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some early examples showed that you cannot have everything, and when
it comes to choosing between community and profit, commercial
enterprises will choose profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;fall&#34;&gt;Fall?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that gives an idea of the ideas behind the Sharing Economy. It&amp;rsquo;s
been ten years now, and there has been a perhaps-inevitable shakeout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many of the &amp;ldquo;Uber for X&amp;rdquo; companies, like Washio, the promise of new
efficiencies has proved hard to achieve. The unpleasant surprise was
perhaps told best by Sarah Kessler, who went back to look at the story
of the drill. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; She showed that many of those companies who were
looking to follow the Sharing Economy template were not growing fast.
Going across town to get a drill from someone you don&amp;rsquo;t know when you
can buy one for \$50 was too much of a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already seen that Washio went bust because its business model
did not reflect reality. Laundry, it turns out, is laundry. In the same
way, the cleaning company Homejoy was set up with \$30 million from
Google Ventures, but any efficiency it gained came at the cost of its
cleaners, who were reported in one revealing article as living under
bridges. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The cost of cleaning is what you pay the cleaners. The
Internet only helps with that if you can push costs, like the time to
travel, onto the cleaners. And obviously they did not want to bear that
cost, so Homejoy had a hard time keeping staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to the problem is that once a homeowner has found a good cleaner,
they probably want the same one again, so the matching problem is not a
huge benefit, and if the cleaner is really a micro-entrepreneur, then
the homeowner can just make a deal with them directly and cut out
Homejoy&amp;rsquo;s portion of the cost. Homejoy went out of business a few years
to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other companies had to carry out what technology companies call a
&amp;ldquo;pivot&amp;rdquo;: change their business model to something different. TaskRabbit
has sold itself to Ikea, and Instacart has partnered with grocery
chains, so both are now a source of cheap labour for orthodox businesses
rather than a peer-to-peer alternative. Perhaps the biggest pivot was in
the &amp;ldquo;peer-to-peer lending&amp;rdquo; market. The companies struggled with high
rates of default, and ended up changing the name to what they call
&amp;ldquo;marketplace lending&amp;rdquo;. Most of the loans for these companies now come
from regular financial institutions, rather than individuals. The role
of the platforms has changed to be that of an automated loan officer:
algorithmically assessing the credit-worthiness of applicants, and
supplying those assessments to the financial institutions who can decide
whether or not to make the loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this tell us? For many companies, the Internet has not been
the game changer they thought. For others, the Internet has worked, but
they have had to move from the Sharing Economy model. And that leaves us
focusing again on the survivors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;2018-full-circle&#34;&gt;2018: Full circle?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018 it seems like we are nearly back to where we started: left with
two successful industries&amp;ndash; ridesharing and short-term rentals. There is
Airbnb and there is Uber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while the overall phenomenon of the Sharing Economy may be fading,
these two are still growing rapidly. A look at their success is still
valuable because of their size and impact, and also because some of the
aspects of their business is a first look at the next wave of
innovation, in which the service providers themselves are algorithms
instead of people. The world of autonomous vehicles and AI services will
be platform-based businesses that face many of the same challenges as
the Sharing Economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like Airbnb and Uber are two cases where the Sharing Economy
model worked: zero marginal costs and network effects combining to give
runaway success. But for Uber at least, it may be too early to say that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uber is often described as a company like Amazon, or Google, or Apple:
one that has changed the nature of the world in which we live. It is
easy to forget that Uber is still not a profitable company, and as
financial quarter after quarter goes by with large losses (over \$1
Billion in 2018 Q3 &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;), it is becoming increasingly doubtful whether
its business model is sustainable. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uber&amp;rsquo;s challenge is to keep both drivers and riders happy. If it raises
prices it loses riders and if it keeps them low then driver retention
becomes a challenge. Much of the early enthusiasm for the company
assumed that this balancing act was solvable because of the huge
efficiency increases that Uber was bringing to the industry, helping
riders and drivers find each other and eliminating idle time for
drivers. The enthusiasm peaked with a 2014 report in the Washington Post
suggesting that some Uber drivers were earning \$90,000 a year, &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:20&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
but that story quickly vanished and now the stories are far more often
about drivers earning less than minimum wage, or facing financial
difficulties because they are unable to keep up payments on a leased
car. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:21&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far Uber has solved its problem by throwing money at it. Uber
subsidises rides by providing enticements to the drivers, burning
through billions of dollars of capital while looking with increasing
desperation for a profitable business model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent reports from New York City suggest that Uber and Lyft cars are
empty for at least as much of the time as the traditional &amp;ldquo;yellow
cabs&amp;rdquo;.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:22&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This is not the case everywhere, but it suggests that
efficiency in its current market is not likely to drive profitability.
Maybe squeezing more out of drivers will be a way to do it? Uber is
investing in dynamic pricing, driver incentives, and a myriad of other
techniques for taking more out of every rider&amp;rsquo;s dollar &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:23&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but we
should not be too quick to assume they will succeed. It remains possible
that Uber is a blip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Airbnb is profitable, but that is a low bar to reach for a
company valued at \$31 Billion, whose repeated attempts to break into
&amp;ldquo;whole trip&amp;rdquo; planning and business travel have been unsuccessful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, both these companies have shown that rapid and global growth is
possible. They have done so at the cost of continual controversy in
cities around the world where they have become popular. There are many
different controversies, but many have a common origin. We highlighted
the need for Sharing Economy companies to have a &amp;ldquo;zero marginal cost&amp;rdquo;
model, but that model relies on the company itself not having
significant new expenses for each service provider or each transaction.
And it has become clear that &amp;ldquo;zero marginal cost&amp;rdquo; is not a feature of
the technology alone, it also depends on the laws that govern the
company&amp;rsquo;s actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing Economy companies present themselves in their terms and
conditions as a marketplace. Uber&amp;rsquo;s user agreement, for example, says
&amp;ldquo;Your ability to obtain transportation&amp;hellip; through the use of The
Services does not establish Uber as a provider of transportation,
logistics or delivery services or as a transportation carrier&amp;rdquo;. The
assertion is that the exchange itself, and anything that may go wrong
with it, is between the consumer and the service provider, not the
consumer and Uber. Other sharing economy companies present themselves in
the same way. Financially, this gets them off the hook for liability and
other problems, and they have relied on a particular American law to
sustain this position. Section 230 of the &amp;ldquo;Communications Decency Act&amp;rdquo;
includes this phrase:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No provider&amp;hellip; of an interactive computer service shall be treated as
the publisher or speaker of any information provided by another
information content provider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These sentences were written with web sites like YouTube in mind. The
hosting platform itself was protected from liability for the actions of
the users on the site. If someone uploads illegal videos to YouTube,
YouTube is at least partially protected from responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether Section 230 to the Sharing Economy is still in dispute. The
European Court of Justice recently ruled that Uber may not qualify for
this kind of protection:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service provided by Uber is more than an intermediation service&amp;hellip;
The ride-booking company must be classified as &amp;lsquo;a service in the field
of transport.&amp;rsquo; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:24&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016 a London tribunal judge was even more direct:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notion that Uber in London is a mosaic of 30,000 small businesses
linked by a common &amp;lsquo;platform&amp;rsquo; is to our minds faintly ridiculous.
&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:25&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end result will not be a simple outcome, as it depends on laws in
different jurisdictions and will vary from company to company. But the
impacts are huge: all kinds of disputes surrounding these companies
focus on their responsibility for some aspects of their business that
they are trying to avoid. Here is a brief list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are Uber drivers employees? Their flexibility suggests not, but that
is not the only criterion for employment: many jurisdictions also
weigh independence while on the job as a criterion, and Uber drivers
do not set their own prices, do not get to select riders, and have
many small controls over how they do their job. Many would say that
full-time Uber drivers, which is a large part of the overall
business, should qualify for many of the benefits that employees
get. This would add significantly to Uber&amp;rsquo;s costs, and present them
with even more financial problems. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:26&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the same way, Airbnb maintains that it is not responsible if its
hosts break the law or break their tenancy agreements in offering
their space for rent, but the company also makes it very difficult
for cities to go after hosts because Airbnb does not, in general,
share host information with the cities where it operates. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:27&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Again, the outcome of this dispute will have a real effect on
Airbnb&amp;rsquo;s cost structure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Brian Chesky was confident that his rating systems could solve
consumer protection problems, it has turned out that there are many
that ratings cannot address. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:28&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Whether it is providing a usable
complaint system, ensuring vehicle safety, ensuring the safety of
Airbnb apartments, so far the Sharing Economy companies have avoided
many of the costs that other providers of commercial services have
to undertake. To the extent that they have to take on the cost of
things going wrong for consumers, the zero-marginal cost model will
vanish.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;As all the transactions on the platform go through the Internet,
both companies have set up shell structures so that they are routed
through subsidiaries in tax-friendly jurisdictions. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:29&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; By not
paying into the tax base of the cities where they operate, the
companies are essentially parasitic on cities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are also many aspects of running cities that governments care
about, from road congestion to housing affordability, where there
have been continual disputes about the responsibility of the
platform companies. Airbnb has long promoted a vision of openness
and authenticity, promising that you could &amp;ldquo;live like a local&amp;rdquo;, but
in some of their biggest markets the locals have not been so happy
about it: Paris neighbourhoods have been losing population,
Barcelona has said &amp;ldquo;bring refugees, keep out tourists&amp;rdquo;. Managing
tourism effectively is a matter of balance, and cities are becoming
increasingly assertive in their dealings with Airbnb.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson from all these disputes is that the business model of new
technology companies is not dictated solely by the technology itself, it
also reflects the responsibilities we expect companies &amp;ndash; particularly
large global companies &amp;ndash; to accept in order to operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been interesting to watch cities become more assertive over time.
When Airbnb and Uber appeared on the scene full of brash promises, they
were intimidated by the challenge to get on board with the future or be
left behind, especially when the platforms could mobilize thousands of
happy customers and service providers to lobby on their behalf. But now
cities are realizing that some problems are shared, and that they have
choices beyond &amp;ldquo;take it or leave it&amp;rdquo;. Major tourist cities are now
regularly talking to each other about their successes and failures when
dealing with Airbnb, for example, and out of this is growing a new set
of rules that balance the interests of tourists with those of the
citizens in the places they visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the &amp;ldquo;zero marginal cost&amp;rdquo; model is shaped by laws as much as by
technology, it raises the question of who builds the future? The debates
around the Sharing Economy mirror earlier debates that have grown around
technological innovation, from the industrial revolution on. Changes are
one part technological, and one part social, and getting the social
arrangements right is just as important for a healthy future as getting
the technology right. Those in the 19^th^ century who fought for child
labour protections or the forty hour working week or the vote were just
as much a part of building the future as the new industrialists and
inventors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the same today. Technology will be a part of the changes that shape
the lives of our children, but so too will the legal and social changes
that surround them. So an understanding of history, of economics, of
society and what a good society needs is just as important as developing
a new twist on an artificial intelligence algorithm when it comes to
shaping the future. Educators in particular play an important role in
ensuring the next generation has the critical faculties and
understanding of society that is going to be needed to ensure they have
a healthy planet and a healthy relationship with our computational
future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future of transport and travel is not being made only by the
technology companies, it is being made in city government offices around
the world. It will be made not just by today&amp;rsquo;s computer science
students, but by our economics students and business students as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rachel Botsman and Roo Rogers, &lt;em&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s Mine Is Yours: The Rise of
Collaborative Consumption&lt;/em&gt; (Harper Business, 2010).&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Airbnb, &amp;lsquo;Fast Facts&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;Airbnb Press Room&lt;/em&gt;, 2018
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://press.airbnb.com/en-uk/fast-facts/&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://press.airbnb.com/en-uk/fast-facts/&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt; [accessed 27
November 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;InterContinental Hotels Group&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/em&gt;, 2018
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=InterContinental_Hotels_Group&amp;amp;oldid=869295066&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=InterContinental_Hotels_Group&amp;amp;oldid=869295066&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 27 November 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crunchbase, &amp;lsquo;TaskRabbit&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;CrunchBase&lt;/em&gt;
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crunchbase.com/organization/taskrabbit&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.crunchbase.com/organization/taskrabbit&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt; [accessed 19
June 2015].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ellen MacArthur Foundation, &amp;lsquo;What Is a Circular Economy? | Ellen
MacArthur Foundation&amp;rsquo;, 2017
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ellenmacarthurfoundation.org/circular-economy/concept&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.ellenmacarthurfoundation.org/circular-economy/concept&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 27 November 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lisa Gansky, &lt;em&gt;The Mesh: Why the Future of Business Is Sharing&lt;/em&gt;
(Portfolio / Penguin, 2010).&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;World Economic Forum, &amp;lsquo;Collaboration in Cities: From Sharing to
&amp;ldquo;Sharing Economy&amp;rdquo;&amp;lsquo;, &lt;em&gt;World Economic Forum&lt;/em&gt;, 2017
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.weforum.org/whitepapers/collaboration-in-cities-from-sharing-to-sharing-economy/&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.weforum.org/whitepapers/collaboration-in-cities-from-sharing-to-sharing-economy/&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 27 November 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Toronto Tool Library, &amp;lsquo;Toronto Tool Library &amp;ndash; Access | Share |
Innovate&amp;rsquo; &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://torontotoollibrary.com/&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://torontotoollibrary.com/&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt; [accessed 27 November
2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rachel Botsman, &amp;lsquo;The Case for Collaborative Consumption (TED
Talk)&amp;lsquo;, 2010
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/rachel_botsman_the_case_for_collaborative_consumption?language=en&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.ted.com/talks/rachel_botsman_the_case_for_collaborative_consumption?language=en&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 27 November 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thomas L. Friedman, &amp;lsquo;And Now for a Bit of Good News &amp;hellip;&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;The
New York Times&lt;/em&gt;, 19 July 2014
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/07/20/opinion/sunday/thomas-l-friedman-and-now-for-a-bit-of-good-news.html&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/07/20/opinion/sunday/thomas-l-friedman-and-now-for-a-bit-of-good-news.html&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 29 June 2015].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;David Brooks, &amp;lsquo;The Evolution of Trust&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt;, 30
June 2014
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/07/01/opinion/david-brooks-the-evolution-of-trust.html&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/07/01/opinion/david-brooks-the-evolution-of-trust.html&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 29 June 2015].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Paul Graham, &amp;lsquo;Do Things That Don&amp;rsquo;t Scale&amp;rsquo;
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://paulgraham.com/ds.html&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://paulgraham.com/ds.html&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt; [accessed 27 November 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jessica Pressler, &amp;lsquo;&amp;ldquo;Let&amp;rsquo;s, Like, Demolish Laundry&amp;rdquo;&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;New York
Magazine&lt;/em&gt;, 21 May 2014
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nymag.com/news/features/laundry-apps-2014-5/&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://nymag.com/news/features/laundry-apps-2014-5/&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt; [accessed
27 November 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brian Chesky, &amp;lsquo;Interviewed by Sara Lacy, Reported in Skift&amp;rsquo;,
&lt;em&gt;Skift&lt;/em&gt;, 11 January 2013
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://skift.com/2013/01/11/airbnb-responds-to-illegal-rentals-story-first-of-all-its-not-illegal-everywhere/&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://skift.com/2013/01/11/airbnb-responds-to-illegal-rentals-story-first-of-all-its-not-illegal-everywhere/&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Richard Barbrook and Andy Cameron, &amp;lsquo;The Californian Ideology&amp;rsquo;,
&lt;em&gt;Mute&lt;/em&gt;, August 1995
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imaginaryfutures.net/2007/04/17/the-californian-ideology-2/&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.imaginaryfutures.net/2007/04/17/the-californian-ideology-2/&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 3 July 2015].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sarah Kessler, &amp;lsquo;The &amp;ldquo;Sharing Economy&amp;rdquo; Is Dead, And We Killed It&amp;rsquo;,
&lt;em&gt;Fast Company&lt;/em&gt;, 14 September 2015
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fastcompany.com/3050775/the-sharing-economy-is-dead-and-we-killed-it&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.fastcompany.com/3050775/the-sharing-economy-is-dead-and-we-killed-it&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 27 November 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kevin Roose, &amp;lsquo;Does Silicon Valley Have a Contract-Worker
Problem?&amp;lsquo;, &lt;em&gt;New York Magazine&lt;/em&gt;, 2014
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://nymag.com/daily/intelligencer/2014/09/silicon-valleys-contract-worker-problem.html&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://nymag.com/daily/intelligencer/2014/09/silicon-valleys-contract-worker-problem.html&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 19 June 2015].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Paayal Zaveri and Deirdre Bosa, &amp;lsquo;Uber Earnings Q3 2018
(Self-Reported)&amp;lsquo;, &lt;em&gt;CNBC&lt;/em&gt;, 2018
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cnbc.com/2018/11/14/uber-earnings-q3-2018-self-reported.html&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.cnbc.com/2018/11/14/uber-earnings-q3-2018-self-reported.html&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 27 November 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hubert Horan, &lt;em&gt;Will the Growth of Uber Increase Economic
Welfare?&lt;/em&gt; (Rochester, NY: Social Science Research Network, 14
September 2017) &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=2933177&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=2933177&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 20 September 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Matt McFarland, &amp;lsquo;Uber&amp;rsquo;s Remarkable Growth Could End the Era of
Poorly Paid Cab Drivers&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;The Washington Post&lt;/em&gt;, 27 May 2014
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/innovations/wp/2014/05/27/ubers-remarkable-growth-could-end-the-era-of-poorly-paid-cab-drivers/&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/innovations/wp/2014/05/27/ubers-remarkable-growth-could-end-the-era-of-poorly-paid-cab-drivers/&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 23 May 2015].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Caroline O&amp;rsquo;Donovan and Jeremy Singer-Vine, &amp;lsquo;How Much Uber Drivers
Actually Make Per Hour&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;Buzzfeed News&lt;/em&gt;, 22 June 2016
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/carolineodonovan/internal-uber-driver-pay-numbers&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/carolineodonovan/internal-uber-driver-pay-numbers&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 27 November 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bruce Schaller, &lt;em&gt;The New Automobility: Lyft, Uber and the Future
of American Cities&lt;/em&gt;, 25 July 2018
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.schallerconsult.com/rideservices/automobility.htm&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.schallerconsult.com/rideservices/automobility.htm&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 20 September 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alex Rosenblat, &lt;em&gt;Uberland: How Algorithms Are Rewriting the Rules
of Work&lt;/em&gt; (University of California Press, 2018)
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucpress.edu/book/9780520298576/uberland&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.ucpress.edu/book/9780520298576/uberland&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt; [accessed
27 November 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark Scott, &amp;lsquo;Uber Is a Transportation Company, Europe&amp;rsquo;s Highest
Court Rules&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;Politico&lt;/em&gt;, 2017
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.politico.eu/article/uber-ecj-ruling/&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.politico.eu/article/uber-ecj-ruling/&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt; [accessed 27
November 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arjun Kharpal, &amp;lsquo;Uber UK Employment Tribunal on Drivers&amp;rsquo; Rights:
All You Need to Know&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;CNBC&lt;/em&gt;, 2017
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cnbc.com/2017/09/27/uber-uk-employment-tribunal-drivers-rights-all-you-need-to-know.html&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.cnbc.com/2017/09/27/uber-uk-employment-tribunal-drivers-rights-all-you-need-to-know.html&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 27 November 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jeremias Prassl, &lt;em&gt;Humans as a Service: The Promise and Perils of
Work in the Gig Economy&lt;/em&gt; (Oxford University Press, 2018)
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/humans-as-a-service-9780198797012?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/humans-as-a-service-9780198797012?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;
[accessed 27 November 2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Benjamin G. Edelman and Abbey Stemler, &lt;em&gt;From the Digital to the
Physical: Federal Limitations on Regulating Online Marketplaces&lt;/em&gt;
(Rochester, NY: Social Science Research Network, 31 January 2018)
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=3106383&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=3106383&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt; [accessed 27 November
2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abbey Stemler, &lt;em&gt;Feedback Loop Failure: Implications for the
Self-Regulation of the Sharing Economy&lt;/em&gt; (Rochester, NY: Social
Science Research Network, 1 April 2016)
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=2754768&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=2754768&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt; [accessed 27 November
2018].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brian O&amp;rsquo;Keefe and Marty Jones, &amp;lsquo;How Uber Plays the Tax Shell
Game&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;Fortune&lt;/em&gt;, 22 October 2015
&amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://fortune.com/2015/10/22/uber-tax-shell/&amp;gt;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://fortune.com/2015/10/22/uber-tax-shell/&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt; [accessed 29
November 2015].&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transport: Time for cities to lead</title>
      <link>https://tomslee.github.io/publication/elpais-transport/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tomslee.github.io/publication/elpais-transport/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tom Slee, September 19, 2018, El País Series on Shared Mobility&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a lesson a few weeks ago, when I spent a weekend in Montreal.
Long a bicycle-mad city, its nine-year-old Bixi ride-share program is
well used and convenient, with over 6,000 bikes sprinkled around its 500
docks throughout the city.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But what really makes the difference is
not so much the bikes themselves, or the docks, or the payment system,
as the separate bike lanes and 700 km of cycle paths that make it safe
to cycle around.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Without investment in infrastructure, the bikes
themselves would not make much difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same goes in the Netherlands: the Dutch own more bicycles per person
than any other country in the world, and almost a quarter of the Dutch
population cycles every day.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In Amsterdam there are twice as many
bikes as cars on the street during rush hour. And the reason is the
roads: 35,000 km of dedicated cycling infrastructure (separate lanes)
and a low speed limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure innovations make a difference. And while bicycles may not
be the future of transport, the lesson applies to other forms of big
city transport. It&amp;rsquo;s a lesson worth keeping in mind with the flood of
transport stories that is coming from the technology industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uber has changed the way many people get around cities. And Uber&amp;rsquo;s
success has produced imitators; a whole generation of
technology-inspired transport visions from Silicon Valley and from
China. Shared bikes (docked and now dockless) and motorized scooters
share the headlines with pooled ridesharing, Elon Musk&amp;rsquo;s tunnels and
driverless cars as the transport of the future. It can seem that transit
innovation is coming from technology companies and not from cities. But
appearances can be deceptive and in this case they are. It is cities
(city governments and citizens) who will shape the transit of the
future, and they should look to each other for inspiration rather than
to Uber and Tesla. Because the challenge is not so much about vehicles
as about space: not so much about cars as about roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Uber moved from being a status-conscious “everybody&amp;rsquo;s private
driver” to being a mode of mass transit, it promised a sustainable
future. We would need less parking space and would live more
economically as private cars faded away; replaced by transport as
reliable as running water. And they would help cities be more efficient
by sharing their traffic flow data, helping to optimize the use of our
roads. But while Uber has grown rapidly year on year, it is not a
template for healthy transit futures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason is that, remarkably, Uber continues to be unprofitable. With
every quarter&amp;rsquo;s financial results the path to profitability seems less
certain. Maybe Uber has grown not just because of its revolutionary
application, but because it subsidizes car rides.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Sooner or later,
it is going to have to make a profit; for commuters, cost matters, and
the idea that everyone can ride an Uber to work may not make economic
sense in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second reason is that Uber is increasingly leading to
congestion.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In major cities, Uber is competing with more
space-efficient mass transit, not complementing it as it promised. New
York City is the best studied city, where 60,000 Uber and Lyft vehicles
are slowing the traffic by about 30%. These vehicles spending as much
time driving empty as a regular yellow cab, despite the high-tech
matching algorithms, and put 2.8 new miles on the road for each mile of
personal driving removed.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Even the shared services such as Uber
Pool have similar statistics. This is no way to build a sustainable
transport infrastructure, and self-driving vehicles would have exactly
the same problem. Smartphones are part of our present and our future,
but they won&amp;rsquo;t fix traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more important innovation, look to Mexico City: since it pioneered
its Bus Rapid Transit (BRT) with dedicated lanes and frequent service,
its steadily growing fleet (now over 700 buses) move 1.8 million people
a day.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In New York City Uber provides 6 rides per vehicle every
day; in Mexico City the BRT provides 2500 rides per vehicle. Other forms
of mass transit are similar: in London, 2 million people per day ride on
about 700 tube trains for over 2000 rides per vehicle. When it comes to
moving lots of people in a big city, mass transit is the way.
Congestion, as traffic expert Jarrett Walker likes to say, is a matter
of urban geometry.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fn-8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:fn-8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are looking to a future of bigger cities, denser city centres,
then we need to make mass transit cool again, and throw off its shabby
image (especially in North America). It will be investment in roads,
paths, and buses that will improve our cities, and those will come from
city governments looking to each other, learning from each other&amp;rsquo;s
innovations and experimenting with new variations. When it comes to
transit, the ballot box is a more important technology of change than
the smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-1&#34;&gt;“BIXI Montréal.”
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-2&#34;&gt;Bruemmer, “Montreal&amp;rsquo;s Bike Path Network: Mind the Gaps.”
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-3&#34;&gt;“Dutch Cycling Figures | BICYCLE DUTCH.”
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-4&#34;&gt;Horan, “Will the Growth of Uber Increase Economic Welfare?”
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-5&#34;&gt;LeBlanc, “Studies Are Increasingly Clear.”
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-6&#34;&gt;Schaller, “The New Automobility: Lyft, Uber and the Future of American Cities”; Schaller, “Unsustainable? The Growth of App-Based Ride Services and Traffic, Travel and the Future of New York City.”
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-7&#34;&gt;“Mexico City Metrobús.”
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fn-8&#34;&gt;Walker, “Does Elon Musk Understand Urban Geometry?”
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fn-8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Airbnb Data Collection: Get the Data</title>
      <link>https://tomslee.github.io/publication/airbnb-get-the-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2017 16:46:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tomslee.github.io/publication/airbnb-get-the-data/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Each link downloads a zip file of the data for a named city or region. The zip file holds one or more csv files. Each csv file represents a single “survey” or “scrape” of the Airbnb web site for that city. The data is collected from the public Airbnb web site without logging in and the code I use is available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tomslee/airbnb-data-collection&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the data provided for each listing. Please note that while other data can be collected from the site, and while other sites (especially the excellent Inside Airbnb) collect richer data about the host and the details of each listing, I have no plans to expand the scope at the moment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;room_id: A unique number identifying an Airbnb listing. The listing has a URL on the Airbnb web site of &lt;a href=&#34;http://airbnb.com/rooms/room_id&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://airbnb.com/rooms/room_id&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;host_id: A unique number identifying an Airbnb host. The host’s page has a URL on the Airbnb web site of &lt;a href=&#34;http://airbnb.com/users/show/host_id&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://airbnb.com/users/show/host_id&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;room_type: One of “Entire home/apt”, “Private room”, or “Shared room”
borough: A subregion of the city or search area for which the survey is carried out. The borough is taken from a shapefile of the city that is obtained independently of the Airbnb web site. For some cities, there is no borough information; for others the borough may be a number. If you have better shapefiles for a city of interest, please send them to me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;neighborhood: As with borough: a subregion of the city or search area for which the survey is carried out. For cities that have both, a neighbourhood is smaller than a borough. For some cities there is no neighbourhood information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reviews: The number of reviews that a listing has received. Airbnb has said that 70% of visits end up with a review, so the number of reviews can be used to estimate the number of visits. Note that such an estimate will not be reliable for an individual listing (especially as reviews occasionally vanish from the site), but over a city as a whole it should be a useful metric of traffic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;overall_satisfaction: The average rating (out of five) that the listing has received from those visitors who left a review.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;accommodates: The number of guests a listing can accommodate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bedrooms: The number of bedrooms a listing offers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;price: The price (in $US) for a night stay. In early surveys, there may be some values that were recorded by month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;minstay: The minimum stay for a visit, as posted by the host.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;latitude and longitude: The latitude and longitude of the listing as posted on the Airbnb site: this may be off by a few hundred metres. I do not have a way to track individual listing locations with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;last_modified: the date and time that the values were read from the Airbnb web site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first line of the CSV file holds the column headings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the cities, the survey dates, and a link to download each zip file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;aarhus&#34;&gt;Aarhus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-10-28 (2258 listings), 2016-11-26 (1900 listings), 2017-01-21 (2167 listings), 2017-02-21 (2295 listings), 2017-03-30 (2323 listings), 2017-04-18 (2398 listings), 2017-04-28 (2360 listings), 2017-05-15 (2437 listings), 2017-06-19 (2802 listings), 2017-07-28 (3142 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/aarhus.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;alpes-maritime&#34;&gt;Alpes Maritime&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-09-06 (24868 listings), 2017-01-28 (25888 listings), 2017-02-26 (26707 listings), 2017-04-24 (26057 listings), 2017-06-19 (28554 listings), 2017-07-12 (32343 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/alpes_maritime.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;amsterdam&#34;&gt;Amsterdam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2014-05-24 (5645 listings), 2014-08-30 (6840 listings), 2015-01-19 (7693 listings), 2015-03-17 (7807 listings), 2015-12-16 (9850 listings), 2016-05-31 (13360 listings), 2016-08-04 (15314 listings), 2016-12-15 (17018 listings), 2017-01-18 (16871 listings), 2017-02-17 (16542 listings), 2017-03-27 (16362 listings), 2017-04-24 (17037 listings), 2017-05-12 (17201 listings), 2017-06-15 (17795 listings), 2017-07-22 (18723 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/amsterdam.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;anchorage&#34;&gt;Anchorage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-05-13 (447 listings), 2017-03-10 (728 listings),
2017-04-12 (764 listings), 2017-05-22 (842 listings), 2017-06-24 (932
listings), 2017-07-20 (969 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/anchorage.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;asheville&#34;&gt;Asheville&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-09-10 (757 listings), 2016-12-26 (799 listings),
2017-03-10 (783 listings), 2017-04-12 (788 listings), 2017-05-14 (810
listings), 2017-06-24 (848 listings), 2017-07-20 (854 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/asheville.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;asturias&#34;&gt;Asturias&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-07-02 (1225 listings), 2017-07-26 (1327 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/asturias.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;auckland&#34;&gt;Auckland&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-08-19 (4590 listings), 2016-12-26 (6103 listings),
2017-01-16 (6230 listings), 2017-02-12 (6507 listings), 2017-03-25 (7384
listings), 2017-04-13 (7889 listings), 2017-04-22 (8010 listings),
2017-05-10 (8487 listings), 2017-06-14 (8847 listings), 2017-07-19 (8815
listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/auckland.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;barcelona&#34;&gt;Barcelona&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2014-05-20 (10441 listings), 2014-09-04 (10413 listings),
2015-01-14 (12467 listings), 2015-04-29 (10468 listings), 2015-11-06
(14012 listings), 2016-05-30 (17154 listings), 2016-07-25 (19145
listings), 2016-08-28 (18953 listings), 2016-10-22 (16383 listings),
2016-12-10 (15148 listings), 2017-01-18 (17153 listings), 2017-02-18
(17269 listings), 2017-03-27 (17385 listings), 2017-04-15 (17448
listings), 2017-04-24 (17572 listings), 2017-05-12 (17775 listings),
2017-06-15 (18558 listings), 2017-07-23 (18838 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/barcelona.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;belgium&#34;&gt;Belgium&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-12-30 (15711 listings), 2017-01-29 (15761 listings),
2017-02-28 (15695 listings), 2017-04-26 (15980 listings), 2017-06-19
(17093 listings), 2017-07-14 (17651 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/belgium.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;berlin&#34;&gt;Berlin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2014-05-18 (7789 listings), 2015-01-19 (11553 listings),
2015-07-04 (12903 listings), 2015-11-07 (14132 listings), 2015-11-30
(14922 listings), 2016-05-01 (16135 listings), 2016-05-29 (8490
listings), 2016-08-30 (15680 listings), 2016-10-09 (16540 listings),
2016-12-15 (18551 listings), 2017-01-01 (18684 listings), 2017-01-17
(18312 listings), 2017-02-16 (18473 listings), 2017-03-26 (18999
listings), 2017-04-23 (19528 listings), 2017-05-11 (19681 listings),
2017-06-15 (20415 listings), 2017-07-21 (21864 listings25 (2443
listings), 2017-02-12 (2565 listings), 2017-03-11 (2580 listings),
2017-04-10 (2634 listings), 2017-05-08 (2645 listings), 2017-06-10 (2721
listings), 2017-07-10 (2954 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/calgary.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cambridge-ma&#34;&gt;Cambridge MA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-09-30 (1442 listings), 2017-03-10 (1694 listings),
2017-04-12 (1713 listings), 2017-05-14 (1765 listings), 2017-06-24 (1825
listings), 2017-07-20 (1809 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/cambriddates:%202016-07-10%20(2437%20listings),%202016-11-07%20(2222%20listings),%202017-01-30%20(2673%20listings),%202017-03-01%20(2743%20listings),%202017-04-27%20(2925%20listings),%202017-05-18%20(3045%20listings),%202017-06-19%20(3358%20listings),%202017-07-16%20(3582%20listings)%3C/p%3E%0A%3Cp%3E%3Ca%20href=&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;florence&#34;&gt;Florence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2015-10-11 (5309 listings), 2015-11-02 (6175 listings),
2015-12-20 (6583 listings), 2016-01-07 (6698 listings), 2016-08-05 (8553
listings), 2016-09-12 (8525 listings), 2016-12-26 (8702 listings),
2017-01-24 (8725 listings), 2017-02-22 (8753 listings), 2017-04-04 (8945
listings), 2017-04-29 (9198 listings), 2017-05-19 (9215 listings),
2017-06-22 (9394 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/florence.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;frankfurt&#34;&gt;Frankfurt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-03-27 (1580 listings), 2016-08-21 (1717 listings),
2016-12-26 (1944 listings), 2017-01-23 (1910 listings), 2017-02-22 (1968
listings), 2017-04-02 (1998 listings), 2017-04-28 (2134 listings),
2017-05-18 (1957 listings), 2017-06-22 (1995 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/frankfurt.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;geneva&#34;&gt;Geneva&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2014-11-26 (702 listings), 2016-08-09 (666 listings),
2017-01-23 (1663 listings), 2017-03-10 (1676 listings), 2017-04-12 (1738
listings), 2017-05-14 (1782 listings), 2017-06-24 (1849 listings),
2017-07-20 (1954 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/geneva.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;girona&#34;&gt;Girona&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-05-13 (393 listings), 2017-06-04 (403 listings),
2017-06-23 (410 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/girona.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;granada&#34;&gt;Granada&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-07-06 (3565 listings), 2017-07-25 (3595 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/granada.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;groningen&#34;&gt;Groningen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-03-18 (382 listings), 2016-03-28 (386 listings),
2016-12-26 (533 listings), 2017-01-24 (588 listings), 2017-02-22 (607
listings), 2017-04-04 (610 listings), 2017-04-29 (648 listings),
2017-05-19 (645 listings), 2017-06-22 (706 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/groningen.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;helsinki&#34;&gt;Helsinki&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-05-07 (1971 listings), 2016-12-26 (2742 listings),
2017-01-23 (2733 listings), 2017-04-02 (2792 listings), 2017-04-28 (2932
listings), 2017-05-18 (2936 listings), 2017-06-22 (3191 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/helsinki.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;houston&#34;&gt;Houston&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-04-30 (7758 listings), 2017-05-08 (7712 listings),
2017-06-11 (7677 listings), 2017-07-13 (7559 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/houston.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;hungary&#34;&gt;Hungary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-02-24 (4507 listings), 2017-04-28 (10517 listings),
2017-05-19 (10605 listings), 2017-06-21 (11141 listings), 2017-07-18
(12139 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/hungary.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;iceland&#34;&gt;Iceland&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-07-29 (4768 listings), 2016-09-24 (5005 listings),
2016-10-25 (4993 listings), 2016-11-29 (5180 listings), 2016-12-22 (5573
listings), 2017-01-27 (5629 listings), 2017-02-26 (5820 listings),
2017-04-23 (6255 listings), 2017-05-14 (6496 listings), 2017-06-18 (6876
listings), 2017-07-12 (7117 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/iceland.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;jersey-city&#34;&gt;Jersey City&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-05-26 (1284 listings), 2016-12-26 (1538 listings),
2017-03-10 (1561 listings), 2017-04-12 (1647 listings), 2017-05-14 (1694
listings), 2017-06-24 (1808 listings), 2017-07-20 (1798 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/jersey_city.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;joshua-tree&#34;&gt;Joshua Tree&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-05-27 (227 listings), 2016-11-06 (234 listings),
2017-03-10 (154 listings), 2017-04-12 (160 listings), 2017-05-14 (171
listings), 2017-06-24 (174 listings), 2017-07-20 (178 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/joshua_tree.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;kenya&#34;&gt;Kenya&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-05-12 (4420 listings), 2017-07-23 (4764 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/kenya.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;kitchener-waterloo&#34;&gt;Kitchener Waterloo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-05-22 (262 listings), 2016-09-22 (274 listings),
2016-10-28 (282 listings), 2016-12-10 (346 listings), 2016-12-25 (326
listings), 2017-02-12 (353 listings), 2017-03-11 (343 listings),
2017-04-10 (349 listings), 2017-05-08 (366 listings), 2017-06-10 (382
listings), 2017-07-10 (388 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/kitchener_waterloo.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lake-tahoe&#34;&gt;Lake Tahoe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-05-08 (4365 listings), 2017-06-29 (4342 listings),
2017-07-25 (4403 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/lake_tahoe.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;las-vegas&#34;&gt;Las Vegas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-02-25 (5268 listings), 2017-03-10 (5261 listings),
2017-04-12 (5520 listings), 2017-05-14 (5691 listings), 2017-06-24 (5823
listings), 2017-07-20 (5830 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/las_vegas.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lenox&#34;&gt;Lenox&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-06-25 (81 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/lenox.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lincoln-county&#34;&gt;Lincoln County&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-04-27 (435 listings), 2017-03-11 (810 listings),
2017-04-12 (492 listings), 2017-05-15 (878 listings), 2017-06-24 (941
listings), 2017-07-20 (1190 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/lincoln_county.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;linkoping&#34;&gt;Linkoping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-08-02 (57 listings), 2017-03-11 (50 listings),
2017-04-12 (50 listings), 2017-05-15 (56 listings), 2017-06-24 (67
listings), 2017-07-20 (70 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/linkoping.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lisbon&#34;&gt;Lisbon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2015-03-18 (5652 listings), 2016-03-20 (8968 listings),
2016-06-02 (10272 listings), 2016-09-12 (10998 listings), 2016-12-26
(11668 listings), 2017-01-21 (11654 listings), 2017-02-21 (11792
listings), 2017-03-30 (12045 listings), 2017-04-18 (12287 listings),
2017-04-27 (12499 listings), 2017-05-15 (12797 listings), 2017-06-19
(13232 listings), 2017-07-27 (13578 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/lisbon.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;london&#34;&gt;London&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2013-12-21 (13054 listings), 2014-05-13 (13237 listings),
2015-01-17 (21298 listings), 2016-01-09 (34414 listings), 2016-08-07
(48515 listings), 2016-09-22 (47472 listings), 2016-12-26 (53313
listings), 2017-01-21 (53947 listings), 2017-03-31 (55846 listings),
2017-04-28 (57826 listings), 2017-06-19 (60561 listings), 2017-07-28
(64144 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/london.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;los-angeles&#34;&gt;Los Angeles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2014-09-01 (10027 listings), 2014-09-18 (11317 listings),
2014-10-25 (11780 listings), 2015-04-06 (13899 listings), 2015-08-03
(15790 listings), 2015-08-27 (16649 listings), 2015-09-09 (16968
listings), 2015-10-13 (17420 listings), 2015-11-16 (18665 listings),
2015-12-10 (19709 listings), 2016-01-11 (18863 listings), 2016-02-10
(19311 listings), 2016-03-12 (19717 listings), 2016-04-12 (20951
listings), 2016-05-14 (21986 listings), 2016-06-14 (21996 listings),
2016-07-13 (23071 listings), 2016-08-15 (23793 listings), 2016-09-13
(24744 listings), 2016-10-14 (25347 listings), 2016-11-17 (24633
listings), 2016-12-17 (30735 listings), 2017-01-12 (29517 listings),
2017-02-10 (29316 listings), 2017-03-10 (29252 listings), 2017-04-06
(29955 listings), 2017-05-03 (30696 listings), 2017-06-05 (30829
listings), 2017-07-08 (32146 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/los_angeles.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lyon&#34;&gt;Lyon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-05-14 (7346 listings), 2016-10-02 (8106 listings),
2016-12-27 (9816 listings), 2017-03-11 (9494 listings), 2017-04-12 (9707
listings), 2017-05-15 (9856 listings), 2017-06-24 (10186 listings),
2017-07-20 (10409 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/lyon.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;madrid&#34;&gt;Madrid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2014-08-29 (4790 listings), 2015-02-21 (5393 listings),
2017-03-11 (12615 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/madrid.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mallorca&#34;&gt;Mallorca&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/mallorca.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;melun&#34;&gt;Melun&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-03-24 (37 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/melun.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;menorca&#34;&gt;Menorca&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-04-19 (1769 listings), 2016-04-20 (1757 listings),
2016-11-06 (1866 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/menorca.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miami&#34;&gt;Miami&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2015-08-17 (6947 listings), 2015-10-03 (7057 listings),
2015-10-18 (7414 listings), 2015-11-19 (7676 listings), 2015-12-12 (8349
listings), 2016-01-13 (8553 listings), 2016-02-12 (8855 listings),
2016-03-14 (9468 listings), 2016-04-12 (7034 listings), 2016-05-15 (7244
listings), 2016-06-15 (7162 listings), 2016-07-14 (7249 listings),
2016-08-16 (7212 listings), 2016-09-14 (7213 listings), 2016-10-15 (6563
listings), 2016-11-18 (6856 listings), 2016-12-21 (9811 listings),
2017-01-13 (7810 listings), 2017-02-12 (7845 listings), 2017-03-12 (7664
listings), 2017-04-07 (7586 listings), 2017-05-04 (7948 listings),
2017-06-04 (9608 listings), 2017-07-09 (8824 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/miami.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;montreal&#34;&gt;Montreal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2014-08-30 (4424 listings), 2015-01-15 (6216 listings),
2015-09-02 (9236 listings), 2015-10-03 (9234 listings), 2016-06-29
(12476 listings), 2016-07-26 (12884 listings), 2016-08-20 (12587
listings), 2016-09-21 (12021 listings), 2016-10-27 (12444 listings),
2016-11-26 (11489 listings), 2016-12-08 (11518 listings), 2016-12-25
(13814 listings), 2017-02-11 (13729 listings), 2017-03-10 (13877
listings), 2017-04-10 (14342 listings), 2017-05-07 (14738 listings),
2017-06-10 (15286 listings), 2017-07-09 (15625 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/montreal.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;moscow&#34;&gt;Moscow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2014-05-26 (1589 listings), 2014-08-24 (1843 listings),
2015-10-11 (3585 listings), 2015-11-02 (3819 listings), 2016-10-08 (5561
listings), 2017-03-11 (6201 listings), 2017-04-13 (6527 listings),
2017-05-15 (6789 listings), 2017-06-26 (6973 listings), 2017-07-21 (7200
listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/moscow.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nairobi&#34;&gt;Nairobi&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-05-12 (2516 listings), 2017-06-29 (2762 listings),
2017-07-25 (2837 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/nairobi.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nantes&#34;&gt;Nantes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-07-01 (2648 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/nantes.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nashville&#34;&gt;Nashville&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-05-22 (3012 listings), 2016-08-30 (3486 listings),
2016-10-10 (3603 listings), 2016-12-16 (4067 listings), 2017-03-11 (4077
listings), 2017-04-13 (4357 listings), 2017-05-16 (4463 listings),
2017-06-26 (4787 listings), 2017-07-21 (4804 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/nashville.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;new-orleans&#34;&gt;New Orleans&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2015-01-16 (1905 listings), 2015-08-21 (2092 listings),
2015-10-03 (2667 listings), 2015-11-19 (2941 listings), 2015-12-13 (3041
listings), 2016-01-15 (3319 listings), 2016-02-15 (3697 listings),
2016-03-16 (3857 listings), 2016-04-12 (4177 listings), 2016-05-17 (4378
listings), 2016-06-16 (4069 listings), 2016-07-15 (4432 listings),
2016-08-17 (4482 listings), 2016-09-15 (4525 listings), 2016-10-16 (4449
listings), 2016-11-19 (4707 listings), 2017-01-13 (5067 listings),
2017-02-12 (5540 listings), 2017-03-12 (5663 listings), 2017-04-08 (5722
listings), 2017-05-04 (5855 listings), 2017-06-21 (3739 listings),
2017-07-10 (3862 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/new_orleans.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;new-york&#34;&gt;New York&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2014-05-10 (18921 listings), 2014-08-31 (20777 listings),
2014-10-17 (22388 listings), 2014-12-02 (25405 listings), 2015-02-27
(26441 listings), 2015-03-14 (28552 listings), 2015-08-10 (30001
listings), 2015-09-10 (30059 listings), 2015-10-13 (29898 listings),
2015-12-04 (33926 listings), 2015-12-21 (36062 listings), 2016-01-21
(36003 listings), 2016-02-25 (34935 listings), 2016-03-24 (34678
listings), 2016-04-03 (34380 listings), 2016-04-20 (34661 listings),
2016-05-23 (35067 listings), 2016-06-23 (34205 listings), 2016-07-20
(35547 listings), 2016-08-24 (37769 listings), 2016-09-20 (35620
listings), 2016-10-23 (35795 listings), 2016-11-26 (37439 listings),
2016-12-26 (39079 listings), 2017-01-15 (38768 listings), 2017-02-17
(37878 listings), 2017-03-14 (38549 listings), 2017-04-21 (39745
listings), 2017-05-06 (40733 listings), 2017-06-12 (39167 listings),
2017-07-12 (41245 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/new_york.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;newhaven-ct&#34;&gt;Newhaven CT&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2015-08-21 (369 listings), 2015-10-03 (475 listings),
2015-10-21 (431 listings), 2015-11-26 (567 listings), 2015-12-15 (586
listings), 2016-01-18 (604 listings), 2016-02-20 (632 listings),
2016-03-21 (678 listings), 2016-04-16 (473 listings), 2016-05-20 (481
listings), 2016-06-20 (489 listings), 2016-07-18 (444 listings),
2016-08-20 (431 listings), 2016-09-17 (444 listings), 2016-10-20 (448
listings), 2016-11-23 (471 listings), 2016-12-24 (407 listings),
2017-01-14 (359 listings), 2017-02-16 (373 listings), 2017-03-13 (370
listings), 2017-04-08 (388 listings), 2017-05-05 (420 listings),
2017-06-10 (414 listings), 2017-07-11 (428 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/newhaven_ct.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;newport&#34;&gt;Newport&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-04-26 (57 listings), 2016-12-26 (70 listings),
2017-03-11 (94 listings), 2017-04-13 (61 listings), 2017-05-16 (83
listings), 2017-06-27 (138 listings), 2017-07-22 (148 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/newport.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nice&#34;&gt;Nice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-06-25 (8802 listings), 2016-10-06 (9288 listings),
2016-12-08 (9444 listings), 2017-01-21 (9511 listings), 2017-02-21 (9604
listings), 2017-03-30 (9962 listings), 2017-04-18 (10168 listings),
2017-04-28 (10229 listings), 2017-05-16 (10576 listings), 2017-06-19
(11193 listings), 2017-07-28 (11629 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/nice.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;oahu&#34;&gt;Oahu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2015-08-17 (2481 listings), 2015-10-18 (2696 listings),
2015-11-19 (2855 listings), 2015-12-12 (3086 listings), 2016-01-14 (3193
listings), 2016-02-13 (3214 listings), 2016-03-15 (3190 listings),
2016-04-14 (3539 listings), 2016-05-16 (3665 listings), 2016-06-15 (3844
listings), 2016-07-14 (3953 listings), 2016-08-17 (4020 listings),
2016-09-14 (4233 listings), 2016-10-15 (4200 listings), 2016-11-18 (4662
listings), 2016-12-21 (5146 listings), 2017-01-13 (5051 listings),
2017-02-12 (5249 listings), 2017-03-12 (5346 listings), 2017-04-07 (5610
listings), 2017-05-04 (5863 listings), 2017-06-08 (6028 listings),
2017-07-09 (6163 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/oahu.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ottawa&#34;&gt;Ottawa&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-05-16 (1496 listings), 2016-08-23 (1586 listings),
2016-09-21 (1624 listings), 2016-10-27 (1736 listings), 2016-12-07 (1897
listings), 2016-12-25 (1906 listings), 2017-02-12 (2003 listings),
2017-03-11 (2090 listings), 2017-04-10 (2257 listings), 2017-05-08 (2476
listings), 2017-06-10 (2919 listings), 2017-07-10 (3593 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/ottawa.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;palermo&#34;&gt;Palermo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-09-14 (3635 listings), 2016-12-26 (3770 listings),
2017-03-11 (3872 listings), 2017-04-13 (3996 listings), 2017-05-16 (4086
listings), 2017-06-27 (4284 listings), 2017-07-22 (4434 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/palermo.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;paris&#34;&gt;Paris&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2013-11-27 (19004 listings), 2014-05-16 (19946 listings),
2014-09-21 (27326 listings), 2014-12-26 (28826 listings), 2015-02-28
(31341 listings), 2015-12-17 (40005 listings), 2015-12-31 (41761
listings), 2016-05-26 (55951 listings), 2016-08-10 (62213 listings),
2017-01-01 (62963 listings), 2017-01-19 (62043 listings), 2017-02-18
(61666 listings), 2017-03-28 (62087 listings), 2017-04-25 (63634
listings), 2017-06-16 (65727 listings), 2017-07-25 (70158 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/paris.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;peel&#34;&gt;Peel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-09-24 (838 listings), 2016-10-29 (875 listings),
2016-12-09 (919 listings), 2016-12-25 (896 listings), 2017-02-12 (927
listings), 2017-03-11 (930 listings), 2017-04-10 (972 listings),
2017-05-08 (1017 listings), 2017-06-10 (1013 listings), 2017-07-10 (1064
listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/peel.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;philadelphia&#34;&gt;Philadelphia&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2015-08-20 (5990 listings), 2015-10-18 (7318 listings),
2015-11-19 (7177 listings), 2015-12-12 (7141 listings), 2016-01-14 (6895
listings), 2016-02-14 (7062 listings), 2016-03-16 (7026 listings),
2016-04-15 (6976 listings), 2016-05-16 (6813 listings), 2016-06-16 (6753
listings), 2016-07-15 (6921 listings), 2016-08-17 (6928 listings),
2016-09-15 (6904 listings), 2016-10-16 (6600 listings), 2016-11-19 (6875
listings), 2017-01-13 (7068 listings), 2017-02-12 (7152 listings),
2017-03-12 (7101 listings), 2017-04-07 (7090 listings), 2017-05-04 (7242
listings), 2017-06-08 (7391 listings), 2017-07-09 (7367 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/philadelphia.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pittsburgh&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-04-30 (850 listings), 2017-05-08 (892 listings),
2017-06-12 (924 listings), 2017-07-13 (879 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/pittsburgh.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;portland&#34;&gt;Portland&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2014-10-28 (1748 listings), 2015-02-22 (1900 listings),
2015-08-22 (1917 listings), 2015-10-23 (2622 listings), 2015-10-26 (2722
listings), 2015-11-21 (2847 listings), 2015-12-13 (2952 listings),
2016-01-15 (2897 listings), 2016-02-15 (2970 listings), 2016-03-17 (3077
listings), 2016-04-13 (3128 listings), 2016-05-17 (3238 listings),
2016-06-17 (3383 listings), 2016-07-15 (3496 listings), 2016-08-18 (3661
listings), 2016-09-15 (3714 listings), 2016-10-17 (3626 listings),
2016-11-19 (3914 listings), 2017-01-14 (3860 listings), 2017-02-16 (3837
listings), 2017-03-12 (3748 listings), 2017-04-08 (3634 listings),
2017-05-05 (3690 listings), 2017-06-09 (3815 listings), 2017-07-10 (3950
listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/portland.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;portland-me&#34;&gt;Portland ME&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-07-31 (409 listings), 2017-03-12 (456 listings),
2017-04-13 (476 listings), 2017-05-16 (519 listings), 2017-06-27 (576
listings), 2017-07-22 (591 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/portland_me.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;porto&#34;&gt;Porto&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-10-13 (4174 listings), 2016-12-12 (4461 listings),
2017-03-12 (4729 listings), 2017-04-13 (4971 listings), 2017-05-16 (5150
listings), 2017-06-27 (5561 listings), 2017-07-22 (5664 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/porto.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;prince-georges-county&#34;&gt;Prince Georges County&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-02-25 (1120 listings), 2017-03-12 (1121 listings),
2017-04-13 (1135 listings), 2017-05-16 (1149 listings), 2017-06-27 (1185
listings), 2017-07-22 (1203 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/prince_georges_county.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;quebec-city&#34;&gt;Quebec City&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-05-17 (2022 listings), 2017-06-11 (2120 listings),
2017-07-10 (2153 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/quebec_city.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;queenstown&#34;&gt;Queenstown&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-03-28 (1171 listings), 2017-04-25 (1137 listings),
2017-05-10 (1205 listings), 2017-06-14 (1227 listings), 2017-07-18 (1210
listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/queenstown.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reykjavik&#34;&gt;Reykjavik&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-04-24 (2551 listings), 2016-06-06 (2799 listings),
2016-06-30 (2936 listings), 2016-08-08 (2813 listings), 2016-09-11 (2821
listings), 2016-11-02 (2807 listings), 2016-11-23 (2996 listings),
2016-12-25 (3036 listings), 2017-01-01 (3053 listings), 2017-01-21 (2969
listings), 2017-02-22 (3046 listings), 2017-03-31 (3091 listings),
2017-04-19 (3237 listings), 2017-04-28 (3178 listings), 2017-05-16 (3306
listings), 2017-06-19 (3406 listings), 2017-07-28 (3650 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/reykjavik.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;richmond-bc&#34;&gt;Richmond BC&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-01-13 (760 listings), 2017-02-12 (627 listings),
2017-03-13 (620 listings), 2017-04-12 (561 listings), 2017-05-12 (531
listings), 2017-06-14 (540 listings), 2017-07-13 (514 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/richmond_bc.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rome&#34;&gt;Rome&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2013-11-27 (1714 listings), 2014-05-19 (7810 listings),
2014-08-25 (9168 listings), 2014-11-28 (10778 listings), 2015-08-29
(15703 listings), 2016-01-06 (17900 listings), 2016-08-05 (23754
listings), 2016-09-11 (24061 listings), 2016-12-26 (25104 listings),
2017-01-16 (25275 listings), 2017-02-16 (25226 listings), 2017-03-25
(25430 listings), 2017-04-13 (25687 listings), 2017-04-22 (26000
listings), 2017-05-11 (26065 listings), 2017-06-14 (26206 listings),
2017-07-19 (26804 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/rome.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;saint-denis&#34;&gt;Saint Denis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-03-10 (564 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/saint_denis.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;saint-lucia&#34;&gt;Saint Lucia&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-09-25 (642 listings), 2017-03-12 (718 listings),
2017-04-14 (743 listings), 2017-05-17 (761 listings), 2017-06-27 (799
listings), 2017-07-23 (835 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/saint_lucia.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;saint-malo&#34;&gt;Saint Malo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-05-17 (1285 listings), 2017-06-29 (1408 listings),
2017-07-25 (1460 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/saint_malo.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;salvador&#34;&gt;Salvador&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-07-01 (4308 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/salvador.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;san-diego&#34;&gt;San Diego&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2014-05-25 (1901 listings), 2014-11-03 (2632 listings),
2015-08-22 (3318 listings), 2015-10-03 (4014 listings), 2015-10-23 (4222
listings), 2015-12-03 (4482 listings), 2015-12-16 (4587 listings),
2016-01-19 (4721 listings), 2016-02-22 (4813 listings), 2016-03-23 (4954
listings), 2016-04-18 (5356 listings), 2016-05-22 (5764 listings),
2016-06-21 (6257 listings), 2016-07-19 (7056 listings), 2016-08-22 (7177
listings), 2016-09-19 (7394 listings), 2016-10-22 (7481 listings),
2016-11-25 (7839 listings), 2016-12-25 (8030 listings), 2017-01-15 (8021
listings), 2017-02-17 (8054 listings), 2017-04-09 (8225 listings),
2017-05-06 (8316 listings), 2017-06-11 (8643 listings), 2017-07-11 (9111
listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/san_diego.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;san-francisco&#34;&gt;San Francisco&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2013-11-17 (215 listings), 2014-05-11 (4771 listings),
2014-08-24 (4771 listings), 2015-02-19 (5202 listings), 2015-06-05 (5305
listings), 2015-08-21 (5140 listings), 2015-10-21 (5587 listings),
2015-11-21 (7146 listings), 2015-12-14 (7399 listings), 2016-01-16 (7604
listings), 2016-02-17 (8549 listings), 2016-03-19 (8539 listings),
2016-04-15 (8051 listings), 2016-05-19 (7913 listings), 2016-06-04 (8669
listings), 2016-06-18 (7783 listings), 2016-07-17 (8037 listings),
2016-08-19 (7983 listings), 2016-09-17 (8076 listings), 2016-10-19 (8236
listings), 2016-11-21 (8407 listings), 2016-12-23 (8899 listings),
2017-01-14 (8508 listings), 2017-02-16 (8397 listings), 2017-03-12 (8286
listings), 2017-03-24 (8310 listings), 2017-04-08 (8319 listings),
2017-05-05 (8391 listings), 2017-07-10 (8344 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/san_francisco.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;santa-barbara&#34;&gt;Santa Barbara&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-01-15 (467 listings), 2017-03-12 (403 listings),
2017-04-14 (398 listings), 2017-05-17 (359 listings), 2017-06-27 (351
listings), 2017-07-23 (384 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/santa_barbara.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sao-paulo&#34;&gt;Sao Paulo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-07-01 (11118 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/sao_paulo.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;savannah&#34;&gt;Savannah&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-05-13 (494 listings), 2016-12-26 (615 listings),
2017-03-12 (717 listings), 2017-04-14 (752 listings), 2017-05-17 (777
listings), 2017-06-27 (835 listings), 2017-07-23 (877 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/savannah.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;seattle&#34;&gt;Seattle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2015-09-01 (3223 listings), 2015-10-23 (3544 listings),
2015-11-28 (3715 listings), 2015-12-15 (3836 listings), 2016-01-19 (3871
listings), 2016-02-22 (3974 listings), 2016-03-22 (4048 listings),
2016-04-18 (4170 listings), 2016-05-22 (4413 listings), 2016-06-21 (4654
listings), 2016-07-19 (4935 listings), 2016-08-22 (5153 listings),
2016-09-18 (5253 listings), 2016-10-21 (5393 listings), 2016-11-24 (5654
listings), 2016-12-25 (5858 listings), 2017-01-15 (5717 listings),
2017-02-17 (5834 listings), 2017-03-13 (5816 listings), 2017-04-09 (5920
listings), 2017-05-06 (6062 listings), 2017-06-11 (6234 listings),
2017-07-11 (6399 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/seattle.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;seoul&#34;&gt;Seoul&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-05-29 (8519 listings), 2016-10-02 (9969 listings),
2016-12-28 (10690 listings), 2017-01-15 (10905 listings), 2017-01-15
(10930 listings), 2017-02-11 (11121 listings), 2017-03-24 (11544
listings), 2017-04-12 (11619 listings), 2017-04-21 (11723 listings),
2017-05-10 (11516 listings), 2017-06-14 (11965 listings), 2017-07-17
(12406 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/seoul.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;singapore&#34;&gt;Singapore&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2015-06-28 (2815 listings), 2016-06-11 (5796 listings),
2016-10-11 (6753 listings), 2017-03-12 (6828 listings), 2017-04-14 (7201
listings), 2017-05-17 (7212 listings), 2017-06-27 (7003 listings),
2017-07-23 (6834 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/singapore.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sri-lanka&#34;&gt;Sri Lanka&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-04-27 (7107 listings), 2016-09-24 (8725 listings),
2017-04-28 (11568 listings), 2017-06-21 (12176 listings), 2017-07-19
(12400 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/sri_lanka.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;switzerland&#34;&gt;Switzerland&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-04-28 (15587 listings), 2016-08-13 (18901 listings),
2016-10-30 (19775 listings), 2016-11-30 (21043 listings), 2016-12-23
(22104 listings), 2017-01-26 (22506 listings), 2017-02-24 (23195
listings), 2017-04-21 (24992 listings), 2017-05-20 (25674 listings),
2017-06-16 (26398 listings), 2017-07-11 (27696 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/switzerland.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sydney&#34;&gt;Sydney&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2014-09-26 (5567 listings), 2015-01-20 (7424 listings),
2015-03-20 (7871 listings), 2016-01-29 (13134 listings), 2016-06-11
(17343 listings), 2017-01-25 (23859 listings), 2017-03-12 (23297
listings), 2017-04-14 (24006 listings), 2017-05-17 (24419 listings),
2017-06-28 (25266 listings), 2017-07-23 (25506 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/sydney.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tallin&#34;&gt;Tallin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-07-08 (1378 listings), 2016-12-26 (1468 listings),
2017-01-24 (1483 listings), 2017-02-22 (1536 listings), 2017-04-04 (1574
listings), 2017-04-29 (1668 listings), 2017-05-19 (1708 listings),
2017-06-22 (1905 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/tallin.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toronto&#34;&gt;Toronto&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2013-12-14 (2617 listings), 2014-05-18 (2656 listings),
2015-02-18 (4831 listings), 2015-06-29 (6587 listings), 2015-07-25 (6586
listings), 2015-11-21 (7607 listings), 2015-12-13 (7969 listings),
2016-01-15 (7980 listings), 2016-02-16 (8352 listings), 2016-03-17 (8452
listings), 2016-04-13 (9149 listings), 2016-05-18 (9446 listings),
2016-06-17 (9595 listings), 2016-07-16 (10155 listings), 2016-08-18
(10700 listings), 2016-09-15 (11026 listings), 2016-10-17 (11301
listings), 2016-11-20 (11735 listings), 2016-12-17 (12801 listings),
2017-01-14 (12597 listings), 2017-02-16 (12679 listings), 2017-03-12
(12528 listings), 2017-04-08 (12755 listings), 2017-05-05 (13042
listings), 2017-06-09 (13161 listings), 2017-07-10 (13267 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/toronto.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;turin&#34;&gt;Turin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2017-01-11 (3092 listings), 2017-03-13 (3205 listings),
2017-04-14 (3301 listings), 2017-05-18 (3403 listings), 2017-06-28 (3546
listings), 2017-07-24 (3662 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/turin.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tuscany&#34;&gt;Tuscany&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-08-02 (37295 listings), 2016-10-30 (38783 listings),
2017-05-04 (32850 listings), 2017-06-23 (24993 listings), 2017-07-20
(49286 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/tuscany.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;vancouver-bc&#34;&gt;Vancouver BC&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2015-04-25 (3036 listings), 2015-08-22 (3375 listings),
2015-11-26 (4595 listings), 2015-12-15 (4751 listings), 2016-01-17 (4731
listings), 2016-02-19 (4833 listings), 2016-03-20 (4916 listings),
2016-04-17 (5004 listings), 2016-05-20 (5209 listings), 2016-06-19 (5297
listings), 2016-07-18 (5611 listings), 2016-08-20 (5820 listings),
2016-09-17 (5926 listings), 2016-10-20 (5758 listings), 2016-11-22 (5611
listings), 2016-12-23 (5843 listings), 2017-01-14 (5619 listings),
2017-02-16 (5596 listings), 2017-03-13 (5588 listings), 2017-04-08 (5618
listings), 2017-05-05 (5781 listings), 2017-06-10 (5909 listings),
2017-07-10 (5994 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/vancouver_bc.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;veneto&#34;&gt;Veneto&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-11-07 (11543 listings), 2017-01-24 (15153 listings),
2017-01-30 (15218 listings), 2017-02-22 (15508 listings), 2017-03-01
(15743 listings), 2017-04-03 (16300 listings), 2017-04-29 (16940
listings), 2017-05-18 (17148 listings), 2017-06-19 (17915 listings),
2017-07-16 (18455 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/veneto.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;venice&#34;&gt;Venice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2015-12-20 (3161 listings), 2016-11-20 (5323 listings),
2016-12-27 (5727 listings), 2017-01-10 (5773 listings), 2017-01-23 (5801
listings), 2017-02-22 (5955 listings), 2017-04-02 (6120 listings),
2017-04-28 (6404 listings), 2017-05-18 (6402 listings), 2017-06-22 (6410
listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/venice.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;versailles&#34;&gt;Versailles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-09-30 (6003 listings), 2017-03-13 (6052 listings),
2017-04-14 (6271 listings), 2017-05-18 (6515 listings), 2017-06-29 (6756
listings), 2017-07-24 (7175 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/versailles.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;victoria-bc&#34;&gt;Victoria BC&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-07-08 (831 listings), 2016-11-06 (841 listings),
2016-12-10 (899 listings), 2016-12-25 (890 listings), 2017-02-12 (949
listings), 2017-03-11 (950 listings), 2017-04-10 (1004 listings),
2017-05-08 (1026 listings), 2017-06-10 (1063 listings), 2017-07-10 (1093
listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/victoria_bc.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;vienna&#34;&gt;Vienna&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2015-07-24 (5274 listings), 2015-08-01 (5445 listings),
2017-01-11 (7790 listings), 2017-03-13 (7787 listings), 2017-04-15 (7840
listings), 2017-05-18 (8010 listings), 2017-06-29 (8715 listings),
2017-07-25 (9252 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/vienna.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;warsaw&#34;&gt;Warsaw&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-12-08 (3299 listings), 2016-12-14 (3389 listings),
2017-03-13 (3726 listings), 2017-04-15 (3863 listings), 2017-05-18 (4016
listings), 2017-06-29 (4325 listings), 2017-07-25 (4593 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/warsaw.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;washington&#34;&gt;Washington&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2015-01-16 (2815 listings), 2015-08-22 (2800 listings),
2015-10-23 (3843 listings), 2015-11-26 (4081 listings), 2015-12-15 (4257
listings), 2016-01-18 (4245 listings), 2016-02-20 (4304 listings),
2016-03-21 (4290 listings), 2016-04-16 (4512 listings), 2016-05-20 (4756
listings), 2016-06-20 (4738 listings), 2016-07-18 (4960 listings),
2016-08-20 (5104 listings), 2016-09-18 (5186 listings), 2016-10-20 (5297
listings), 2016-11-23 (5975 listings), 2016-12-24 (7497 listings),
2017-01-14 (8885 listings), 2017-01-19 (9097 listings), 2017-02-16 (8475
listings), 2017-03-13 (8232 listings), 2017-04-08 (8061 listings),
2017-05-05 (8115 listings), 2017-05-11 (8085 listings), 2017-06-10 (8174
listings), 2017-07-11 (8237 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/washington.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;wellington&#34;&gt;Wellington&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-08-19 (858 listings), 2016-12-26 (1018 listings),
2017-01-16 (1039 listings), 2017-02-12 (1192 listings), 2017-03-25 (1338
listings), 2017-04-13 (1446 listings), 2017-04-22 (1455 listings),
2017-05-10 (1577 listings), 2017-06-14 (1894 listings), 2017-07-18 (1866
listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/wellington.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;west-indies&#34;&gt;West Indies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-09-28 (39195 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/west_indies.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yellowknife&#34;&gt;Yellowknife&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-09-27 (67 listings), 2016-11-20 (78 listings),
2016-12-26 (84 listings), 2017-02-12 (93 listings), 2017-03-11 (89
listings), 2017-04-10 (83 listings), 2017-05-08 (93 listings),
2017-06-10 (95 listings), 2017-07-10 (88 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/yellowknife.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;york&#34;&gt;York&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-11-21 (551 listings), 2016-11-29 (754 listings),
2016-11-30 (587 listings), 2016-12-04 (495 listings), 2016-12-15 (511
listings), 2017-01-04 (92 listings), 2017-01-18 (496 listings),
2017-02-10 (519 listings), 2017-02-17 (532 listings), 2017-03-27 (545
listings), 2017-04-14 (563 listings), 2017-04-24 (561 listings),
2017-04-21 (607 listings), 2017-05-12 (580 listings), 2017-05-22 (139
listings), 2017-06-15 (617 listings), 2017-07-22 (670 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/york.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;zagreb&#34;&gt;Zagreb&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/zagreb.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip
file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;zurich&#34;&gt;Zurich&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey dates: 2016-01-11 (912 listings), 2017-04-17 (2410 listings),
2017-05-18 (2271 listings), 2017-06-22 (2392 listings)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/tomslee-airbnb-data-2/zurich.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Download zip file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Wide</title>
      <link>https://tomslee.github.io/publication/openwide/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2013 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tomslee.github.io/publication/openwide/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Markdown Reprinted from &lt;a href=&#34;http://thenewinquiry.com/essays/open-wide/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The New Inquiry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In cities and on the Web, distinctive shared spaces attract private capital,
which erodes the very qualities that make them unique&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the earliest days of Linux and of Wikipedia, conflicting attitudes to
profit have co-existed with a commitment to digital sharing. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s
source code, text, artistic works, or government data, some see the open
digital commons as an ethical alternative to corporate production, while
others believe that sharing and profit go together like wine and cheese. And
now, as massively open online courses bring the rhetoric of digital openness
to education and Web-based startups are making it easy to share apartments and
cars and unused parking spaces and jobs, the seeds have been planted for a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.time.com/time/specials/packages/article/0,28804,2059521%5F2059717%5F2059710,00.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;sharing economy&lt;/a&gt; whose flowering is welcomed both by idealists who value
authenticity, sustainability and community sharing over commodity ownership
and by venture capitalists looking to make their next fortune. Strange
bedfellows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cities have long been sites of commons and commerce: full of trade and private
enterprise but shaped by parks and streetscapes, neighborhoods and rhythms of
daily life that grow from non-commodified sharing. In his 2012 book &lt;em&gt;Rebel
Cities&lt;/em&gt;, David Harvey observes how, in cities, &amp;ldquo;people of all sorts and classes
mingle &amp;hellip; to produce a common of perpetually changing and transitory life,&amp;rdquo;
from the irrepressible energy of Manhattan to the café culture of Rome to
Barcelona&amp;rsquo;s distinctive architecture to the symbolic meaning of modern Berlin.
Yes, by 2009, volunteers had spent &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive%5FSurplus&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a hundred million hours&lt;/a&gt; building Wikipedia,
but cities put this dramatic number into perspective: Every year the citizens
of Canada alone volunteer &lt;a href=&#34;http://volunteer.ca/content/about-us&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;roughly 20 Wikipedias&lt;/a&gt; for hospitals and children&amp;rsquo;s
sports, for charities and the arts &amp;mdash; the equivalent of more than a million
full-time jobs in a population of 30 million &amp;mdash; and there is no reason to
believe that the count is complete or that Canada is exceptional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The similarities between urban and digital worlds are not incidental. Both are
cultural spaces, and cultural spaces have always been iceberg-like. Above the
surface, market forces and state interventions; beneath, a mass of
noncommercial activity organized, at least in part, as open commons. But while
digital entrepreneurs look to the &amp;ldquo;Internet&amp;rsquo;s way of working&amp;rdquo; to disrupt the
bricks and mortar of our cities, urban experiences have sober lessons for the
digerati if they will listen: The relationship between commons and commerce is
fraught with contradictions. Harvey never once mentions computer technology in
his book, but his reflections on cities make a compelling case that
money-making and sharing are far from natural allies, and that the role of
openness must be questioned if commons-based production is to be a real
alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economics of culture are those of monopolistic competition. Each and every
cultural work is a unique creation and, like other unique goods, they offers
the prospect of &amp;ldquo;monopoly rents&amp;rdquo; for any who can corner the market on that
work. Open commons are themselves cultural works, and while the tending of
commons is collective and non-commodified by definition, the commons itself is
a magnet for private capital. As Harvey points out, &amp;ldquo;the common, even &amp;mdash; and
particularly &amp;mdash; when it cannot be enclosed, can always be traded upon &amp;hellip; the
ambience and attractiveness of a city &amp;hellip; is a collective product of its
citizens [but] it is the tourist trade that commercially capitalizes upon that
common.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a non-commercial common attracts commercial capital, but is this a problem?
After all, open commons are not scarce resources, prone to depletion like
clean water or ocean fish stocks. Your enjoyment of a city park or a
downloaded song does not hinder me from enjoying the same. What turns the
contradiction into a tragedy is that private capital tends to destroy the
qualities that attracted it in the first place. While commons and commerce can
never be completely disentangled, it is large-scale capital that is most
damaging, and it is the commitment to openness that blocks off ways to prevent
the damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Private capital damages open commons through three mechanisms. It erodes the
common, it alienates the community that tends the common, and distorts the
essential nature of the common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighborhood diversity is an open commons prone to erosion. Harvey writes: &amp;ldquo;A
community group that struggles to maintain ethnic diversity in its
neighborhood and protect against gentrification may suddenly find its property
prices (and taxes) rising as real estate agents market the ‘character&amp;rsquo; of
their neighborhood to the wealthy as multicultural, street-lively, and
diverse. By the time the market has done its destructive work, not only have
the original residents been dispossessed of that common which they had created
(often being forced out by rising rents and property taxes), but the common
itself becomes so debased as to be unrecognizable.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capital homogenizes even as it demands uniqueness. For a global tourist
industry to profit from a city&amp;rsquo;s special qualities it must fit that city into
its worldwide operations. Hotel chains build standardized hotels, charter
companies demand standardized airports, marketing departments seek messages
that resonate around the world. The more distinct a city&amp;rsquo;s culture, the more
pressure to squeeze it into the homogenizing templates of global tourism and
global trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the digital world, sharing-economy sites such as Yelp or TripAdvisor are
built on reputation systems, which are digital commons prone to erosion. The
value of these systems is their trustworthiness, so the work of tending them
must be non-commercial: payments for ratings automatically tarnish the
integrity of the system. But once the reputation commons has become
sufficiently valuable, the temptation for hotel owners, visitors, and others
to game the system for private gain becomes significant. A restaurant rating
placed by a competitor restaurant is not easily identified, and so disputes
proliferate as reputation systems become more widely used. It is up to the
site owners to handle the erosion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, the approach of some &amp;ldquo;sharing economy&amp;rdquo; companies is to ignore the
problem. TripAdvisor CEO Stephen Kaufer &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.economist.com/blogs/gulliver/2010/06/tripadvisor&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dismissed&lt;/a&gt; the issue of reputation
gaming, saying, &amp;ldquo;One or two phony reviews: who gives a shit?&amp;rdquo; Brian Chesky of
apartment rental service AirBnB &lt;a href=&#34;http://skift.com/2013/01/11/airbnb-responds-to-illegal-rentals-story-first-of-all-its-not-illegal-everywhere/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;claims&lt;/a&gt; that when it comes to screening
apartments, &amp;ldquo;It turns out that cities can&amp;rsquo;t screen as well as technologies can
screen. Companies have these magical things called reputation systems.&amp;rdquo; But
reputation systems are not magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of occasional bad reviews is not immediately obvious and varies
from context to context. A few bad outcomes completely break some regimes
(there is a reason the supply of heart surgeons is not governed by open
recommendation systems); for others, such as the entries in Wikipedia,
scattered inaccuracies are less important. Accommodation sites have had their
share of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theatlanticwire.com/technology/2011/08/airbnb-becoming-known-property-damage-meth-and-zero-security/40655/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;damage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://gizmodo.com/5934731/prostitutes-turn-airbnb-apartment-into-brothel&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;misuse&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1205794/Rape-horror-tourist-used-couchsurfing-website-aimed-travellers.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;rape&lt;/a&gt;, but Chesky and Kaufer emphasize the large
number of successful transactions on their systems, gauging their success by
the average user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But incumbent licensing regimes, so disparaged by sharing-economy advocates,
are evaluated differently and with good reason. The severe consequences of
extreme incidents lead, over time, to demands for rules that are stricter than
crowd-based ratings. The value of the system is determined not by the average
but by the worst possible user experience. So far, there is no sign that
sharing-economy sites are taking serious measures to treat the rare calamities
with the central importance they deserve: The commercial incentives of
sharing-economy entrepreneurs make them bad stewards of the reputation-system
commons on which they rely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harvey writes that, in co-opting the uniqueness of an open common, capital
&amp;ldquo;produces widespread alienation and resentment among the cultural producers
who experience first-hand the appropriation and exploitation of their
creativity and their political commitments to the benefits of others.&amp;rdquo; Many
digital commoners have experienced such an alienation moment, a realization
that the common they thought they were tending is, in reality, a private
estate, made green and fertile with voluntary labor and then sold lock, stock,
and barrel to the highest bidder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Woody Guthrie wrote one of the great commons songs: &amp;ldquo;This Land Is Your Land.&amp;rdquo;
After Guthrie&amp;rsquo;s death, his daughter Nora entrusted piles of his previously
unheard lyrics to radical musician Billy Bragg, who put them to music and
turned them into a pair of successful albums in the 1990s. When entrepreneur
Michael Birch was putting together social network Bebo.com in 2006, he reached
out to Bragg, who &amp;mdash; frustrated by the music industry&amp;rsquo;s treatment of
musicians &amp;mdash; gave him advice on how to build an &amp;ldquo;artist-centered
environment.&amp;rdquo; But the two &amp;ldquo;ignored the elephant in the room: the issue of
whether he ought to consider paying some kind of royalties to the artists.&amp;rdquo;
Bebo was to be a common after all, and the tending of commons must be done in
a sharing, non-commodified way. In 2008, Birch sold Bebo.com to AOL, pocketing
an estimated $600 million. The sale led Bragg to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/22/opinion/22bragg.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;write&lt;/a&gt; that &amp;ldquo;if young
musicians are to have a chance of enjoying a fruitful career, then we need to
establish the principle of artists&amp;rsquo; rights throughout the Internet &amp;mdash; and we
need to do it now.&amp;rdquo; This site, it turns out, is not your site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whole online communities have experienced their own similar alienation
moments. Goodreads, a social space for book lovers, was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/blog/show/413-exciting-news-about-goodreads-we-re-joining-the-amazon-family&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;sold to Amazon&lt;/a&gt;,
triggering an angry backlash among members whose voluntary contributions built
much of the site&amp;rsquo;s value. Academic reference manager Mendeley, which long
employed a rhetoric of openness, alienated its user base by &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2013/04/08/a-matter-of-perspective-elsevier-acquires-mendeley-or-mendeley-sells-itself-to-elsevier/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;selling itself&lt;/a&gt; to
Elsevier, a company with a reputation for resisting open-access publication at
every turn. Undeterred, Mendeley still pronounces that its &amp;ldquo;real power lies in
what it does with the collective data from users.&amp;rdquo; Tumblr&amp;rsquo;s owner David Karp
may not be &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cnbc.com/id/100751632&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;about the money&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;rdquo; and the owners of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zipcar.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Zipcar&lt;/a&gt; may believe that their
company is &amp;ldquo;about the people who make it a reality: a team that works hard,
members who believe, and organizations that are making conscious decisions for
the future.&amp;rdquo; Nonetheless, they didn&amp;rsquo;t mind selling out to Yahoo and Avis,
respectively, and alienating their commoners when the price was right. Early
collaborative sites like IMDB (another property of Amazon) and CDDB (now owned
by Sony Corporation) also turned out to be not commons but private estates,
tended by sharecroppers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Techno-optimists tend to credit technology alone for fostering digital commons
and downplay the nontechnical work of many commoners. In his book Cognitive
Surplus, Clay Shirky highlighted &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.couchsurfing.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Couchsurfing&lt;/a&gt;, a site where young global
travelers can arrange to visit and host each other, as a healthy digital
commons. Couchsurfing started life as couchsurfing.org, not couchsurfing.com;
even the code that ran the site was provided by the Couchsurfers themselves.
But the site did have owners, and in August 2011, they &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.triplepundit.com/2011/09/couchsurfing-corporation-bona-fide-bogus/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;incorporated&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.crunchbase.com/company/couchsurfing-international&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;accepted&lt;/a&gt; $7.6 million in venture funding. As the company&amp;rsquo;s market value has
grown, the Couchsurfing community has deteriorated. A long-time Couchsurfer
&lt;a href=&#34;http://nithincoca.com/2013/03/27/the-rise-and-fall-of-couchsurfing/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;laments&lt;/a&gt; the days of &amp;ldquo;art gatherings, bonfires, a weekly meet up at a bar, café
gatherings, potlucks,&amp;rdquo; now lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The community&amp;rsquo;s former strength turned out to have little to do with
technology. As a commenter at Quora &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quora.com/CouchSurfing/What-is-happening-to-Couchsurfing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The old Couchsurfing thrived with a very haphazard and underfunded management
structure precisely because local volunteers around the world believed they
were part of a cause bigger than profit. Local collectives were highly tied to
their local communities &amp;hellip; The technical architecture of the new systems is
much better, but paradoxically the ‘professional&amp;rsquo; product development process
fixes things that were broken on purpose. In other words, Couchsurfing evolved
around certain quirks and inefficient processes that actually became critical
to the health of the social trust platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 5000 Couchsurfing members have joined the forum &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.couchsurfing.org/group.html?gid=45507&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;We are Against CS
becoming a for-profit corporation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrast Couchsurfing with Hostelling International, a venerable network of
national youth hostelling organizations that has remained resolutely
nonprofit. Over 100 years old, it is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hihostels.com/pdf/HistoryPhilosophy.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;still going strong&lt;/a&gt; and &amp;ldquo;currently
provides 35 million overnight stays a year through more than 4,000 hostels in
over 80 countries.&amp;rdquo; Some people do support themselves through the commons of
hostels &amp;mdash; some work in the hosteling organizations, others are paid to run
hostels themselves &amp;mdash; but it&amp;rsquo;s orders of magnitude away from the sudden
injection of millions of venture-capital dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As capital is attracted to a successful common, so the nature of the common
itself becomes a matter for dispute. In his analysis of cities, Harvey turns
again to conflict between the tourist industry and residents over the shared
meaning of an urban space: &amp;ldquo;The initial erasure of all mention of the slave
trade in the reconstruction of Albert Dock in Liverpool generated protests on
the part of the excluded population of Caribbean background.&amp;rdquo; Similarly, after
reunification, Berliners were caught between the frying pan of a globalized
aesthetic (the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://habitusmag.com/2011/08/3841/the-disneyfication-of-the-berlin-wall/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Disneyfication of the Berlin Wall&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;) and the fire of a
&amp;ldquo;parochial nationalism,&amp;rdquo; with the potential for &amp;ldquo;a virulent rejection of
foreigners and immigrants.&amp;rdquo; Capital, Harvey argues, wades into the culture
wars to pursue the monopoly rents at stake in commons, making &amp;ldquo;interventions
in the field of culture, history, heritage, aesthetics, and meanings.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital commons are subject to similar distortions. The nature of Linux, which
famously started as an amateur hobby project, has been changed by the private
capital it attracted. Independent contributors now &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theregister.co.uk/2013/04/17/state%5Fof%5Flinux%5F2013/make&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;make&lt;/a&gt; fewer than 12% of the
changes to the kernel; the bulk of the changes come from developers employed
in the hundreds of corporations that build businesses on the Linux commons. In
an &lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/yVpbFMhOAwE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;introductory video&lt;/a&gt;, the Linux Foundation explicitly acknowledges the
corporatization of the effort, explaining that Linux is &amp;ldquo;built
collaboratively, across companies, geographies, and markets.&amp;rdquo; Reflecting this
shift, the operating system is no longer primarily for individual users who
wish to control their computing environment. Instead, its major uses are in
consumer electronics products (including phones), enterprise data centers,
financial trading systems, and the massive data centers of the Web 2.0 giants
such as Amazon, Google, and Facebook. Once a challenger to capitalist modes of
production, Linux is now an integral part of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So capital erodes, alienates, and distorts efforts to build value on
non-commodified sharing, and openness demands that capital is given unfettered
access to the commons. Are digital commons and urban commons doomed to feed
the hand that bites them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps not. Among all the contradictions of the commons, Harvey identifies
one that provides grounds for hope. The search for monopoly rents on commons
&amp;ldquo;leads global capital to value local initiatives &amp;mdash; indeed, in certain
respects, the more distinctive and, in these times, the more transgressive the
initiative, the better &amp;hellip; It can even support (though cautiously and often
nervously) transgressive cultural practices because this is one way in which
to be original, creative, and authentic, as well as unique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capital cannot afford to eliminate the uniqueness of a particular commons
entirely. Harvey argues that this contradiction provides an opportunity for
radical movements to build around urban commons, that the urban commons can
still be &amp;ldquo;spaces of hope for the construction of &amp;hellip; a vibrant
anti-commodification politics: one in which the progressive forces of cultural
production and transformation can seek to appropriate and undermine the forces
of capital rather than the other way round.&amp;rdquo; Some would see the eruption of
protest in Turkey, sparked by the redevelopment of a park near Istanbul&amp;rsquo;s
Taksim Square, as an example of such politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the digital world, limiting openness is one way to restrict the
encroachment of capital and to maintain digital commons as alternative spaces.
Like urban commons, digital commons can be spaces of hope, but only if the
contradictory relationship between commons and commerce is acknowledged and
addressed, if the destructive influence of capital can be limited, and if some
of the accepted wisdom around digital commons is challenged &amp;mdash; including the
unquestioning acceptance of &amp;ldquo;openness&amp;rdquo; as a virtue.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
